People talk a lot about passive income.
人们经常谈论被动收入。
This
这
&gt;&gt; is not a thing. Look, there's two ways
不存在。你看，有两种方法
to get wealthier, and passive income is
要想变得更富有，被动收入是……
not part of that equation, but what's
不属于那个等式，但那是什么呢？
really important for people is how we
对人们来说，真正重要的是我们如何
should spend money. Cuz I've written
应该花钱。因为我写过
about money and finance and investing
关于金钱、金融和投资
for 20 [music] years, and I can tell you
我从事音乐行业20年了，我可以告诉你
the correlation between how much you
你拥有多少与你的相关性
spend and how happy you are. It can
消费以及你的幸福感。它可以
exist, but it is not as simple as you
存在，但并不像你想象的那么简单。
think. Morgan Hel is the legendary
思考。摩根·赫尔是传奇人物
financial guru,
金融专家
&gt;&gt; revealing that everything we've been
揭示了我们一直以来所经历的一切
told about saving and spending money
讲述了储蓄和消费之道
&gt;&gt; could be our biggest downfall. [music]
这可能是我们最大的败笔。 [音乐]
And here's why. If you're unhappy with
原因如下。如果您对以下方面不满意
your life, it is a very easy assumption
你的人生，这是一个很容易理解的假设。
to make that if you had more money, a
如果你有更多钱，就能做到这一点。
bigger house, a better car, or whatever
更大的房子、更好的车，或者其他什么
it might be, things would be better. And
或许情况会好转。和
it's a lie we tell ourselves, of course,
当然，这是我们对自己撒的谎。
because here's the truth. So much of
因为这就是真相。很多
spending is a psychological itch that
消费是一种心理上的渴望，
you're trying to scratch. And that
你在试图挠痒。而那
manifests in so many different ways. For
它以多种不同的方式表现出来。为了
example, life is a competition. It
例如，人生就是一场竞争。它
doesn't matter how well I'm doing, it
我做得好不好并不重要，
matters how well I'm doing relative to
我的表现相对于其他人来说有多好，这很重要。
you. And the most [music] tangible way
你。而最切实可行的音乐方式
to do that is through material stuff.
实现这一目标需要通过物质手段。
&gt;&gt; I was reading some funny stats. They say
我当时在看一些有趣的统计数据。他们说
that if you win the lottery, the
如果你中了彩票，
probability of your neighbor going
你的邻居去
bankrupt [music] increases.
破产音乐增加。
&gt;&gt; It's an amazing statistic. So, be
这是一个惊人的统计数据。所以，要……
careful who you socialize with because
要谨慎选择社交对象，因为
you're going to anchor to them as a
你要把它们作为锚点。
baseline level of success and happiness.
成功和幸福的基准水平。
&gt;&gt; So, is it wrong to buy a Rolex?
那么，买劳力士手表错了吗？
&gt;&gt; Absolutely not. But when it's
绝对不是。但当它是
controlling your personality, it's no
控制你的个性，这并非易事。
different than any other addiction where
与其他任何成瘾症都不同，
it's forcing you to do things that you
它迫使你去做你不想做的事情
otherwise don't want to do.
否则就不想做。
&gt;&gt; What about people who don't seem to
那么那些似乎没有……的人呢？
spend anything?
花什么钱？
&gt;&gt; It's just as dangerous. [music] Like
它同样危险。 [音乐] 喜欢
there's something called post-traumatic
有一种东西叫做创伤后应激障碍。
broke syndrome and I'll talk about that.
破产综合症，我会谈谈这个。
But I guarantee you that everyone can
但我保证每个人都能
spend money in a way it's going to make
花钱要以能带来收益的方式进行。
them happier.
他们更快乐了。
&gt;&gt; So if I wanted to make a framework to
所以如果我想创建一个框架
know how to spend my money, where do I
知道如何花钱，我应该去哪里花钱
start? But also based on everything you
开始？但也要基于你的一切
know about money, if I want to get
了解金钱，如果我想获得
complete financial freedom, what's the
完全的财务自由，是什么？
five things that I should be thinking
我应该思考的五件事
about?
关于？
&gt;&gt; The first thing that I think that's most
我认为最重要的第一点是
important is
重要的是
&gt;&gt; I see messages all the time in the
我经常在……中看到消息
comment section that some of you didn't
评论区里有些人没有
realize you didn't subscribe. So, if you
意识到你没有订阅。所以，如果你
could do me a favor and double check if
能不能帮我个忙，再确认一下？
you're a subscriber to this channel,
您是本频道的订阅者，
that would be tremendously appreciated.
非常感谢。
It's the simple, it's the free thing
它很简单，而且是免费的。
that anybody that watches this show
任何观看这档节目的人
frequently can do to help us here to
通常情况下，他们可以在这里帮助我们。
keep everything going in this show in
让这个节目继续下去
the trajectory it's on. So, please do
它所处的轨迹。所以，请务必这样做。
double check if you've subscribed and uh
请再次确认您是否已订阅，呃……
thank you so much because a strange way
非常感谢，因为这是一种奇怪的方式
you are you're part of our history and
你是我们历史的一部分，
you're on this journey with us and I
你和我们一起踏上这段旅程，而我
appreciate you for that. So, yeah, thank
谢谢你。是的，谢谢
you [music]
你[音乐]
Morgan.
摩根。
Everybody loves to talk about investing.
每个人都喜欢谈论投资。
They love to talk about saving money.
他们喜欢谈论省钱。
But I've never heard anybody emphasize
但我从未听人强调过这一点。
the importance of spending money. You've
花钱的重要性。你已经
written this book, The Art of Spending.
写了这本书，《消费的艺术》。
So, it begs the question, why would
所以，这就引出了一个问题，为什么会这样？
someone like you who sells tens of
像你这样卖出几十个的人
millions of copies of their books when
他们的书籍销量达数百万册
they write about something and really,
他们写一些东西，而且真的，
really cares about the art of writing
非常关心写作艺术
commit themselves to writing a book
他们致力于写一本书。
about the art of spending? when you
关于消费的艺术？当你
couldn't when you could have written
当你本可以写的时候却没能写出来。
anything that you wanted to and it would
任何你想做的事，它都会
have been a success.
已经取得了成功。
&gt;&gt; So I've written about money and finance
所以我写过关于金钱和金融的文章。
and investing for 20 years and almost
投资了20年，几乎
never had I myself
我从未有过这样的经历。
said what is my spending philosophy? I
我问：我的消费理念是什么？我
could tell you how I invest. I can tell
我可以告诉你我是如何投资的。我看得出来
you how I save. I could tell you why I
告诉我我是如何省钱的。我可以告诉你为什么我
do those things. If five years ago if
去做那些事。如果五年前如果
you said Morgan tell me your philosophy
你说摩根，告诉我你的哲学
about spending in your own life I'd be
关于如何支配自己的生活，我会是
like I I don't really know. And as I
我真的不知道。而当我
looked into it, there are literally tens
我调查了一下，确实有几十个。
of thousands of books on how to invest,
数以千计的关于如何投资的书籍，
how to grow your money, how to get rich,
如何让你的钱增值，如何致富，
how to help your career. That top that
如何助力你的职业发展。那件上衣
topic is endless. There is virtually no
话题无穷无尽。几乎没有
book out there written about spending
市面上有一本关于消费的书。
money. And I think the reason why is
钱。我认为原因在于……
because we don't I think we intuitively
因为我们没有，我认为我们凭直觉……
think nothing needs to be said because
我觉得没什么好说的，因为
the answer should be obvious. More is
答案显而易见。更多是
better, fancier is better. That's the
更好，越精致越好。那就是
end of the topic. But if you know
话题结束。但如果你知道
particularly wealthier people, I mean it
尤其是比较富裕的人，我的意思是。
affects everybody, but particularly
影响所有人，但尤其如此。
wealthier people, you know, it's not
你知道，对于富裕的人来说，情况并非如此。
that simple. That the correlation
就这么简单。相关性
between how much you spend and how happy
消费多少和快乐程度之间有关系。
you are, it it can exist. Everyone can
你存在，它就能存在。人人都可以
spend money in a way it's going to make
花钱要以能带来收益的方式进行。
them happier, but it is not as simple as
让他们更快乐，但这并不像看起来那么简单。
you think. And as I started digging into
您认为。当我开始深入研究时
it in my own life of when have I been
在我的人生中，我何时经历过这种情况？
envious of other people, of their
嫉妒他人，嫉妒他们的
material possessions, why was I envious?
物质财富，我为什么会嫉妒？
Why when have I been jealous? Why was I
我什么时候嫉妒过别人？为什么是我
jealous? What kind of spending made me
嫉妒的？什么样的消费让我
happy? What left me completely flat?
快乐的？什么让我彻底泄气了？
It's it's a much more complicated topic
这是一个复杂得多的话题。
than it seems at the surface. You know,
比表面看起来更复杂。你知道，
another title for the book could have
这本书的另一个书名可能是
been the psychology of spending money
一直是消费心理
because that's what this is. So, to look
因为这就是它的本质。所以，要看
at the psychology of greed and envy and
贪婪和嫉妒的心理学
social aspiration and like climbing the
社会抱负和攀登
social ladder, who you're trying to
社会阶梯，你试图……
impress, whether those people are paying
给人留下深刻印象，无论这些人是否付费。
any attention to you, that's what this
任何对你关注的事情，就是这个
book is. So for someone like me who
这本书是。所以对于像我这样的人来说
wants to improve my relationship with
想改善我与……的关系
spending, I guess the question, yeah, I
花钱，我想这个问题，是的，我
guess the qu first question is
猜猜第一个问题是
understanding the art of spending money,
懂得花钱的艺术
simple choices for a rich, what is it
富人的简单选择是什么？
going to do for me? How is it going to
你会为我做什么？将会如何？
make my life better to understand this?
理解这一点能让我的生活变得更好吗？
Why why does it matter to the person
为什么这对这个人很重要？
that's listening right now?
现在正在收听的是谁？
&gt;&gt; I think it is a very easy assumption to
我认为这是一个很容易理解的假设。
make if you're unhappy with your life
如果你对自己的生活不满意，那就去做吧
that if you had more money, those
如果你有更多的钱，那些
problems would go away.
问题就会消失。
&gt;&gt; Sometimes it can be true. It's not
有时确实如此。它不是
automatically false. It's just easier to
自动判定为假。这样做更容易
assume that that's true than it actually
假设这是真的，那么实际上
is. And so I guarantee you that every
是。所以我向你保证，每一个
single person listening to this right
单身人士正在收听此内容
now has some degree of that. If I had a
现在在某种程度上已经具备了这种特征。如果我有一个
little bit more money, my problems would
如果再多一点钱，我的问题就会迎刃而解。
go away. Even if they don't necessarily
离开。即使他们不一定
know it or not. So much of spending is a
知道与否都无所谓。消费中很大一部分是
psychological exercise. There's an itch
心理训练。痒。
that you're trying to scratch and that
你试图挠痒痒，而且
manifests in so many different ways. And
它以多种不同的方式表现出来。和
so I've often thought of money, look, is
所以我经常会想到钱，你看，是
money the root of society, the core of
金钱是社会的根基，是社会的核心。
society? No. There's obviously a million
社会？不，显然有一百万个。
things more important than money, but I
比金钱更重要的事，但我
do think it's the clearest window that
我认为这是最清晰的窗户。
we can look through to try to figure out
我们可以仔细查看，试图找出答案。
what's going on in our own lives, in
我们自己的生活中正在发生什么，在
other people's lives, in society. It
在社会中，其他人的生活。它
shows very starkly what people value,
这非常鲜明地展现了人们的价值观，
what they're scared of, what they're
他们害怕什么，他们是什么
aspiring to become. There are many more
渴望成为。还有很多。
elements to the puzzle. Your health,
拼图的组成部分。你的健康，
your friends, your family. We can go on
你的朋友，你的家人。我们可以继续
that forever. But money is a very clear
永远如此。但金钱是一个非常明确的问题。
window that if you see how somebody
透过那扇窗户，你可以看到某人是如何做的
engages with money, you're like, "Oh, I
谈到金钱，你会想，“哦，我
understand your insecurities. I
了解你的不安全感。我
understand your aspirations. I
了解你的抱负。我
understand your self-confidence. I
了解你的自信。我
understand what you think of other
了解你对其他人的看法
people. But the point is that it's a
人们。但重点是，这是一个
psychological itch. It It's not just I
心理上的渴望。这不仅仅是我
want the nice car because nice cars are
想要好车，因为好车
better. There's a social signaling.
更好的。这是一种社会信号传递。
You're signaling to others. You're
你在向他人发出信号。你是
signing to yourself. It's a trophy for
对自己签名。这是一座奖杯
yourself of what you've overcome. The
想想你已经克服了什么。这
more I dug into it, the more it was so
我越深入研究，就越觉得……
clear of like spending is not just on
清楚地认识到，消费不仅仅局限于此。
material stuff. It's not just I want to
物质的东西。不仅仅是我想
buy this car or this house or these
买这辆车、这栋房子或这些
clothes or these jewelry because it's
衣服或这些珠宝，因为它们是
nice. It's I'm trying to send a signal
好的。我正试图发送一个信号
to others or to myself of what I've
无论是对别人还是对我自己，我所拥有的
overcome. One of the ways I thought
克服。我思考的方式之一
about this in my own life was if I was
关于我自己的人生经历，就好像我是……
on a deserted island with maybe just
在一个荒岛上，或许只有
just me and and my family, nobody could
只有我和我的家人，没有人能……
see how we were living. Nobody can see
看看我们以前的生活状况。谁也看不见
your house, nobody can see your car,
你的房子里，没人能看到你的车。
nobody can see your clothes, nobody can
没人能看到你的衣服，没人能
see your jewelry. How would I live? For
看看你的珠宝。我会如何生活？为了
me, and I think most people in that
我，而且我认为大多数人都是这样。
exercise, you immediately gravitate away
运动时，你会立刻远离运动。
from status and towards utility. Like I
从地位转向实用性。就像我
would not want a Lamborghini. I probably
我不想买兰博基尼。我可能
want like a pickup truck, something that
想要一辆像皮卡那样的车，那种
has like more utility. If nobody could
更像是实用工具。如果没人能
see it, I would just want utility. I
我觉得，我只想要实用性。我
would not want an enormous house. I
我不想住很大的房子。我
would want a house with a nice view
想要一栋视野开阔的房子
because I'm not trying to show off to
因为我并不是想炫耀。
other people. I just want something that
别人。我只是想要一些……
is calming and and serene to myself. And
让我感到平静和安宁。和
so once you start seeing the stark
所以一旦你开始看到鲜明的
difference between utility and status
效用与地位的区别
once you once you force yourself to see
一旦你强迫自己去看
it, you're like, "Oh, it's everywhere."
你会觉得，“哦，它无处不在。”
&gt;&gt; Is something inherently wrong with
是否存在本质上的问题？
status? Is it wrong to buy a Rolex?
地位？买劳力士手表错了吗？
&gt;&gt; Absolutely not. Particularly at certain
绝对不是。尤其是在某些情况下
points of your life.
你生命中的重要时刻。
&gt;&gt; Okay. So, when when is it good? When is
好的。那么，什么时候才算合适呢？何时
it bad? When is it indifferent? Like
情况很糟糕吗？什么时候才算漠不关心？喜欢
indifferent?
冷漠？
&gt;&gt; I don't know. I don't know. It's hard to
我不知道。我不知道。很难
say what's good and bad in terms of a
就此而言，说说什么是好什么是坏
formula because everybody's different.
因为每个人都不一样，所以只能用公式来表示。
But I would say this.
但我想说的是……
&gt;&gt; My own personal desire to show off
我个人的炫耀欲望
materially
重大
happened when I was in my late teens,
这件事发生在我十几岁末期，
early 20s. And looking back, I didn't
二十出头。回想起来，我并没有
know this then, but the reason why is
当时你就知道这一点，但原因在于……
because I had nothing else to offer the
因为我别无他物可以奉献
world. I had no intelligence. I had no
世界。我当时智力低下。我没有
wisdom. I didn't know how to love
智慧。我不知道如何去爱
anyone. I had nothing else to offer
任何人。我别无他法。
friends, family, spouses, whatever it
朋友、家人、配偶，无论是什么
would be. And so the last remaining
将会是。所以，最后剩下的
lever if you're trying to get attention
如果你想引起注意，就用杠杆。
and respect is well look I have no
尊重嘛，你看，我没有
intelligence to offer. I have no wisdom
可提供的情报。我没有智慧
to offer. Maybe people will admire me
提供。或许人们会欣赏我。
for my car.
给我的车用的。
&gt;&gt; That was why I wanted it.
这就是我想要它的原因。
&gt;&gt; And now that I I hope
现在我希望
&gt;&gt; in a in I I hope to today 20 years later
我希望今天20年后
I have a little bit more to offer to my
我还能为我的……贡献更多。
wife to my friends to my family to
对我的朋友和家人来说，妻子
employers and customers whatot then my
雇主和客户，然后呢？
desire for those things has gone down.
对这些东西的需求下降了。
Not to zero but it's gone down. There's
虽然没有降到零，但已经下降了。有
a great Warren Buffett quote where he
沃伦·巴菲特的一句名言
says, "Success in life is when the
他说：“人生成功就是……”
people who you want to love you do love
你想爱的人，你最终都会爱上。
you." And key to that is like you have
你。”而关键在于，就像你拥有……
to ask the question like, "Who do you
问这样的问题：“你是谁？”
want to love you?" And for a lot of
想爱你吗？对于很多人来说
people, the quick knee-jerk reaction is
人们的快速本能反应是
everybody. And so you want to have a
所有人。所以你想拥有一个
nice car, nice clothes, nice jewelry
好车，好衣服，好首饰
because you think everyone's going to
因为你认为每个人都会
stop and stare. When I drive this down
停下来凝视。当我开车经过这里时
the road, people are going to be stop
这条路，人们将会停下来
and say, "Look at that guy. Look, look
然后说：“看那家伙。看，看。”
at her. That's amaz
对着她。太棒了！
I admire them. I respect them. And by
我敬佩他们。我尊重他们。并且通过
and large, that is almost never true
而大面积的这种情况，几乎从未发生过。
because no one's thinking about you as
因为没人会把你当成……
much as you are. They're not they're not
就像你一样。他们不是，他们不是
paying attention to your car or your
集中注意力在你的车或你的
clothes or your house. They're busy
衣服或房子。他们很忙。
worrying about themselves.
他们只关心自己。
&gt;&gt; Jimmy Carr, who I think you've had on
吉米·卡尔，我想你们之前请过他。
the show before. Is that right?
上一期节目。是这样吗？
&gt;&gt; Love [clears throat] Jimmy Carr. He said
爱[清嗓子]吉米·卡尔。他说
this a couple weeks ago. I heard it and
这是几周前的事了。我听到了，
it was one of those I had to stop and
那是我不得不停下来的一次机会，
write it down because it was so
写下来，因为它太……
profound. He said, "In your 20s, people
深刻的。他说：“在你二十多岁的时候，人们
worry about what other people think of
担心别人怎么看你
them. In your 30s, you say, "I don't
他们。到了三十多岁，你会说：“我不……”
care what anybody thinks of me." And in
我不在乎别人怎么看我。”
your 40s, you finally realize a truth,
到了四十岁，你终于明白了一个道理。
which was nobody was thinking about you
也就是说，没人会想到你。
the whole time. They were busy worrying
一直如此。他们忙着担心
about themselves. And look, that's not
关于他们自己。你看，那不是
black and white. Of course, people think
黑白的。当然，人们会这么想。
about you and look at you and sometimes
关于你，看看你，有时
judge you, but not nearly to the extent
我会评判你，但远没有到那种程度。
that we think. And that was why I get
我们认为。这就是我明白的原因
back to the exercise. If nobody was
回到练习。如果没有人
watching, how would I live? The truth is
看着这一切，我该如何生活？事实是
because virtually nobody is watching
因为几乎没人看
except the people who I really love and
除了我真正爱的人之外，
admire. and they're gonna admire me for
钦佩。他们会因此而敬佩我。
things that have nothing to do with the
与此无关的事情
kind of car that I drive or the clothes
我开的车或者我的衣服
that I wear.
我穿的。
&gt;&gt; What's the the evolutionary basis for
进化基础是什么？
all of this stuff?
所有这些东西？
&gt;&gt; Life's a competition. It doesn't matter
人生就是一场竞赛。没关系
how well I'm doing. It matters how well
我做得怎么样？效果好坏很重要。
I'm doing relative to you. It doesn't
我这样做是相对于你的。它不
matter how big my house is. If I'm
无论我的房子有多大。如果我是
trying to signal, all that matters is my
试图发出信号，但所有重要的都是我的
house is bigger than yours. That's true
这房子比你的大。这是真的
for all wealth. There's no such thing as
为了所有财富。根本不存在这种事
you are wealthy once you have x number
当你拥有 x 个数字时，你就富有了。
of dollars. That that does not exist.
美元。那并不存在。
Everything is relative to other people.
一切都是相对的。
And the truth is like we live in a world
而事实是，我们生活在一个这样的世界里。
of such material abundance where the
如此丰富的物质资源，其中
majority of people listening this will
大多数听众会
have some sort of shelter and a car and
有住处和一辆车，
and can buy can buy clothes and whatnot.
而且可以买衣服之类的东西。
And because relative to a lot of
而且相对于很多……
history, we live in material abundance.
从历史的角度来看，我们生活在一个物质丰富的时代。
The competition the arms race for bigger
争夺更大军备的竞争
nicer things is extraordinary. And it's
美好的事物非同凡响。而且是
way more powerful and potent today than
如今它比以前强大得多，效力也强得多。
it's ever been for two reasons. One is
原因始终有两个。一是
social media. So I am now aware of the
社交媒体。所以我现在知道了
homes that other people live in. the
其他人居住的房屋。
cars that they drive, the clothes that
他们开的车，他们穿的衣服
the vacations that they take. I'm now
他们去度假。我现在
aware of it in a way that we were not 15
我们对此的了解程度，与我们15岁时的认知程度不同。
years ago. The other thing is because
几年前。另一件事是因为
the internet has democratized
互联网使民主化
access to audience and attention. The
获得观众和关注的机会。这
ability to become extremely rich is much
拥有变得极其富有的能力是很大的
more powerful than it's ever been. It's
比以往任何时候都更加强大。它是
still rare, of course, but it's it's
当然，这种情况仍然很少见，但它确实存在。
easier today than it's ever been to
如今比以往任何时候都更容易。
become very very wealthy, even if only a
即使只有
small number of people are doing it
少数人这样做
because your your potential customer
因为你是你的潜在客户
base is now the entire world. You know,
基地现在就是整个世界。你知道，
a 100 years ago, if I was a businessman,
一百年前，如果我是个商人，
my customer base was whoever lived in my
我的客户群就是住在我所在地区的所有人。
town.
镇。
&gt;&gt; Now, if you're a [clears throat]
现在，如果你是[清嗓子]
businessman, your customer base can be
商人，您的客户群可能
the entire world. And so, it's easier to
全世界。因此，更容易
make a huge fortune. And because of
发大财。正因为
social media, once you make that
社交媒体，一旦你做到了这一点
fortune, people are probably going to
运气好的话，人们可能会……
know about it because a lot of those
我知道这一点，因为很多那些
people who become very rich are going to
那些变得非常富有的人将会
say, "Look at how I'm living." And so,
说：“看看我的生活。”所以，
you have this like trickle down
这就像是涓滴效应一样。
aspiration of everyone else being like,
希望其他人都能像我一样，
"My definition of wealthy, if you're a
“我对富有的定义是，如果你是一个……”
young person today,
当今的年轻人
&gt;&gt; a young person's definition of wealthy
年轻人对富有的定义
might be a multi-billionaire with a
可能是一位拥有……的亿万富翁
private jet and a private island." where
私人飞机和私人岛屿。”
I think 80 years ago people's definition
我认为80年前人们对……的定义
of wealthy was a three-bedroom house and
富裕人家拥有一栋三居室的房子，
one car and and a and and a happy
一辆车，还有，还有，还有快乐
family. And so we live in a world where
家庭。因此，我们生活在一个这样的世界里
like aspirations have inflated by such a
就像这样的抱负被膨胀了一样
dramatic degree that the arms race of
军备竞赛的程度非常显著
spending just gets that much that much
消费就是这样，不知不觉就变得如此之多。
higher. I think there's something in
更高。我觉得这里面肯定有猫腻。
this idea that you almost have to
你几乎不得不这样想
develop the skill of disconnecting your
培养断开连接的能力
admiration from your aspirations if you
如果你的抱负能让你赢得钦佩，那就太好了。
want to live a good life because so many
想要过上美好的生活，因为有太多……
kids will like look up to you and say I
孩子们会仰慕你，并说“我
want to be like Morgan when I'm older um
我希望长大后能像摩根那样。
because they admire what you've done but
因为他们钦佩你所做的一切，但是
the reality is they they're just seeing
现实情况是，他们只是看到了而已。
the sort of shop window yeah
那种橱窗，嗯。
&gt;&gt; of your life and so I people do this
你的生活，所以我人们会这样做
with Elon all the time
一直和埃隆在一起
&gt;&gt; right and Elon has even said he's like
没错，埃隆甚至说过他就像……
you might think you want to be me but
你或许认为你想成为我，但
you you don't
你不
&gt;&gt; and he the clip where he did that he
还有他做那件事的视频片段
points his head and he's It's a it's a
他指着头说：“这是……这是……”
tornado up here.
这里出现了龙卷风。
&gt;&gt; And I think it's true that for most
我认为这对大多数人来说确实如此。
people who are extremely successful,
那些非常成功的人，
&gt;&gt; who are the ones that people tend to to
人们往往会关注哪些人？
look up to, like the extreme outlier
仰望，就像极端的异类
successes, a lot of the reason they're
成功的原因有很多，其中很多都是他们成功的原因。
so successful financially and in their
他们在经济上和事业上都取得了成功
career is because they've devoted every
他们之所以能取得今天的成就，是因为他们全身心投入了每一件事。
second of their life to that career,
他们将生命中的第二部分奉献给了那份事业。
&gt;&gt; which most of the time comes at the
这种情况大多发生在……
expense of everything else. So they are
其他一切费用。所以他们是
very successful, made a lot of money,
非常成功，赚了很多钱。
and that came at the expense of their
而这却以他们的利益为代价。
health, their relationships,
健康、人际关系、
relationships with their their spouses,
他们与配偶的关系，
their children. So I make the point in
他们的孩子。所以我把这一点表达出来
the book that of the top 10 richest men
这本书讲述了全球十大最富有的男人们的故事。
in the world there are a cumulative 13
世界上共有13个
divorces among the top 10 richest people
十大富豪中的离婚率
and it's a small sample size like you
而且样本量很小，就像你一样。
can't really you know say that that that
你不能真的这么说吧。
much with that but this is a group that
虽然有很多这样的例子，但这是一个……
is almost universally admired
几乎受到所有人的赞赏
particularly among young men you know
尤其是在你认识的年轻人当中。
Elon Musk Jeff Bezos Mark Zuckerberg how
埃隆·马斯克、杰夫·贝佐斯、马克·扎克伯格如何
how amazing would it be to have that
如果能拥有它该有多棒啊！
much money but if you dig into their
很多钱，但如果你深入了解他们的
actual their the the whole life
实际上，他们的整个生活
&gt;&gt; not just their net worth not just the
不仅仅是他们的净资产，不仅仅是
house and the jet that they have but if
他们有房子和私人飞机，但是如果
you look at holistically their entire
你从整体上看待他们的全部
life, you're like, I don't know. It's
生活啊，你就会想，我不知道。它是
it's it's it's not that great. It's it's
其实，其实，其实没那么好。是它的
one thing to admire someone if you can
如果可以的话，欣赏某人的一件事
pick bits and pieces. I want I want his
零零碎碎地捡起来。我想要，我想要他的
house and her car and his career and his
房子、她的车、他的事业以及他的
physique, but you can't pick bits and
体格，但你不能挑剔局部和
pieces. You have to take the whole
件。你必须接受全部
thing. And once you take the whole
事物。一旦你把整个
thing, you realize that like a lot of
你会意识到，很多事情都是如此。
the people who you may have been looking
你可能一直在寻找的人
up to either did not have a better life
要么他们没有过上更好的生活。
than you did or it was just marginally
比你做得好，或者只是略好一些。
better in a way that was easy to
以一种易于实现的方式变得更好
overlook. I had this conversation with a
俯瞰。我和某人进行了这次谈话
girl in New York last week. I was at a
上周在纽约遇到的一个女孩。我当时在
shoot, a client, like a brand shoot, and
拍摄，客户，比如品牌拍摄，以及
she sat me down to interview me for Tik
她让我坐下，准备就 Tik 一事对我进行采访。
Tok. And she said, um, she goes, "What
托克。然后她说，嗯，她接着说，“什么
age did you become a millionaire?" And I
你多大年纪成为百万富翁的？”还有我
said, "About 24, 25." And she went, "Oh,
他说：“大约24、25。”她接着说：“哦，
I'm 24, 25 now, and I'm not a
我现在24、25岁了，我不是……
millionaire." And I remember saying to
“百万富翁。”我还记得我曾对他说过
her, I was like, "Yeah, but would you
我当时就跟她说：“是啊，但是你愿意吗？”
would you take my trade?"
你愿意接受我的交易吗？
&gt;&gt; And I explained to her, I was like, "So,
我向她解释说，我当时是这样的：“所以，
I was lonely between the age of 18 and
18岁到19岁之间，我一直感到孤独。
roughly 20. I was working in call
大约20岁。我当时在电话客服部门工作。
centers. my parents wouldn't speak to
中心。我的父母不愿与我说话
me. So I had no contact with my family
我。所以我与家人没有任何联系。
really um for through that period. And
确实，在那段时间里。和
then I started shoplifting at about 18
然后我大概18岁的时候开始偷东西。
19 to feed myself. And my brother had
19岁，为了养活自己。我哥哥有
given me this big um sort of industrial
给了我这种巨大的、嗯……工业方面的感受。
packet of oats. And what I had to do is
一包燕麦片。而我必须做的是……
it's like powder. I mixed the powder
它像粉末一样。我把粉末混合在一起。
with water. And there's there's there's
与水。还有，还有，还有
a photo online I think from my previous
网上有一张照片，我觉得是我以前拍的。
TED talk, my first one, where I was just
我的第一次TED演讲，当时我只是
drinking this this powdered water. So I
喝这种粉末状水。所以，我
said to her, I said and I was a
我对她说，我说，我是一个
millionaire at 24. lonely, not speaking
24岁成为百万富翁，孤独，不说话
to my family, drinking powder do
对我的家人来说，喝粉剂
shoplifting, working night shifts in
商店行窃，上夜班
multiple call centers, would you take
多个呼叫中心，你会接受吗？
the trade? And she went, "No." Right?
交易？她回答说：“不。”正确的？
&gt;&gt; She went, "Absolutely not." She wouldn't
她回答说：“绝对不行。”她不会
take the trade. And I said, "So, you
接受这笔交易。我说：“所以，你
can't you can't pick it apart because I
你不能把它拆解开来，因为我
if you want to my outcome, you have to
如果你想得到我这样的结果，你就必须这样做。
take the path that I took. If you want
走我走过的路。如果你想
my specific outcome, and people don't
我的具体结果，但人们却不这么认为。
think about that, like one of the things
想想看，就像其中一件事一样。
this podcast has actually taught me is
这个播客实际上教会了我什么
to think through the framework of
仔细思考框架
trade-offs."
权衡取舍。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; So, think about everything as a
所以，把一切都看作是
trade-off. Think of a Zmpeek as a
权衡。把 Zmpeek 想象成一个
trade-off. There's a trade you're making
权衡。你正在进行一笔交易。
somewhere. And even, you know, when you
某处。甚至，你知道，当你
aspire, you admire people, if you admire
有抱负，你就会钦佩别人，如果你钦佩别人
what we've done here, for example, think
例如，想想我们在这里所做的一切。
about the trade-off. Like even with this
关于权衡取舍。即便如此
team, the team have been working here
团队，团队一直在这里工作。
every single day, including the weekends
每一天，包括周末。
from morning till night for the last 14
从早到晚，过去14天
days here in New York. Every single day,
在纽约的这些天。每一天，
&gt;&gt; right?
正确的？
&gt;&gt; Do you want to do you want to do you
你想做吗？你想做吗？
want a podcast? Like, [laughter]
想听播客吗？就像，[笑声]
&gt;&gt; do you want the trade? And if you do,
你愿意进行这笔交易吗？如果你这么做了，
fine. But just be informed about, as you
美好的。但你要了解清楚，就像你
say, both sides of the trade. Another
比如说，交易双方。其他
Jimmy Carr quote that I love. He's a
我很喜欢吉米·卡尔的一句名言。他是一个
profound individual. Not only is he
深沉的人。他不仅如此
hilarious, he's very smart. The quote
他很幽默，也很聪明。引言
is, "Everyone is jealous of what you've
是，“每个人都嫉妒你所拥有的……”
got. Nobody's jealous of how you got
得到。没人会嫉妒你获得成功的方式。
it."
它。”
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And I think it's just so easy to
我觉得这太容易了
overlook. One of the things I write in
俯瞰。我写的东西之一是
the book is what's called the reverse
这本书是所谓的“反向”叙事。
obituary, which is it's a very good
讣告，这是一篇非常好的讣告。
helpful exercise to write down. It's
写下来很有帮助。它是
kind of morbid, but what do you want
有点病态，但你想要什么？
your obituary to say? kind of a weird
你的讣告里要写些什么？有点奇怪
thing, but for me, everyone's different,
但对我来说，每个人都不一样。
but for me, I would want it to say
但对我来说，我希望它说：
Morgan was a good father, a good
摩根是个好父亲，一个好父亲
husband, a good friend, helped his
丈夫，一位好朋友，帮助了他
community, was a good worker. That's
社区里，他是个好员工。那是
what I would want it to say. Never in a
我希望它表达什么。从未在
million years in that obituary would I
那篇讣告里会写上百万年吗？
want it to say what my income was, how
我希望它能显示我的收入是多少，以及如何
big my house was, how many times I went
我的房子很大，我去过多少次。
on vacation, how many horsepower my car
度假时，我的车有多少马力？
had. Like, it's ridiculous to think that
有。认为这一点简直荒谬至极。
that's what it would [laughter] be. I
确实会是这样（笑声）。我
would want it. You instantly drift
想要。你瞬间漂移
towards the things that you know you're
朝着你清楚自己在做什么的事物前进
actually you actually want in life. And
其实，你真正想要的是什么。和
of course, it's going to be different
当然，情况肯定会有所不同。
for everyone, but I I I found it a
对每个人来说都是如此，但我发现它
helpful thing because you realize that
这样做很有帮助，因为你会意识到这一点。
it would be completely absurd to put the
这样做完全是荒谬的。
things that I might be chasing in my
我可能在追求的东西
life in my obituary. And so if in any
我的讣告里写着我的一生。所以，如果在任何情况下
given day, in any given year, you're
在任何一年中的任何一天，你
like, I got to earn a higher income and
比如，我的收入提高了，
I want to buy a bigger house and a I got
我想买一栋更大的房子，而且我得到了
to need a new car and all you see, they
需要一辆新车，而你所看到的，就是他们
came out with this watch. But at the end
推出了这款手表。但最后
of your life, you know, that's not going
你知道，在你生命中，那不是会发生的。
to matter. What's going to matter is
很重要。真正重要的是……
were you a good spouse, a good parent, a
你是一位好配偶、好父母吗？
good worker, were you honest? Were you a
你是个好员工，你诚实吗？你当时是
good friend? Were you [clears throat]
好朋友？你当时是[清嗓子]
funny? That's you know that's what's
有趣的？你知道，那就是……
going to matter because that's what you
这很重要，因为这就是你所关心的。
want in your obituary.
想出现在你的讣告里。
&gt;&gt; I think part of the reason people spend
我认为人们花费的部分原因是
in the way that they do as well is
他们这样做的方式也同样如此。
linked to that which is sometimes that
与有时是那件事有关
behavior which is also linked to the
这种行为也与以下方面有关：
point about trauma at the start might
一开始就指出创伤可能
result in a savings addiction. I often
结果导致储蓄成瘾。我经常
wonder this cuz you know when I was
想知道这个，因为你知道我以前是
younger I had this crazy spending
年轻的时候我疯狂地花钱。
problem. And I've also seen people who
问题。我也见过一些人，
don't seem to spend anything and they're
他们似乎不花钱，而且他们是
just like hoarding capital. You talk
就像囤积资金一样。你说话
about this a bit in the book. Like what
书中对此有所提及。比如什么
&gt;&gt; is that equally bad behavior?
这种行为也同样不好吗？
&gt;&gt; Yeah, I think it's equally bad because
是的，我觉得同样糟糕，因为
both of them are the exact same thing
它们两者完全相同。
which is money's controlling you. Money
这就是金钱控制你。钱
should be a tool that you use to become
应该成为你用来成为……的工具
a better version of yourself to become a
成为更好的自己
happier, more content version of
更快乐、更满足的版本
yourself. But when it's controlling your
你自己。但当它控制你的时候
personality, it's it's it's no different
性格，没什么不同。
than like any any other addiction where
比其他任何成瘾症都更甚，
you don't it's forcing you to do things
你不需要，它是在强迫你做事。
that you otherwise don't want to do. And
你原本不想做的事。和
that can manifest on either end of the
这可能体现在两端
side. Either people can't stop spending
边。要么人们无法停止消费
or they cannot spend enough. A lot of
或者他们消费能力不足。很多
financial adviserss will tell you one of
财务顾问会告诉你其中之一
the biggest problems that they have are
他们面临的最大问题是：
clients who have saved enough money for
已经攒够钱的客户
retirement. Good job. You saved for 40
退休。好工作。你攒了40块钱
years. You maxed out your 401k. You did
年。你的401k账户已经存满了。你做到了
everything you were supposed to. and now
你应该做的一切。现在
you're 70 years old and you have enough
你已经70岁了，而且你拥有足够的
money to travel and play golf and you
有钱去旅行和打高尔夫球，还有你
won't you won't do it. And I think it's
你不会的，你不会这么做的。我觉得是
because they become so accustomed to the
因为他们已经习惯了
identity of I'm a saver. Every month I
我的身份是储蓄者。每个月我
save and every month my net worth goes
每个月我的净资产都会减少。
up and they cannot bring themselves into
起来，他们无法让自己进入
switching gears and going in the other
转换思路，转向另一个方向
direction. And for a lot of those
方向。而且对于很多那些人来说
people, the money is in full control
人们啊，金钱完全掌控着一切。
over their identity. It's telling them
围绕他们的身份认同。它是在告诉他们
how to live, what to like, what to
如何生活，喜欢什么，做什么
aspire to, what to enjoy. the money is
渴望拥有什么，享受什么。钱是
totally in control of their personality
完全掌控自己的个性
and and it's it's just as dangerous and
而且，它同样危险。
just as just as detrimental as you when
和你一样有害
you were a teenager of I can't stop
你曾是《我无法停止》的青少年
spending. It's and both of those are in
开支。是，而且这两个都在
are they the money is like playing the
他们把钱当作游戏吗？
marionette doll of your life. It's
你人生的傀儡。它是
telling you exactly what to do and when
告诉你具体该做什么以及何时做。
to do it.
去做这件事。
&gt;&gt; If I wanted to make a framework to know
如果我想建立一个框架来了解
how to spend my money where do I start?
我该如何花钱？从哪里开始？
Do I have to get clear on something? Do
我需要弄清楚什么吗？做
I you know and I guess the other
你知道，我想其他的
question which is somewhat linked to
这个问题与以下方面有些关联：
this is this overarching debate around
这是围绕这个主题展开的总体辩论。
can money make you happy?
金钱能让你快乐吗？
&gt;&gt; Right? But I'm trying to figure out like
正确的？但我正在努力弄清楚……
where do I start because I I want to one
我该从哪里开始呢？因为我想……
of the things I want to get out of today
我今天想得到的东西
is I want to have a a clearer framework
我希望有一个更清晰的框架。
for how to spend my money.
关于如何花钱。
&gt;&gt; Well, those two points that you just
嗯，你刚才提到的那两点。
brought up I think are very related. The
我认为提出的问题与此密切相关。这
first on the point of can money make you
首先，关于金钱能否让你……这一点。
happier? The answer is yes, but there's
更快乐吗？答案是肯定的，但是还有……
a there's a there's an asterisk next to
旁边有个星号
it that we need to get to. For years,
这是我们需要达成的目标。多年来，
there was a big academic debate of does
学术界曾就剂量问题展开过激烈的辩论。
more money make you happy? A lot of some
钱越多你越快乐吗？很多一些
of the studies showed yes, clearly it
研究表明，是的，很明显。
does. Others show studies showed no, it
做。其他研究表明并非如此。
really doesn't. And the academics, the
确实不是。而学者们，
economists were like battling for
经济学家们就像在为……而战
decades. It's kind of been cleared up in
几十年。这件事基本上已经澄清了。
the last just the last couple of years,
就最近这两年而言，
this last couple of decades with some
过去二十年来的一些
nuance, which is this. If you are
细微差别，就是这一点。如果你是
already an unhappy person, if you're
如果你本身就是一个不快乐的人，那么
already anxious, if you're already
已经焦虑了，如果你已经
depressed, by and large, having more
总体而言，情绪低落，拥有更多
money will not help you at least that
至少在这方面，钱帮不了你。
much. It might help you a little bit
很多。或许对你有点帮助。
around the margins. If you're if you
在边缘地带。如果你是如果你
start as an unhappy, depressed, anxious
最初是一个不快乐、抑郁、焦虑的人。
person. If you are already a happy,
人。如果你已经很快乐了，
content, joyful, laughing person, having
满足、快乐、爱笑的人，拥有
more money will give you a better life.
钱越多，生活就越好。
So in either direction, it's just
所以无论哪个方向，都只是
leveraging who you already were. It's
发挥你自身已有的优势。它是
not going to change you that much. It's
不会对你产生太大影响。它是
just going to leverage who you already
只是要利用你现有的人脉资源。
were. Very similar to like they say this
是。和他们说的很像
about power. Like once you gain power in
关于权力。就像一旦你获得了权力……
politics or something, it just leverages
政治或其他什么因素，它只是利用了这一点。
the personality that you already had.
你原本就有的性格。
&gt;&gt; Money is very much like that. And so
金钱其实就是这样。所以
it's it's not a a a panacea in the sense
它并非万灵药。
of like oh like if you're miserable like
比如，哦，比如如果你很痛苦的话
if you had more money it's going to
如果你有更多钱，那就会……
clear up your problems. It can make some
解决你的问题。它可以制造一些
of your problems a little bit easier to
让你的问题变得更容易解决一些
deal with. But I mean think about it in
处理。但我的意思是，仔细想想……
these stark terms. Let's say you are
这些鲜明的措辞。假设你是
overweight and unhappy. You hate your
超重且不快乐。你讨厌你的
job and you're recently divorced and
你有一份工作，而且最近刚离婚。
your kids won't talk to you but you live
你的孩子不跟你说话，但你仍然活着。
in a mansion that has a Ferrari in the
在一栋拥有法拉利的豪宅里
driveway and you got all kinds of fancy
车道，还有各种各样的花式
stuff. Is is is that a good life? If all
东西。这样的生活算是美好的生活吗？如果所有
if everything else in your life sucked
如果你的人生其他方面都很糟糕
and you woke up every morning going,
你每天早上醒来都会想，
"Ah, I got to go to work today. I hate
啊，我今天得去上班了。我讨厌上班。
my job. I can't stand my job. I'm I'm
我的工作。我受不了现在的工作。我 我
lonely. I'm miserable. I'm overweight. I
孤独。我很难过。我超重了。我
can't sleep. I'm addicted to alcohol."
睡不着。我酗酒成瘾。
Whatever it might be. Of course, it's a
不管是什么。当然，这是一个
terrible life. The house and the car
糟糕的生活。房子和车
don't matter at all. But you can flip
完全没关系。但你可以翻转
that around and say like, let's say you
就这样，比如说，假设你
live in a very modest middle class house
住在非常普通的中产阶级住宅里
and you drive a a 10-year-old Honda
你开的是一辆10年车龄的本田车。
Civic, but you love your job. You love
你热爱你的工作，因为你是一名公民。你爱
your co-workers. You have a great
你的同事。你很棒
relationship with your spouse. Your kids
你与配偶的关系。你的孩子
admire you. You have your friends over
我很欣赏你。你邀请朋友们来家里玩。
for a barbecue every Friday night.
每周五晚上都会举行烧烤聚会。
Materially, it's very modest. You have
从物质层面来说，它非常朴素。你有
what you need. You're not impoverished.
你需要什么。你并不贫穷。
You're not homeless. You have the food
你不是无家可归者。你有食物
that you want and the shelter that you
你想要的以及你想要的庇护所
want. But you would be an absolute
想。但你绝对会是
maniac to choose the miserable person in
疯子会选择那个可怜的人
the mansion versus the content, happy
豪宅与内容，快乐
person in the middle house. If your goal
住在中间房子里的人。如果你的目标
is to live a good life, it's psychotic
过上美好生活，这简直是精神错乱。
to pick one of one over the other. I
在两者之间做出选择。我
felt this quite starkly recently because
最近我对此感受尤为强烈，因为
I flew to Cape Town on my own. Um I've
我独自一人飞往开普敦。嗯，我
only ever been there with my girlfriend
我只和女朋友一起去过那里。
and with other friends and the first
和其他朋友以及第一个
time I've only been there a few times.
我只去过那里几次。
I've got a house there and it's a very
我在那里有一栋房子，那是一个非常……
big house and the first time I came with
大房子，我第一次来这里
was with my family. Second time it's
当时和家人在一起。第二次是
with my girlfriend and my friends. This
和我的女朋友和朋友们一起。这
time I came on my own
那是我独自前来的时候
&gt;&gt; and I felt this deep existential feeling
我感到了一种深刻的存在主义感受。
waking up walking through that house
醒来时正在穿过那栋房子
alone thinking [__] me. Like it [snorts]
独自一人想着“操我”。就像这样[嗤之以鼻]
was so clear to me that the point of
这一点对我来说非常清楚，以至于我明白了其中的意义。
such a such a thing is to fill it with
这样的事情就是用……填满它
people and you say
人们，你说
&gt;&gt; yes that's what I I make this point in
是的，这就是我提出这一点的原因。
the book of like the very simple
这本书就像非常简单的
question will a big house make you
问题：一栋大房子会让你……
happier?
更快乐吗？
&gt;&gt; I think it will make you depressed if
我认为如果你这样做，你会感到沮丧。
it's empty [laughter]
里面空无一人 [笑声]
&gt;&gt; because that's how I felt. I was like
因为我当时就是这么想的。我当时就像
I'd rather be in a studio apartment
我宁愿住在单身公寓里。
alone than a big house on my own.
比独自一人住在大房子里更孤独。
&gt;&gt; Right. I had a similar realization to
正确的。我也有类似的感悟。
you a couple years ago when I took my my
几年前我带我去的时候，你……
my my family and I went to Maui for a
我和我的家人去了毛伊岛。
vacation and I love Maui. my favorite
度假，我爱茂宜岛。我最喜欢的
place in the world. And now they have
世界上的某个地方。现在他们拥有
kids. So I'm building sand castles with
孩子们。所以我正在用沙子堆沙堡
my kids on the beach in Maui. And that I
我的孩子们在毛伊岛的海滩上。而我
remember thinking like this is this is a
记住当时的想法是这样的：这是一个
10 out of 10. This is like this is peak
十分满分！这简直就是巅峰之作！
life for me. Building sand castles with
对我来说，这就是生活。用沙子建造沙堡
my kids, everyone's happy in the sun.
我的孩子们，大家都在阳光下很开心。
&gt;&gt; But then I had this realization of like
但后来我突然意识到……
if that's a 10, playing with Legos at
如果那是10分的话，那就是玩乐高积木
home on the living room floor with my
我和家人一起躺在客厅的地板上。
kids is like a nine. Like it's really
孩子就像九岁。就像真的
close because the realization was what I
接近真相是因为我意识到了这一点。
enjoy is like quality time with my kids.
享受就像和孩子们共度美好时光。
And I think a lot of the reason that
我认为很大程度上是出于这个原因。
people like vacate, like travel is not
人们喜欢度假，喜欢旅行，但这并不重要。
because they like getting on an airplane
因为他们喜欢坐飞机
and flying around the world and being
飞遍世界各地，并且
jet-lagged and cramped into a small
时差反应严重，而且挤在一个小房间里
hotel. What they like is uninterrupted
酒店。他们喜欢的事情不会受到干扰。
time away from work, away from all the
远离工作，远离一切
other stresses of everyday life. That's
其他日常生活压力。那是
what they actually enjoy. That's why
他们真正喜欢的是什么。这就是原因
they like travel. It's not necessarily
他们喜欢旅行。不一定。
the location. It's like what the
地点。这就像……
location is doing for you. So the
地理位置会为你提供帮助。所以
question of will a big house make you
大房子会让你……这个问题
happier? It will to the extent that it
更快乐吗？它将在一定程度上实现这一点
makes it easier to have your friends and
这样更容易和朋友们相处，
family over
家庭聚会
&gt;&gt; because your friends and family are the
因为你的朋友和家人就是
ones who are actually making you happy.
那些真正让你快乐的人。
&gt;&gt; And so the answer can be can will a nice
所以答案可以是“可以”或“一个好的”。
house make you happy? The answer can be
房子让你快乐吗？答案可能是
yes if you're using it for the right
是的，如果你用对了用途的话。
reasons. There was this article in the
原因。有这样一篇文章
New York Times, this is probably 10 or
《纽约时报》，这大概是10或
15 years ago and uh the article said two
15年前，呃，文章里说了两个
things happened to Julia Roberts this
朱莉娅·罗伯茨这期间发生了一些事
week. One, she won the Academy Award and
星期。第一，她获得了奥斯卡奖；
two, she found out her husband was
第二，她发现她的丈夫是
cheating on her. And so the column said,
背叛了她。于是，专栏文章写道：
"Pop quiz, did Julia Roberts have a good
“小测验，茱莉亚·罗伯茨过得好吗？”
week?" And it's like, you'd be a fool to
一周？” 这就像，你简直就是个傻瓜，
say yes. It was probably the worst week
答应下来。那可能是最糟糕的一周。
of her life, I imagine.
我想，这是她生命中的一部分。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Um, but what we see from the outside was
嗯，但我们从外面看到的是……
doled up in a beautiful dress, accepting
身着华丽礼服，欣然接受
the highest honor of her career and
这是她职业生涯中的最高荣誉。
saying like, "Wow, that must be an
比如说，“哇，那一定是……”
amazing." But it gets back to once you
“太棒了。”但事情又回到了你
see the full picture, you're like, "Nah,
当你看到全貌时，你会想，“不，
it's not as easy as it seems."
这并不像看起来那么容易。
&gt;&gt; You say on page 23 of your book, a quote
你在书的第23页引用了一句话。
that I loved, show off the inside of
我喜欢展示它的内部
your house, not the outside.
你指的是你的房子，而不是房子外面。
&gt;&gt; Right.
正确的。
because the inside of your house or what
因为你家里面是什么？
your friends and your family are seeing.
你的朋友和家人都看到了。
&gt;&gt; Is there like a a hack here? Like is
这里是不是有什么破解方法？就像是
there, you know, because you have all
你知道，因为你拥有这一切
these like internet commun communities
这些类似于互联网社区
that come up with these like hacks,
那些想出这些类似黑客手段的人，
these other ways to live. They they they
其他的生活方式。他们他们
step outside of the matrix and they form
走出矩阵，它们便会形成
their own little their own little cult
他们自己的小邪教
that are like doing it differently and
就像用不同的方式做事一样
not not abiding by the rules of the the
不遵守规则
quote unquote matrix. I very much feel
引用矩阵。我深有同感
like most of us are trapped in the
就像我们大多数人一样，被困在……
matrix. We're trapped in this like
矩阵。我们被困在这种境地里了
status game competing against each
在地位博弈中，每个人都在竞争。
other, not not searching for happiness.
其他，并非在寻找幸福。
like what is the the hack here? How do I
这里的破解方法是什么？我该怎么做？
get out the matrix and what does that
摆脱矩阵，那会怎样？
look like?
看起来像？
&gt;&gt; I think if there is a formula that I I
我认为如果存在一个公式，我
lay out in the book and I I make the
在书中排版，我制作
point that like there's there's no
关键在于，好像没有
formula for how to spend money. But if I
花钱的公式。但是如果我
did try to make a formula for a pretty
确实尝试过为漂亮的
good life and this extends way outside
美好生活，而且这种美好生活远远超出了我们的想象。
of money, the formula for a pretty good
金钱，一个相当不错的公式
life is independence plus purpose. If
生活就是独立加上目标。如果
you want to say like how how can I be a
你想问的是，我怎样才能成为一个
happy person? You need to be
快乐的人？你需要是
independent. You need to be able to do
独立的。你需要能够做到
what you want to do when you want to do
你想做什么，什么时候想做
it with whom you want to do it with. And
你想和谁一起做这件事。和
you need some kind of purpose that is
你需要某种目的，那就是
higher than yourself. And that could be
比你自身更高。而这有可能
a million different things. It could be
数不胜数的事情。有可能
friends, it could be family, it could be
朋友，也可能是家人，也可能是……
career, it could be religion, whatever
职业，也可以是宗教，等等。
it might be. I think it is very
有可能。我认为这非常
difficult to imagine anyone having a
很难想象有人会……
good life without those two things. If
没有那两样东西，生活也很美好。如果
your entire life and your schedule is
你整个生活和你的日程安排是
dictated by somebody else of you have to
受他人指示，或者你必须
go to this job that you don't like, you
去做这份你不喜欢的工作吧，你
have to have a long commute that you
你必须忍受漫长的通勤时间。
don't like, you have to do this when you
不喜欢的话，你必须这样做。
don't want to do it, it's it's hard to
不想做，这很难……
be happy. And if you don't have any kind
要开心。如果你没有任何种类
of purpose that you're doing it for,
你做这件事的目的，
it's difficult to be happy. And so the
快乐很难获得。所以，
idea that to me, the best thing to spend
对我来说，最好的消遣方式就是花时间
money on is independence. And I view it
金钱的用途在于独立。我的看法是
as purchasing. I I don't view it as
如同购买一样。我不认为它是
saving money. I view it as purchasing
省钱。我将其视为购买
independence. That's how I I view I view
独立。这就是我的看法。
like I'm buying independence when I
就像我买的是独立一样
save. And so to me, the biggest thing
节省。所以对我来说，最重要的事情
that I spend my money on, and this
我把钱花在这上面，还有这个
sounds weird, but I is saving. And I
听起来很奇怪，但我确实在存钱。我
view that as buying independence. I view
把这看作是购买独立性。我的看法
that as every dollar that I save is a
因为我省下的每一美元都是一笔宝贵的财富。
little bit more independent than I was
比我当时稍微独立一些
before. It's a little bit of my future
前。这有点像我的未来。
that I now own and control. And if if
我现在拥有并控制它。如果如果
you're listening to this and you're
你在听这个，而且你是
like, "Look, I'm not financially
比如，“你看，我经济上并不富裕。”
independent. I have no I have no
独立的。我没有 我没有
possibility of being financially
经济上的可能性
independent." Independence exists on a
独立。”独立存在于……
spectrum. And literally every dollar
光谱。每一美元，都实实在在地存在着。
that you save is a little bit more
你省下的钱会更多一些。
independent than you were before. If you
比以前更独立了。如果你
have a $100 in the bank in savings, that
我在银行里有100美元的存款。
can make it so that if you were to lose
可以这样，即使你输了
your job, you have a little bit more
你的工作，你还有更多。
flexibility for rent or groceries or
租金或食品杂货方面的灵活性
whatever it might be that you didn't
无论你没做到的是什么
before. $1,000, $10,000, any amount that
前。 1000美元，10000美元，任何金额
you have is a little bit more
你拥有的比这多一点。
independent than you were before. And so
比以前更独立了。所以
when you view
当你查看
one of the cores of living a good life
美好生活的核心要素之一
as independence and any amount of saving
独立性和任何金额的储蓄
money will buy you independence, I think
我认为金钱可以买到自由。
that's a powerful observation for
这是一个很有见地的观察。
people. And then the purpose part is
人们。然后，目的部分是……
going to be different for everyone. For
每个人的情况都会不一样。为了
me right now in my life, it's being a
我现在的生活状态是……
good father. That's what I want my end
好父亲。这就是我想要的结局
my identity to be. That's my
我的身份。那是我的
[clears throat] overarching goal in life
[清嗓子]人生的最终目标
is to be a good dad. I I think the vast
就是做一个好爸爸。我认为广阔的
majority of parents will tell you that
大多数家长会告诉你：
there was no greater joy, purpose than
没有什么比这更快乐、更有意义了。
watching their kids thrive. Can also
看着自己的孩子茁壮成长。也可以
bring a lot of sorrow and a lot of
带来很多悲伤和很多
sleepless nights and a lot of anxiety
失眠的夜晚和严重的焦虑
and a lot of worry that comes along with
以及随之而来的诸多担忧
it. But nothing that I've experienced or
它。但我所经历的或
any of the other parents that I know
我认识的其他家长
would would say that anything in their
他们会说，他们中的任何事
life has come before that that it's been
生命早已到来，它一直如此。
a great thing. So we got on this point
一件好事。所以我们谈到了这一点。
because the formula is independence plus
因为公式是独立性加
purpose. For me the purpose is being a
目的。对我而言，目的在于成为一个
parent. That's not going to be true for
父母。这种情况不会发生。
everyone.
每个人。
&gt;&gt; But you're trading independence for
但你却用独立性换取了……
that.
那。
&gt;&gt; I'm trading it's internal independence
我用它的内部独立性来交换
that I'm giving up. I want to sacrifice
我放弃了。我想牺牲
for my kids. I want to like loyalty to
为了我的孩子们。我想喜欢忠诚
people who deserve your loyalty is a
值得你忠诚的人是
wonderful thing. Loyalty to people who
美好的事物。对那些人的忠诚
don't deserve your loyalty sucks. And so
不配得到你的忠诚，太糟糕了。所以
if you are work, if you're giving your
如果你在工作，如果你在付出你的
loyalty to a company that doesn't
对一家不忠诚的公司保持忠诚
respect you, that sucks. That's
尊重你，这太糟糕了。那是
terrible. Loyalty to people who deserve
糟糕的。对值得的人忠诚
it is a very fulfilling thing. So my
这是一件非常有成就感的事情。所以我的
kids deserve my loyalty.
孩子们值得我忠诚。
&gt;&gt; How did they earn that loyalty?
他们是如何赢得这份忠诚的？
[laughter]
[笑声]
&gt;&gt; Just by being my kids. And there's some
仅仅是因为他们是我的孩子。还有一些
days where I feel like they they don't
有些日子我觉得他们不……
appreciate it, [laughter] of course. But
当然，我很感激。[笑声]但
I I think that tends to be true. People
我认为情况往往如此。人们
get into problems when they are loyal to
当他们忠于……时，就会陷入困境
people or organizations or political
个人、组织或政治
affiliations who don't deserve the
不配享有此等荣誉的附属机构
loyalty. That's when it gets dangerous.
忠诚。那时就危险了。
&gt;&gt; Do you think the promise of independence
你认为独立的承诺如何？
and freedom has a secret hidden dark
而自由背后，隐藏着一个黑暗的秘密。
trade-off that people don't talk about?
人们不愿提及的权衡取舍？
Because there's this culture right now
因为现在存在这种文化
of like, you know, be your own boss and
就像，你知道，自己当老板一样
stand on your own two feet. And when you
自立自强。当你
think about what makes humans happy, it
想想什么能让人感到快乐，是
seems to be collective things. It seems
似乎是集体性的事物。它似乎
to be actually in your case, as you were
实际上，就你的情况而言，就像你曾经那样。
saying, dependence. Your kids depend on
也就是说，依赖。你的孩子依赖于
you. In some ways, you depend on them.
你。在某些方面，你依赖他们。
All the things that seem to like having
所有那些似乎喜欢拥有的东西
my friends at my house made me happier
朋友们来我家让我更快乐
than being in the house alone, right?
总比一个人待在家里强，对吧？
But the nar the public narrative is all
但公众叙事的全部内容
about like optimizing for freedom,
就像追求自由一样，
whatever that means, and really more so
无论这意味着什么，而且实际上更重要的是
optimizing for independence, not
优化目标是独立性，而不是
depending on someone else. But when you
依赖他人。但是当你
look at the people that seem to be the
看看那些看起来像是……的人
the most unhappy, they seem to be the
最不快乐的人，他们似乎是
most independent,
最独立的，
&gt;&gt; right? because they're they if you
正确的？因为如果你是他们，他们就是他们。
picture someone like living in a living
想象一下有人喜欢住在……
by themselves in the middle of Montana
他们独自一人在蒙大拿州中部
with no one around them or whatever it
周围没有人，或者其他什么情况
might be.
有可能。
&gt;&gt; No family, no pets, freelance work on a
没有家庭，没有宠物，自由职业。
laptop on their own in a in a glass box
笔记本电脑单独放在一个玻璃盒子里
in Dubai. Um no no big obligations, not
在迪拜。嗯，没有，没有什么重大义务，不是。
not in a church.
不在教堂里。
&gt;&gt; But back to the formula, independence
但回到公式本身，独立性
plus purpose. Those people have no
加上目的。那些人没有
purpose.
目的。
&gt;&gt; Oh yes.
哦是的。
&gt;&gt; And so I think it's I think yes,
所以我觉得答案是肯定的。
everyone is going to be I'm I'm
每个人都会是“我”
dependent on my wife, my kids. But, you
依靠我的妻子和孩子。但是，你
know, there is dependency there, but I'm
我知道，这其中存在依赖关系，但我
I'm choosing I chose her as a spouse. I
我选择她作为我的伴侣。我
chose to have kids. And so, I I still
选择生孩子。所以，我仍然
did it on my terms. And so, you're never
完全按照我的方式做的。所以，你永远不会
going to be or I think you don't want to
会是，或者我觉得你不想是
be a 100% independent in the sense that
百分之百独立，就是指
you don't rely on anyone and no one
你不依赖任何人，也不依赖任何人。
relies on you because then you have no
依赖你，因为那样你就没有
purpose.
目的。
&gt;&gt; It's choosing who [clears throat] you
这是选择你和谁[清嗓子]
want. I think it's I think you're not
想。我觉得你不是
independent if you have to be loyal to a
如果你必须忠于某人，那就保持独立
job that you hate, but you have to have
一份你讨厌但又不得不做的工作
it because it's the only job you got and
因为这是你唯一的工作。
you and you have to do it and you're you
你，你必须这么做，你就是你自己
you have to pay this exorbitant rent on
你必须支付这笔高昂的租金
an apartment that you don't even enjoy
一套你根本不喜欢的公寓
that much. Like those are dependence on
就这么多。就像那些依赖于
things that you don't want, but like I
你不想要的东西，但就像我
want to be dependent on my family
想依靠我的家人
because that gives me purpose.
因为那样我才能有目标。
&gt;&gt; It's like the independence to make the
这就像是拥有自主权一样。
choice, I guess.
我想，这是一种选择吧。
&gt;&gt; To make the choice of who you're going
选择你要去的地方。
to be dependent on, right?
可以依赖，对吧？
&gt;&gt; Got you. And [clears throat] on this
抓到你了。然后[清了清嗓子]关于这一点
earlier point, you were talking about
前面你提到过……
saving um and that you your favorite
保存它们，并且你最喜欢的
form of spending is saving.
消费的一种形式就是储蓄。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Someone's listening now, how much money
有人在听，多少钱？
do you think they should at a minimum
你认为他们至少应该……
have saved?
已经存钱了吗？
&gt;&gt; If you try to get technical about it, I
如果你试图从技术角度分析，我
would say what are the odds that at some
会问，在某些情况下，这种可能性有多大？
point in your life, you're going to lose
在你人生的某个阶段，你会失去
your job and not be able to find another
你丢了工作，而且找不到另一份工作。
job for six months. The odds are not bad
这份工作为期六个月。胜算还不错。
that that will happen to you at some
你迟早也会经历这种事。
point. Not very comfortable to think
观点。想到这一点感觉不太舒服。
about. Maybe it's already happened to
关于。也许已经发生过了
you already, but the odds that at some
你已经知道了，但在某些情况下，这种可能性仍然存在。
point that will happen are pretty good.
即将发生的事情相当不错。
And therefore, if you were to say like,
因此，如果你要说，比如，
look, a good measure of
你看，一个很好的衡量标准
some level of higherend independence,
一定程度的高端独立性，
not a low level of independence, but
并非独立性低，而是
like a a medium level of independence is
就像中等程度的独立性一样
six is is I could keep myself going for
六点意味着我可以一直坚持下去
6 months. Now, for a lot of people,
6个月。现在，对于很多人来说，
that's a daunting task. And I it's okay.
那是一项艰巨的任务。我觉得没关系。
You're probably not going to achieve
你可能无法实现
that when you're 18. Am I it's going to
当你18岁的时候。我会……
take some savings to get there, but that
需要攒些钱才能到达那里，但是
is a level at which you can exhale to a
是一个你可以呼气到……的水平。
degree that most people have never been
大多数人从未达到的程度
able to do before of like there's going
能够在之前做到，就像即将发生的那样
to be some bad stuff happening in your
你身边发生了一些不好的事情。
life. It's going to be uncomfortable,
生活。这会让人感到不舒服。
but it's going to be okay. And for for
但一切都会好起来的。而对于
for most people for most of history, it
对大多数人来说，在历史的大部分时间里，它
was there's bad things going to happen
会有不好的事情发生吗？
to you and you're not going to be okay.
对你来说，你不会好起来的。
It's going to be very traumatic. And and
这将是非常痛苦的。而且
one of the important things there is
其中一件重要的事情是
when you lose that job, the ability to
当你失去那份工作时，你就会失去以下能力：
go find a good job, even a better job
去找份好工作，最好是份更好的工作。
where you want, doing what you want with
想去哪儿就去哪儿，想做什么就做什么。
the people who you like working with is
你喜欢和哪些人一起工作？
very important. If you don't have any
非常重要。如果你没有任何
savings, you're going to have to by
要想省钱，你必须……
default pick the very first job that you
默认情况下，选择你找到的第一份工作。
can come across, even if it's a terrible
即使是很糟糕的，也能给人留下深刻印象。
job in a location that you hate, doing
在你讨厌的地方做一份工作
something you hate, working with people
你讨厌的事情之一，就是和人一起工作
you don't like. And so the flexibility
你不喜欢。因此，灵活性
to give yourself time to find a job that
给自己一些时间去找一份工作
is a little bit easier and better for
更容易一些，也更好一些
you, that is the purpose of savings.
这就是储蓄的目的。
&gt;&gt; And that goes back to your point about
这就回到了你刚才提到的那一点。
independence, which is you want to
独立，也就是你想要的
building up those savings is building up
积累这些储蓄就是在积累财富。
the independence or the freedom to make
独立性或自由
a choice about who you work with,
选择与谁共事，
&gt;&gt; right?
正确的？
&gt;&gt; If the worst were to happen, you don't
如果最糟糕的情况发生，你不会
have to necessarily go get a job at, you
你未必必须去那里找份工作。
know, some awful place,
我知道，某个糟糕的地方，
&gt;&gt; some some terrible place. You talk about
某个糟糕的地方。你谈到
jealousy in the book as well and um I
书中也有嫉妒的情节，嗯……
was reading [clears throat] some stats
正在阅读[清嗓子]一些统计数据
that quite funny stats but they they say
这些数据挺搞笑的，但他们说
that essentially that if you're if you
本质上来说，如果你是，如果你
win the lottery the probability of your
赢得彩票的概率
neighbor going bankrupt increases.
邻居破产的案例增加了。
[laughter]
[笑声]
&gt;&gt; It's an amazing statistic, right?
这是一个惊人的统计数据，对吧？
[gasps]
[倒吸一口气]
&gt;&gt; So what's what's happening [laughter]
所以到底发生了什么事？（笑声）
there?
那里？
&gt;&gt; Well, you're looking at your neighbor
嗯，你眼前这位就是你的邻居。
who won the lottery and your neighbors
谁中了彩票，以及你的邻居
probably bought a vacation house, bought
可能买了一套度假屋，买
a new car, sending their kids to private
买辆新车，送孩子上私立学校
school, whatever it might be. and you
学校，不管是什么学校。你呢
watching that are like, I need that for
看着那些画面，我就觉得，我需要那个。
myself. It's it's unfair that they have
我。他们这样做是不公平的。
it and I don't and I'm gonna go do any
它，而我没有，我要去做任何事
reckless financial decision to get that.
为了得到它，我做出了一个鲁莽的财务决定。
So much of what we think is is normal.
我们认为的很多事情都是正常的。
Our definition of success is what other
我们对成功的定义是……
people around us have. And so if you are
我们周围的人都有。所以，如果你是
watching your neighbor live a better
看着邻居过着更好的生活
life than you, then all a sudden your
比你过得更好，然后突然间你的
definition of a good life is what
美好生活的定义是什么？
they're doing. And you will do some
他们正在这样做。你也会做一些事。
reckless things to get it. I think
为了得到它，他做了许多鲁莽的事情。我认为
that's that's what happens. And so one
事情就是这样发生的。就这样……
of the takeaways there is like be
其中的一些要点就像是……
careful who you socialize with because
要谨慎选择社交对象，因为
you're going to anchor to them as a
你要把它们作为锚点。
baseline level of success and happiness.
成功和幸福的基准水平。
Be very careful with what you do and who
做事和与人交往都要非常谨慎。
you look up to and who you aspire to. I
你仰慕的人，你渴望成为的人。我
grew up in Lake Tahoe, California. And
在加利福尼亚州太浩湖长大。和
this was before tech money when it was
这发生在科技资金涌入之前。
not a wealthy area. it is now because
并非富裕地区。正是因为如此。
all the tech money from San Francisco
旧金山所有的科技资金
came up. But Tahoe in the 90s and early
出现了。但90年代和90年代初的太浩湖
2000s was was just a out in the woods
2000年代就像是在树林里一样。
and you know you could buy a house for
你知道你可以买一套房子
nothing and most people in town didn't
什么也没有，镇上大多数人也没有。
have any money. And then I went to
你有钱吗？然后我就去了
college in Los Angeles where there is a
洛杉矶的一所大学，那里有
lot of wealth, there are high
财富很多，而且很高。
expectations and there are Lamborghinis
期望，还有兰博基尼
and Rolls-Royces and whatnot. And one of
还有劳斯莱斯之类的。其中一个
my observations was people were happier
我的观察是，人们更快乐了。
in Tahoe. And I think the reason why is
在太浩湖。我认为原因在于……
because the definition of success in
因为成功的定义是
Tahoe back then was a two-bedroom house
当时的塔霍是一栋两居室的房子。
and a pickup truck.
还有一辆皮卡。
&gt;&gt; That was success. In Los Angeles, the
那就是成功。在洛杉矶，
definition of success was a mansion and
成功的定义是拥有一座豪宅
a and a Bentley. And so it was it was
一辆宾利。事情就是这样。
easier for people in Tahoe to be like,
对于太浩湖的人们来说，这样更容易些。
I'm good. I I check the boxes. Like
我很好。我勾选了这些方框。喜欢
look, I'm successful. Look at look at my
你看，我很成功。看看我的
tiny little house and my beat up pickup
小小的房子和我那辆破旧的皮卡
truck. That's success, right? And so
卡车。那就算成功了吧？所以
that was like be careful who you
那就像是要小心你和谁在一起。
socialize with because you're going to
与人交往，因为你要……
anchor to their level of success. I have
以他们的成功水平为基准。我有
a some graphs in front of you there. Um
你面前有一些图表。嗯
I think one of them is the spectrum of
我认为其中之一是光谱
financial independence.
经济独立。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Could you explain to me what that is and
你能给我解释一下那是什么吗？
and how how that's useful to understand
以及这对于理解事物有何用处
and why that's useful to understand?
为什么理解这一点很有用？
&gt;&gt; I think it's I had this friend uh 10 or
我想是我有个朋友，呃，10岁或
10 or 20 years ago and he said, "I don't
十年前或二十年前，他说：“我不……”
save any money because I don't see the
省钱是因为我看不到……
purpose. All I'd be able to save is a
目的。我唯一能省下的就只有
hundred bucks a month and what's that
每月一百美元，那又怎样？
going to do for me?" And since I don't
你会为我做什么？”既然我不会
think it's going to do anything for me,
我觉得它对我没什么用。
I I might as well just go spend it. And
我干脆就去把钱花掉算了。和
I remember thinking, no, no, that's like
我记得当时我想，不，不，那就像
$100 in savings or if you do it for a
节省100美元，或者如果你这样做的话
year, $1,200 in savings is $1,200 more
一年下来，节省1200美元就相当于多出1200美元。
independence than you had before. And
比以前更独立。和
again, not if, but when you lose your
再说一遍，不是“如果”，而是“当你失去”
job or your car breaks down, you're
如果你的工作出了问题，或者你的车抛锚了，你就……
going to realize how unbelievably
将会意识到这有多么不可思议
valuable that money is. And it's not
金钱的价值就在于此。但事实并非如此。
savings, it's independence that it's
储蓄，以及独立自主，才是最重要的。
giving you. So the idea that
给你。所以这个想法是
independence is on a spectrum. It is not
独立性是一个连续谱。它不是
you either don't have to work or you
你要么不用工作，要么……
have to work. It's not that stark, but
得工作。情况并没有那么糟糕，但是
most people think of it in those terms.
大多数人都是这样看待这个问题的。
Why would I try to become independent if
如果这样，我为什么要努力独立呢？
I have no chance of not working?
我完全没有不工作的可能吗？
&gt;&gt; And the simple way to view it is every
最简单的理解方式就是……
dollar that you save is a piece of your
你省下的每一美元都是你的一部分。
future that you own, that you control,
属于你自己、由你掌控的未来
that is yours. The flip side of that is
那是你的。另一方面是……
like every dollar of debt that you have
就像你背负的每一美元债务一样
is a piece of your future that somebody
这是你未来的一部分，由某人决定。
else controls. It's a it's a moment in
否则控制。这是一个瞬间
time in the future that is not yours. It
不属于你的未来时光。它
belongs to somebody else. And so I've
属于别人。所以，我
always viewed it on a spectrum. When I
我一直把它看作一个连续谱。当我
was younger and much poorer, I was a big
我当时年纪小，家境也很差，我是一个大
saver. Even though like was I
省钱。即使就像我
independent? Like no, of course I had to
独立的？不，我当然必须这么做。
work. I had to work to pay my rent and
工作。我必须工作才能支付房租，
pay my groceries, of course. But I
当然是帮我付买菜钱啦。但我
viewed it as like every $20 that I
我觉得就像我每花20美元一样。
saved, every $50 that I saved put me in
我省下了钱，每省下50美元，我就……
a better position than I was before. And
我现在的处境比以前好多了。和
looking back on it, I I don't think I
回想起来，我觉得我
could have articulated that 20 years
20年前本可以阐明这一点
ago, but it's what I felt. A lot of that
虽然是很久以前的事了，但这就是我的感受。很多这样的
for me back then was coming from a place
对我来说，那时我来自一个地方
of fear. I didn't have a lot of
恐惧。我没有很多
self-confidence in myself, in my career.
对自己和自己的事业充满自信。
So, I was like, I need to save to
所以，我就想，我得存钱。
prepare for when this all comes crashing
做好一切崩溃时的准备。
down. Mhm.
向下。嗯。
&gt;&gt; And even though it didn't come crashing
即使它没有坠毁
down, I'm so glad that I did it because
下来之后，我很高兴我这么做了，因为
I' I've had a sense of financial
我对经济方面有所了解。
security and I've had a sense of
安全感，我一直有这种感觉。
independence financially since I was in
自从我……以来，我就实现了经济独立。
my early 20s. Not because I had saved a
我二十出头的时候。并非因为我存了钱
ton, I hadn't, but any amount that I
吨，我没有，但任何数量我
saved, I I viewed as like the cushion
保存下来，我把它看作是垫子
that that gave me a much higher sense of
那让我对……有了更深刻的认识。
confidence that if or when things go
有信心，如果或当事情进展顺利时
wrong, I'm not going to be flailing. I'm
错了，我不会胡乱挥舞手臂。我是
gonna have some cushion to fall back on.
总会留点后路的。
And what is this this spectrum? Uh what
这个光谱是什么？呃，什么
are the stages of this spectrum?
这个光谱包含哪些阶段？
&gt;&gt; So let's start at the very bottom.
那么，让我们从最底层开始吧。
You're homeless. You're panhandling.
你无家可归。你在乞讨。
Reliant on the kindness of strangers. As
依靠陌生人的善意。作为
you go up from there, you can be
从那里往上走，你就可以
completely reliant on your boss in a job
在工作中完全依赖你的老板
that you don't like. Now that's that's
你不喜欢的。好了，就是这样。
that's a that's another low level. As
那又是另一个低级别水平了。作为
you go up from there, you have look, I
你从那里往上走，你会看到，我
am I'm relying on my job. I'm relying on
我靠这份工作维持生计。我依靠
my on my paycheck, but I probably have
我的工资单上有这部分，但我可能还有
some opportunities. I could go work at
一些机会。我可以去工作
another job. I could I could choose to
另一份工作。我可以选择
work here. I could choose to work there.
在这里工作。我可以选择在那里工作。
And then you go from there is like, yo,
然后你就从那里开始，就像，哟，
I I like my job and I have some savings.
我喜欢我的工作，而且我还有些积蓄。
So if I lost this job, I can fall back
所以如果我丢了这份工作，我还有退路。
onto it from there. You can go up from
接下来就看情况了。你可以从……向上走
there to have you can live where you
在那里你可以拥有你居住的地方
want. You can work where you want. You
想。你可以选择在任何你想工作的地方工作。你
can change fields. You can you can go
可以更改字段。你可以去
and you can do a completely different
你可以做完全不同的事情
job. You can take two months off and
工作。你可以休假两个月，
travel if you wanted to. Like you're
想去就去旅行。就像你
working your way up all the way to the
一路晋升到
highest level of financial independence,
最高程度的财务独立性
which is I don't need to work anymore.
也就是说，我不再需要工作了。
I've saved enough and I can I can I can
我已经攒够钱了，我可以，我可以，我可以
wake up every morning and do whatever I
每天早上醒来，做任何我想做的事。
would like to do. That's obviously an
想做。那显然是一个
aspiration that for most people will
大多数人的愿望
never be reached until they're maybe in
直到他们可能在……之前，永远无法联系到他们。
their, you know, 70s and they're
你知道，他们70多岁了，他们是
retiring and they have social security
他们退休了，而且他们有社会保障金。
and some other savings from there. But
以及由此节省的其他一些开支。但
for most people, like a good level of
对大多数人来说，就像达到一个良好的水平
independence as a good goal is enough
独立作为一个好目标就足够了。
savings so that if you lost your job, if
这样，万一你失业了，你的积蓄也能派上用场。
your car broke down, if you needed to
如果你的车抛锚了，你需要
replace the roof on your house, you
更换你家的屋顶，你
would be able to do it without losing
能够做到而不损失
that much sleep. That is a realistic
睡够了。那是一个现实的例子。
level that I think almost anyone can
我觉得几乎任何人都能达到的水平
achieve. based on everything you know
达到。基于你所知道的一切
about money if I want to get to that
说到钱，如果我想谈到那个话题的话。
highest level of complete financial
最高级别的全面财务
freedom, what what what's like the the
自由，那是什么感觉？
five things that I should be thinking
我应该思考的五件事
about at just a sort of a very simple
大概就一种非常简单的
level, you know, cuz so many people
水平，你知道，因为太多人
listening right now think, you know, my
现在听着，想想，你知道，我的
goal in life isn't to become a
人生目标不是成为一个
billionaire or a tens of millionaire. My
亿万富翁或数千万美元富翁。我的
goal in life is just to get to that
人生的目标就是达到那个境界。
point of freedom as soon as I can. Yeah.
尽快获得自由。是的。
&gt;&gt; Where I can start calling the shots. And
我可以从哪里开始发号施令了。和
there's there was someone who I was
曾经有一个人，我
speaking to the other day and said that
前几天跟人说了这件事，他说
there's this internet movement of kids
互联网上出现了一种儿童运动。
who are trying to get what do they call
他们试图得到什么，他们称之为
it it's like they're trying to get to
就好像他们试图达到某种目的一样
the point where they can retire early
他们可以提前退休的点
&gt;&gt; fire something
点燃某物
&gt;&gt; financial independence retire early that
财务自由，提前退休
&gt;&gt; y
是
&gt;&gt; like how do I get how do I get there
我该怎么去？我该怎么到达那里？
&gt;&gt; the first thing that I think that's most
我认为最重要的第一点是
important this is the first and the last
重要提示：这是第一点，也是最后一点。
thing this is the most important part is
这件事，最重要的部分是……
that all wealth your feeling of wealth
财富，你对财富的感觉。
is what you have minus what you want and
就是你拥有的减去你想要的。
it's so easy to ignore the latter I talk
忽略后者太容易了，所以我说
about in the book my my late
关于我书中的我，我晚年
grandmother-in-law, my wife's
岳母，我妻子的
grandmother, passed away a couple years
祖母几年前去世了。
ago. For 30 years, she lived off of
前。三十年来，她靠……生活
nothing but 17 or $1,800 a month in
每月只有 17 美元或 1800 美元。
social security. Not a lot of money by
社会保障。没多少钱
most accounts, very little money. But
大多数账户，但余额很少。但
she didn't want anything more. She did
她别无所求。她确实
she if she made $1,700 a month, she did
如果她每月能挣1700美元，她就这么做了。
not want $1,700 in one in $1. She was
不想花 1 美元买到 1700 美元。她
perfectly happy. She she found all of
非常满意。她找到了所有的一切。
her happiness working in her garden,
她很享受在花园里劳作的快乐。
going for walks, watching the birds,
散步、观鸟，
watching the sunrise, watching the
观看日出，观看
sunset, talking to her friends, hanging
日落时分，她和朋友们聊天，闲逛
out with her family. But if you asked
和家人一起外出。但如果你问
her, you said, "You only make $7,700 a
你对她说：“你一个月才挣7700美元。”
month. You're broke. Doesn't that make
月。你没钱了。那岂不是……
you unhappy?" She'd be like, "What?"
你不开心吗？”她会问：“什么？”
Like, "Do you think having more money
比如，“你觉得拥有更多钱会怎么样？”
makes the sunset more beautiful? You
让日落更美吗？你
think having more money makes going for
认为钱多就能追求
a walk more pleasant?" And I'm not
散步更愉快吗？而我并非如此。
saying you should live like you should
说你应该像你应该的那样生活
be content with that amount of money,
对这笔钱感到满足吧。
but the point is like, she was content.
但重点是，她当时很满足。
She was totally content. And it was her
她非常满足。是她。
choice. And I think she was happier
选择。我觉得她更快乐了。
financially than some billionaires
经济实力比某些亿万富翁还要强
because there's a lot of billionaires
因为有很多亿万富翁
who have a billion dollars but they want
他们拥有十亿美元，但他们想要
two. They have two billion but they want
二。他们有20亿，但他们想要
four. One of the things is that
四、其中一点是……
happiness might be the wrong word here.
这里用“幸福”这个词可能不太合适。
The word that people want is content.
人们最想听到的词是“内容”。
When you sit here and daydream about
当你坐在这里做白日梦的时候
having the bigger mansion, what you're
拥有更大的豪宅，你就是
actually doing is you're imagining
实际上，你所做的只是你的想象。
yourself in the mansion being content
你独自一人在豪宅里，感到满足
with it. You imagine yourself sitting in
和它一起。你想象自己坐在
that house and saying, "I don't want
那栋房子，然后说：“我不想要
anything more than this." The feeling
比这更多。”这种感觉
that we are aspiring to is just being
我们所追求的，仅仅是存在。
content. Happiness is always like a 30-
内容。幸福总是像30分钟一样。
secondond emotion. It's like laughter.
第二情绪。就像笑声一样。
Like if I tell you a funny joke, you'll
比如，如果我给你讲个笑话，你就会
laugh for 30 seconds and then and it's
笑30秒，然后就结束了
over. Like very few times in life are
超过。就像人生中极少有的时刻一样
you happy for more than a couple minutes
你高兴超过几分钟了吗？
at a time. But what you want that is
一次一次。但你想要的是
like a durable emotion is being content.
就像知足常乐一样，是一种持久的情感。
Just saying like I'm good. I'm good with
就这么说，好像我没事似的。我对此很满意
this. I don't want anything more.
这。我别无所求。
&gt;&gt; I interviewed Dr. Anna LMK and she's
我采访了安娜·LMK博士，她是
like the the uh the scientist who's most
就像那位最……的科学家
uh renowned for talking about and
呃，以谈论和而闻名
writing about dopamine.
关于多巴胺的文章。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And I was wondering how much do the
我想知道多少钱
molecule dopamine dovetailes into this
多巴胺分子与此完美契合。
because I think one of the things she
因为我认为她所做的事情之一
said to me was that dopamine is the
有人告诉我，多巴胺是
chemical for wanting. Yeah.
想要化学物质。是的。
&gt;&gt; And people have I think mistaken it for
我认为人们把它误认为是
being the the pleasure
乐趣
&gt;&gt; happiness. Yeah. Happiness hormone.
幸福。是的。快乐荷尔蒙。
&gt;&gt; It's it's more more. It's like you want
是它更多更多。就像你想要的那样
more. And she told me this crazy study
更多的。她跟我讲了这个疯狂的研究
about this rat where they removed the
关于这只老鼠，他们把它移走了
dopamine receptor from its brain so it
来自大脑的多巴胺受体，所以它
couldn't produce dopamine and then they
无法产生多巴胺，然后他们
put food 2 in from its mouth and the rat
把食物2从它的嘴里放进去，然后老鼠
starved to death because it it it and
饿死了，因为它，因为它，它
that I've always thought about that is
我一直都在想的是……
like okay so that's what dopamine is.
好吧，原来多巴胺就是这个。
It's the motivation to go get to go get
这是去争取的动力。
to want to pursue. What role is dopamine
想要追求。多巴胺的作用是什么？
playing here?
在这里演出吗？
&gt;&gt; It's huge and that's actually a good
它非常大，这其实是件好事。
realization to be like a lot of this is
意识到很多事情都像这样是
not something you can solve on a
这不是你能在短时间内解决的问题。
spreadsheet. It's not something you can
电子表格。这不是你能做的事。
solve with a formula. It's chemicals in
用公式求解。它是化学物质。
your brain. And obviously some people
你的大脑。显然有些人
are going to be more susceptible to that
更容易受到这种影响
than others. I think my
比其他人更胜一筹。我觉得我的
grandmother-in-law
婆婆
just had for whatever it was was was
不管那是什么，反正就是
wired differently than most people. Part
他的思维方式与大多数人不同。部分
of that was like she was a product of
那感觉就像她是某种产物……
the Great Depress. She grew up during
大萧条。她在这段时期长大
the Great Depression, which probably
大萧条，这很可能
like lowered her expectations. She never
比如降低了她的期望值。她从未
had social media and whatnot. But of
有社交媒体之类的东西。但是
course, I think some people are wired
当然，我认为有些人天生如此。
differently than others for a level of
与其他水平不同的是
contentment. But I think just there's a
满意。但我认为，就存在一个
big thing in psychiatry where diagnosing
精神病学中的一件大事，就是诊断
a mental illness is sometimes more
精神疾病有时更严重
important than the treatment. If you
比治疗本身更重要。如果你
just get a diagnosis of like, oh, you're
就确诊一下，比如，哦，你是
ADHD, whatever it is, just knowing just
不管是什么，多动症，只要知道就好。
like the the fact that you can stop
比如你可以停下来
questioning, why am I having these
质疑，为什么我会有这些
thoughts? You can you can understand why
有什么想法？你就能明白为什么了
you have those thoughts is more
你之所以会有这些想法，是因为你更……
important than the treatment sometimes.
有时，重要性甚至超过了治疗本身。
And I think that's true here. If if you
我认为这里的情况也是如此。如果你
it's easier said than done to completely
要完全做到这一点，说起来容易做起来难。
control your desires, but just knowing
控制你的欲望，但仅仅是知道这一点就足够了。
why you're doing it and realizing that
你为什么这样做，并意识到这一点
it's probably not going to give you the
它可能不会给你带来什么
happiness that you want, that it's just
你想要的那种幸福，就只是
like any addiction that the more you
就像任何一种成瘾一样，你越沉迷其中，就越容易上瘾。
chase it, the further away it's going to
追它，它就会跑得越远。
get,
得到，
&gt;&gt; can go [clears throat] a big ways. And
可以走很远（清嗓子）。和
so for me myself, there's all the time
所以对我个人而言，时间总是充裕的。
there are moments where I'm like, "Oh, I
有时候我会想，“哦，我
I should I I should get that car. Maybe
我应该，我应该买那辆车。或许
I should get a bigger house." I have
我应该买个更大的房子。我有
those feelings daily. So the feelings
每天都会有这种感觉。所以，这些感觉
don't go away. But I think I'm better
不要走。但我认为我情况好转了。
now than I've been in the past at
现在比我过去任何时候都更……
reminding myself of like it's not going
不断提醒自己，就好像它不会发生一样。
to make you happier. You know that.
让你更快乐。你知道的。
You've tried this before. You've tried
你以前试过这种方法。你已经尝试过了
it before and it didn't make you happy.
你以前试过，但那并没有让你开心。
What is going to make you happy is
能让你快乐的是
spending time with your kids, having a
花时间陪伴孩子，拥有
good relationship with your wife and
与妻子保持良好的关系
your own physical health and laughing
你自身的身体健康和欢笑
with your friends and having good times
和朋友们一起度过美好时光
with people who you enjoy. You know
和自己喜欢的人一起。你知道
that's going to make you happy. And you
那会让你开心的。你呢
know that's not. And I have to remind
我知道那不是真的。我必须提醒大家
myself because it's not intuitive. And I
我自己觉得这不直观。我
have dopamine that tells me you should
体内多巴胺告诉我你应该
want more and more more and more and
想要更多更多更多，而且
more. So, you never get over it, but I
更多的。所以，你永远无法释怀，但我
think once you've diagnosed the problem,
一旦你诊断出问题所在，就应该思考：
it becomes easier at just like spotting
就像发现目标一样，这变得更容易了。
that emotion and realizing that it's
那种情绪，以及意识到这一点
telling you a story that's probably not
给你讲一个可能并非真实的故事
true.
真的。
&gt;&gt; I wonder if you I could trade the
我想知道我们是否可以交换
addiction cuz you, you know, you
上瘾，因为你，你知道，你
referred to it there as being an
在那里称之为
addiction. If it's a dopamine equation,
瘾。如果这是一个多巴胺方程式，
could I not shift my addiction to
我难道不能把我的瘾转移到
something more productive and would that
一些更有意义的事情，那会怎样？
mean that my spending would get better?
这意味着我的消费习惯会改善吗？
So actually when I think about me as 18
所以，当我回想起18岁时的自己时，其实是这样的……
years old and having that horrific
多年过去，却遭受了如此可怕的折磨
spending problem, maybe I just shifted
消费问题，或许我只是换了个地方而已。
the the thing that gave me dopamine to
让我分泌多巴胺的东西
like building businesses or to
比如创办企业或
podcasting or to writing books or to
做播客或者写书或者
being a great dad. I don't know. Do you
做一个好爸爸。我不知道。你
know?
知道？
&gt;&gt; I think it's probably true that
我认为这很可能是真的。
everybody without exception is addicted
无一例外，人人都会上瘾。
to something and it's just harnessing
成为某种东西，而这只是利用
that that process for whatever it might
这个过程，无论它是什么……
be. So some people are addicted to my
是。所以有些人对我的东西上瘾了。
wife's addicted to gardening, let's say.
比如说，我妻子迷上了园艺。
She couldn't care less about about
她对此毫不在意
investing or spending money on a nice
投资或把钱花在美好的事物上
she could not care less about her car or
她根本不在乎她的车或
my car or your car. But if you have a
我的车还是你的车？但是如果你有一个
good gardener, if you you have a pretty
一个好的园丁，如果你有一个漂亮的
garden, she's she's all over this. So,
花园里，她到处都是她。所以，
everybody's got their thing and it's
每个人都有自己的爱好，而且……
just like, can you harness that for
比如，你能利用这一点吗？
productivity?
生产率？
&gt;&gt; I think a lot of like extremely
我认为很多人非常
successful people are people who took
成功人士是那些采取了……的人。
their their natural addiction and
他们天生的瘾好
harnessed it for productivity into their
他们利用这一点来提高生产力。
business.
商业。
&gt;&gt; And that's that's why they're so
正因如此，他们才如此……
successful. this became obsessed with
成功的。这件事变得令人着迷
one thing and it's it's a good question
一件事，而且这确实是个好问题。
of whether we can actually guide that
我们是否真的能够引导这一点
addiction or if it's just kind of
上瘾，或者只是有点……
pre-wired in itself. I think it's true
本身已预先接线。我认为这是真的
for myself, someone who's written books
就我个人而言，作为一个写过书的人。
about money for 20 years, thought about
关于金钱，思考了20年。
money for 20 years. My mom tells a story
20年的资金。我妈妈讲了一个故事
that when I was three, I would sit there
我三岁的时候，常常坐在那里
and count pennies. I don't want to count
然后数着硬币。我不想数
seashells. I don't want to count cards.
贝壳。我不想算牌。
I don't want to count rocks. I want to
我不想数石头。我想要
count money. And so I think I've always
数钱。所以我觉得我一直
had this disposition towards being
有这种倾向
fascinated with money.
对金钱着迷。
&gt;&gt; Why?
为什么？
&gt;&gt; I don't know because I did it when I was
我不知道，因为那是我做这件事的时候……
three. I did it before I could even
三。我甚至在我能够做到之前就做到了。
think through it. But I think everyone
仔细想想。但我认为每个人
has their little thing. It's always been
他们有自己的小秘密。一直都是
fascinating to me. I don't think I'm
我觉得很有意思。我不认为我是
obsessed with money. I don't think it
痴迷于金钱。我不这么认为。
controls my life. But I've had to go out
掌控着我的人生。但我不得不出去。
of my way to have a a healthier
我追求更健康生活的方式
relationship with it. But I think it's
与它的关系。但我认为是这样
definitely been true that the reason
确实如此，原因也确实如此。
that I've found myself in this career is
我发现自己在这个职业生涯中扮演着这样的角色：
that it's always been my thing. And I
那是我一直喜欢做的事。我
think everybody has that thing in their
我觉得每个人心里都有那东西
life. You know, people talk about
生活。你知道，人们谈论
addictive personalities and uh I was
有成瘾倾向的人格，呃，我曾经是
reflecting one of my best friends who
这让我想起了我的一位最好的朋友，他
was an alcoholic, had a problem with
他是个酗酒者，有这方面的问题
gambling, then had a problem with
赌博，然后又出现了问题
eating, then got obsessed with marathons
先是吃，然后迷上了马拉松
and he he traded each one of those
他把那些东西一个个都交易了出去。
things for the next thing. So now he's
为下一件事做准备。所以他现在是
like obsessed with health and fitness.
就像痴迷于健康和健身一样。
And so I was when I was thinking about
所以，当我思考……的时候，我就是这样。
people that are struggling with money
那些经济拮据的人
problems and even my own historical
问题，甚至我自己的历史
struggle with money, I I think I
我觉得我在经济上很挣扎。
probably just traded it for something.
可能只是拿去换了什么东西。
And actually, I'm kind of happy about
实际上，我对此感到挺高兴的。
that because I traded it for a better
因为我用它换了一个更好的。
addiction, one that was productive.
成瘾，但是一种有益的成瘾。
&gt;&gt; Your career?
你的职业生涯？
&gt;&gt; My career and um
我的职业生涯和嗯
&gt;&gt; I guess doing this. I'm pretty addicted
我想这样做。我对此非常着迷。
to doing this,
这样做，
&gt;&gt; right? And but I think
正确的？但我认为
&gt;&gt; makes me happier than the plasma screen.
比等离子屏幕更让我开心。
&gt;&gt; It's exactly. Yeah.
正是如此。是的。
&gt;&gt; I think what's true about a money
我认为关于金钱的真相是这样的。
addiction is that it tends to be the
成瘾的本质在于它往往是
classic addiction of like you tell
经典的成瘾就像你讲述的那样
yourself if only I get one more hit, so
如果我再击中你一次，你就赢了。
to speak, then I'll be satiated. Then
我说完话，我就满足了。然后
then then that'll be enough. And the
那样就足够了。以及
answer is like, no, it absolutely will
答案是，不，绝对不会。
not. I'll tell you like a a personal
不是。我会像个私人顾问一样告诉你。
thing. I don't think this is true, but
事物。我不认为这是真的，但是
it made me laugh. My wife and I bought a
它逗笑了我。我和妻子买了一辆
new house about a year ago. It's an
新房子大约一年前买的。这是一个
awesome house. We love it. It's great.
很棒的房子。我们很喜欢。这很棒。
And my brother-in-law came over the
我姐夫过来了
other day and he goes, "You know, you're
前几天他说：“你知道，你是……”
only going to live here for 2 years
只打算在这里住两年
before you want to buy a bigger house."
在你想要买更大的房子之前。”
And I had to laugh cuz I'm like, "God,
我忍不住笑了，因为我心想：“天哪，
like I I I don't think that's true. I
我觉得那不是真的。我
think we're going to live here for a
我觉得我们会在这里住一段时间。
while, but I know what you're saying is
虽然，但我知道你的意思。
right. That's the natural guide towards
正确的。这是自然而然的指引。
it." that when we bought the house, it
它。”当我们买下这栋房子时，它
was like, "Oh, this is going to be so
当时我就想，“哦，这肯定会非常……”
great. Can you imagine? We're going to
伟大的。你能想象吗？我们将要
get to do this and get to do that and we
可以做这个，可以做那个，我们
have these neighbors, whatnot, and you
有这些邻居，等等，还有你
become accustomed to that very quickly
很快就能习惯这一点
and then your gaze shifts a little bit
然后你的目光稍微转移了一下。
higher. You're like, "Yeah, but look at
更高。你会想，“是啊，但是看看……”
that house over there. That one's nicer,
那边那栋房子。那款更好一些。
isn't it?" That's always the natural
难道不是吗？这总是很自然的。
thing. And that's dopamine at work. That
事物。这就是多巴胺在起作用。那
is dopamine purely at work. Because the
纯粹是多巴胺在起作用吗？因为
truth is, our previous house was was
事实上，我们之前的房子是
great. And our previous house used to be
伟大的。我们之前的房子曾经是
our dream. And dopamine exists when
我们的梦想。多巴胺在以下情况下存在：
there's a when there's a gap between
当两者之间存在间隙时，就会出现这种情况。
where you are and where you want to be
你现在在哪里，以及你想去哪里。
with something. And when that gap
用某物。而当这个差距出现时
closes, they often refer to that as the
关闭时，他们通常称之为
arrival fallacy.
到达谬误。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Right.
是的。正确的。
&gt;&gt; Which is a really kind of what you're
这其实就是你正在做的事情。
describing.
描述。
&gt;&gt; You tell yourself once I get there, then
你告诉自己，等我到了那里，然后
I'll be then I'll be good. Then that's
到时候我就没事了。那么，那就是
enough. And it's a fallacy because you
足够的。这是一种谬误，因为……
know that's not true. As soon as you get
我知道那不是真的。一旦你得到
to that whatever that mountain top is,
到那座山峰，无论它是什么。
there's another mountain above it. It
它上面还有一座山。它
pushes you in a way that is not easy.
它会以一种并不容易的方式鞭策你。
Like nobody should pretend that you can
就像没人应该假装自己可以
just go do this today. But it pushes you
今天就去做这件事。但它会推动你
into appreciating what you have now and
学会珍惜你现在所拥有的一切，
finding your joy, finding your happiness
找到你的快乐，找到你的幸福
through other things that don't have the
通过其他不具备这种特性的事物
arrival fallacy. Never have as I as a
到达谬误。我从未像我一样
parent have I said, "Oh, if only I had
我曾对父母说过：“哦，如果我当初……”
one more kid." Then then that would be
再添一个孩子。”然后，那就会是
great. There's no there's really no
伟大的。真的没有
arrival fallacy for kids. You just kind
儿童版到达谬误。你只是有点
of be like this. Like I I I just
就是这样。就像我，我只是
appreciate being around you. I just
很珍惜和你在一起的时光。我只是
appreciate all the And if anything, it's
感谢所有人。如果说有什么的话，那就是……
the opposite. It's you look back and
恰恰相反。是你回头看的时候
you're like, "Oh, I I I miss when you
你会想，“哦，我好想念你……”
were younger." It was like, "Oh, I I'm
当时我们更年轻。”感觉就像，“哦，我，我是
It's It's sad how fast you're growing
你长得这么快，真让人难过。
up." If if anything, rather than like
向上。”如果说有什么不同的话，那就是像
looking ahead and being like, "Oh, it's
展望未来，然后想：“哦，那是……”
going to be better then." You're looking
到时候会好起来的。” 你看着
back and you're like, "Ah, I wish I had
回来之后你会想，“啊，我真希望我当时……”
appreciated that phase a little bit
稍微欣赏一下那个阶段。
more."
更多的。”
&gt;&gt; When you talked about um one of the ways
当你谈到其中一种方法时
to get to early retirement and to live a
为了提前退休并过上……
better life is to want what you have um
更好的生活就是珍惜你所拥有的。
and basically want less things. I go
基本上想要的东西越来越少。我去
back and forward a lot with this idea
围绕这个想法，我反复思考了很多次。
because there's like the monks who say
因为就像那些僧侣说的那样
that like happiness is not wanting
幸福就像不匮乏一样。
something and then there's like the
有一些东西，然后就像……
reality of life where striving for
生活的现实，就是努力追求
things seems to make me happy and
某些事物似乎能让我感到快乐，
everybody describes the journey as being
每个人都把这段旅程描述为
the most enjoyable part.
最令人享受的部分。
&gt;&gt; That's your purpose.
这就是你的目的。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Yeah. So, like what what how do
是的。是的。所以，比如，什么，怎么做？
how do I make sense of this? That like
我该如何理解这件事？就像
the monks are telling me that not to
僧侣们告诉我不要
want anything cuz that's going to make
想要任何东西，因为那会……
me frustrated and unsatisfied. And then
让我感到沮丧和不满。进而
my lived experience is striving for
我的生活经验就是努力追求
things with a group of people makes me
和一群人一起做的事情让我
seems to make me happy.
它似乎让我感到快乐。
&gt;&gt; I think there's a there's a difference.
我认为这两者之间是有区别的。
It's a subtle difference, but between
这是一个细微的差别，但两者之间
pursuing something that you genuinely
追求你真正热爱的事物
enjoy doing, which for you is this and
享受做这件事的过程，对你来说就是这件事。
your [clears throat] your business and
你的（清嗓子）你的生意和
whatnot,
诸如此类，
&gt;&gt; versus being addicted to something that
与沉迷于某种事物相反
chasing something that you don't have
追逐你没有的东西
yet. And so I imagine, you can correct
然而。所以我想，你可以纠正
me if I'm wrong, but I imagine when
如果我错了请告诉我，但我设想的是……
you're doing this, you don't tell
你这么做，却不说。
yourself, I need to work harder so that
你自己，我需要更加努力工作，这样……
one day the podcast can be up here.
总有一天，播客节目会上传到这里。
&gt;&gt; I [clears throat] I imagine, tell me if
我（清了清嗓子）我想，告诉我是否
I'm wrong, but I imagine you come to
我错了，但我认为你会来
work every day and you're like, I I like
每天工作，你会想，我喜欢
doing this today. I like today. I
今天就做这件事。我喜欢今天。我
[clears throat] liked yesterday. I'm
[清嗓子] 昨天点赞了。我是
going to like tomorrow. And so you're
大概明天就到。所以你是
not chasing a false goal. You just
不要追求虚假的目标。你只是
actually enjoy doing it.
我真的很喜欢做这件事。
&gt;&gt; Do you know what? It's a weird thing
你知道吗？这是一件很奇怪的事。
because it's it's uh I'm going to be
因为，呃，我将会是
honest because it's the only useful
诚实是唯一有用的
position to take. It's it's a weird
采取的立场。这很奇怪
combination of both. So I say like it's
两者结合。所以我说，就像这样
important for us to have some like goal
对我们来说，拥有类似的目标很重要。
&gt;&gt; but also live in the in in the total
但也生活在整体之中
understanding that the goal doesn't
明白目标并非
actually matter.
实际上很重要。
&gt;&gt; And it's this weird dichotomy I live in
我生活在这种奇特的二元对立之中。
like if we become the biggest podcast in
比如，如果我们成为最大的播客……
the world like set that as a goal
世界似乎将此设定为目标
because it gives [clears throat] us
因为它给了我们[清嗓子]
something to
某事
&gt;&gt; chase. I get that
追赶。我明白了。
&gt;&gt; KPI and then like put time frames
KPI，然后设定时间框架
against and get excited by and focus on
反对、兴奋并专注于
&gt;&gt; but then also living in the total
但同时也生活在整体之中
realization that it's not going to
意识到这不会发生
matter at all. Nothing is going to
根本无关紧要。什么都不会发生
change in my life. Zilch, what am I
我的生活发生了变化。什么都没有，我是什么？
going to get? A better black shirt. It's
你会得到什么？一件更好的黑色衬衫。它是
like, [laughter] do you know, you know
就像，[笑声]你知道，你知道
what I mean?
我的意思是？
&gt;&gt; But here's the truth. The reason that we
但事实是这样的。我们之所以这样做，是因为我们
live in a world with a ton of technology
生活在一个科技高度发达的世界。
and a ton of great businesses and great
还有很多很棒的企业和很棒的
medicine, whatnot, is because virtually
医学等等，是因为实际上
everybody for all of human history has
纵观整个人类历史，每个人都……
woken up every morning and said, "It's
每天早上醒来都会说：“是……”
not enough. I need more." That's the
不够。我还需要更多。”就是这样。
fuel of progress. And I don't want to
进步的动力。我不想
live in a world where everyone wakes up
生活在一个每个人都醒来的世界里
and says, "I have all I need." Because
他说：“我拥有我所需要的一切。”因为
then progress would stop that day. We
那么，进步将在那天停止。我们
probably start declining that day.
可能从那天起就开始下降。
&gt;&gt; And so there is a paradox here of like
所以这里存在一个悖论，就像
as a whole society, I'm grateful and you
作为整个社会的一份子，我心存感激，你
should be grateful that people wake up
应该庆幸人们醒悟过来。
unfulfilled
未实现的
&gt;&gt; because we live in a way better world
因为我们生活在一个更好的世界里
today than existed 100 or 200 years ago
如今的情况比100年前或200年前要好得多。
because of that. And the richest people
正因如此。以及最富有的人
in the world who I think are by and
在世界上，我认为谁是……
large tortured psychologically have
遭受巨大心理折磨的人
created amazing technology that you and
创造了令人惊叹的技术，你和
I benefit from. And the reason we're
我从中受益。而我们之所以……
doing this podcast is because people
做这个播客是因为人们
before us who were way wealthier than
在我们之前，那些比我们富有得多的人
you and I woke up in the morning and
你和我早上醒来，
said this is not enough. Bill Gates,
他说这还不够。比尔·盖茨
Jeff Bezos, all those people, Elon Musk,
杰夫·贝佐斯，还有那些人，埃隆·马斯克，
Mark Zuckerberg, they woke up and said,
他们醒来后对马克·扎克伯格说：
"I don't care if I have a hundred
我不在乎我有没有一百个
billion dollars. It's not enough. I need
十亿美元。这还不够。我需要
I need to create better technology." And
我需要研发更好的技术。”
that's great. We benefit from that. And
那太棒了。我们因此受益。和
so there is a paradox here that what is
所以这里存在一个悖论，即什么是
all and that will never change that will
这一切，而且永远不会改变。
never change. So there's a paradox that
永远不要改变。所以这里存在一个悖论：
like the more the better society becomes
就像社会越美好就越好一样
I think like it's always going to be the
我觉得它总是会是……
case that as a whole society we're going
假设我们整个社会正在走向
to have a level of angst and anxiety and
感到一定程度的焦虑和不安
not be satisfied and say it's not
不要不满意，并说这不是
enough. At the individual level though I
足够的。但就个人层面而言，我
think you can recognize that game and
你觉得你能认出那款游戏吗？
contextualize it within your own life
将其置于你自己的生活中进行理解。
and say like look
就像这样
I want more money. I I want to sell more
我想要更多钱。我想卖出更多
books and have a better career. I want
读书并拥有更好的职业发展。我想
to save more money. I also have to go so
为了节省更多钱。我也得走了
far out of my way to put it into context
我费了好大劲才把它解释清楚。
and say none of it's going to matter
然后说这一切都无关紧要
unless I have a higher purpose beyond
除非我拥有超越世俗的更高目标。
that money. So, I think you can aspire
那笔钱。所以，我认为你可以有远大的抱负。
for more and still go out of your way to
为了更多，并且仍然不遗余力
realize what the expectations game is.
要明白什么是期望游戏。
Even if you can't perfectly control it,
即使你无法完美控制它，
it's similar to like I want to eat a
这就像我想吃东西一样。
good diet. Of course, I want to eat
良好的饮食习惯。当然，我想吃
healthy food. I'm not going to pretend
健康食品。我不会假装
for a second that I don't want Oreos and
有一瞬间，我不想吃奥利奥了。
ice cream. are great and they're always
冰淇淋。他们很棒，而且他们总是
going to taste great. And so I'm never
味道肯定很棒。所以，我永远
going to get to a point where I say, "I
总有一天我会说：“我
don't want a nicer house." I'm I'm a
我不想要更好的房子。我是一个
human and and so are you and so is
人类，你也是，也是。
everyone else. You're always going to
其他人。你总是会
have those feelings. But you can
你也有这种感觉。但是你可以
recognize the game. You can recognize
认清游戏规则。你可以认出
the voice that's talking to you and
跟你说话的声音
realize when that voice lies to you and
要学会分辨那个声音何时在说谎。
when it's telling you a story that is
它在讲述一个故事时
either false or just a little bit
要么是假的，要么只是一点点。
incomplete. I think if you had to like
不完整。我觉得如果你非要喜欢的话
say who is the happiest person in the
说出谁是世界上最快乐的人。
world on average, not like naming a
世界平均水平，不像命名一个
person, but if you had to describe the
这个人，但如果要描述……
life of like who's the happiest person
比如，谁是最幸福的人？
out there, my guess is it's probably
我猜想，它可能就在那里。
something close to a a middle-ass family
差不多是一个中等水平的家庭
that lives in a three-bedroom house and
住在三居室房子里的人
has a a 5-year-old car, but they have an
他们有一辆五年车龄的汽车，但他们有一个
amazing marriage, tons of friends,
一段美好的婚姻，很多朋友，
they're in good health, but they are by
他们身体健康，但他们……
any other statistic ordinary. and at the
其他任何统计数据都很普通。并且
end of their life more than the people
他们生命的终结比人们更甚。
who are very very successful that
那些非常非常成功的人
ordinary family is going to look back
普通家庭终将回顾往事
when they're on their deathbed when
当他们卧床不起，奄奄一息的时候
they're 95 years old and be like that
他们95岁了，还是那样。
was good
很好
&gt;&gt; that was a good time
那段时光真美好。
&gt;&gt; do you think um this is a very strange
你觉得这很奇怪吗？
question to ask but do you think I could
有个问题想问，但你觉得我能吗？
make myself like that
让自己变成那样
&gt;&gt; no
不
here's the truth I think on the nature
我认为关于自然的真相是这样的
nurture spectrum
后天培养谱
most of what we believe and the feelings
我们所相信的大部分以及我们的感受
that we have is forged at conception and
我们所拥有的一切，是在受孕之初就已形成的。
it's just we're just wired that Okay.
我们天生就是这样，好吧。
And there's not much we can do about it.
对此我们无能为力。
Some people have different aspirations.
有些人有不同的抱负。
Elon Musk was born wired very
埃隆·马斯克天生就很有才华。
differently than you and I. And there's
与你我不同。而且还有
nothing we can do about that. So, we are
对此我们无能为力。所以，我们是
who we are, but I think we can put those
我们是谁，但我认为我们可以把这些放在那里。
feelings into a better context. Even if
将情感融入更好的语境中。即使
we can't control having those feelings,
我们无法控制自己产生这些感觉。
we can choose we can put tell ourselves
我们可以选择，我们可以告诉自己
a more complete story about why we're
更完整的故事讲述了我们为什么
having those feelings and what those
拥有那些感觉以及那些
aspirations will actually do to our
抱负实际上会对我们产生影响。
happiness. So on this point of how to
幸福。那么，关于这一点，如何……
retire early, the first one was about
提前退休，第一个大约是
managing what you want. Is there
掌控你想要的一切。有没有
anything else there that if if I'm
还有什么其他情况吗？如果我是
trying to increase the probability that
试图提高以下概率
I get to retire early, um I should know
我可以提前退休，嗯，我应该知道。
in terms of tactics and strategies.
在战术和战略方面。
&gt;&gt; Well, one of the things, this is a
嗯，其中一件事是……
little bit different than than the
与……略有不同
question that you asked, but one of the
你提出的问题，但其中一个
things that's important is that a lot of
重要的是，很多
the people who do retire early, who they
那些提前退休的人，他们
tell themselves, I'm going to save so
告诉自己，我要存钱。
much money, I'm going to retire when I'm
钱很多，我打算退休的时候……
32 and then life's going to be great.
32岁之后，生活就会很美好。
What actually happens is they retire at
实际情况是，他们会在退休。
32 and six months later they're bored
32岁零6个月后，他们感到无聊了。
out of their mind and they realize that
他们神志不清，然后意识到
like what actually makes you happy is
真正让你感到快乐的是什么？
purpose. And for a lot of people their
目的。对很多人来说，他们的
purpose can be their career or they
目的可以是他们的事业，或者他们
realize they had this idea that when
他们意识到他们有这个想法，当
they retired it was just going to be a
他们退休了，这本来就是一件……
great life. But the truth is all of
美好的生活。但事实是，所有这一切都
their friends are working and don't have
他们的朋友都在工作，没有……
time to go play golf with them on
该和他们一起去打高尔夫了。
Tuesday afternoon. And so a lot of those
周二下午。所以很多那些
people who retire early end up going
提前退休的人最终会……
back. they realized it was not what it
后退。他们意识到事情并非如此。
was meant what it was made out to be
其含义正如人们所解释的那样
because they had if the the formula is
因为他们有，如果公式是
independence plus purpose they gained
他们获得了独立性和目标感。
independence but they kind of lost their
独立性，但他们某种程度上失去了……
purpose and then the for and so it was
目的，然后是“为了”，所以就是这样。
incomplete they didn't get what they
不完整，他们没有得到他们想要的
wanted
通缉
&gt;&gt; what about passive income people talk a
人们常说的被动收入是怎么回事？
lot about passive income I had a friend
我有个朋友，他跟我讲了很多关于被动收入的事情。
DM me the other day and say Steve I've
前几天私信我说史蒂夫，我
got some debts etc but if I could just
我有些债务等等，但如果我能……
figure out a way to create some passive
想办法创造一些被动的
income then that should solve the
那么，收入问题应该就能解决了。
problem and this term passive income has
问题在于，被动收入这个术语……
become like
变得像
&gt;&gt; completely overused because for example
完全滥用，例如
a lot of people when they talk about
很多人在谈论……
passive income They're like, "Oh, I'm
被动收入 他们会说：“哦，我是……”
going to own real estate. I'm going to
准备拥有房产。我要
have some rentals and that's passive
有一些出租房产，那是被动收入。
income." If you think owning a rental
收入。”如果你认为拥有一套出租房是值得的
property is passive income, you've never
房产是被动收入，你从未有过
owned a rental property because there's
拥有一套出租房产是因为有
nothing passive about it. It is a
这绝非被动的。这是一个
constant chain of broken toilets and
厕所持续损坏，一连串故障
leaky roofs and tenants who don't pay
漏水的屋顶和拖欠房租的租户
you on time. And there's nothing
你准时到达。什么也没有
passive. That's a full-time job doing
被动的。那是一份全职工作。
that. And so, I heard someone say this
那。于是，我听到有人这么说
recently that there's two ways to get
最近有两种方法可以获得
wealthier. You can sacrifice more or you
更富有。你可以牺牲更多，或者你
can want less and that's it. and gain
可以少些欲望，仅此而已。并获得
passive income is not part of that
被动收入不属于这一范畴。
equation because
因为方程式
&gt;&gt; what's the first one? Sacrifice more.
第一个是什么？牺牲更多。
&gt;&gt; Sacrifice more.
牺牲更多。
&gt;&gt; What does that mean?
这意味着什么？
&gt;&gt; Work harder. Work work in a job that is
更加努力。从事一份工作
that has a lot of downsides that might
这有很多缺点，可能会……
stress you out and requires you to wake
让你压力很大，需要你起床
up early and go to work and do some
早起去上班，做一些事情
things that you don't want to do and
你不想做的事情和
spend time away from your kids in a way
以某种方式抽出时间远离你的孩子。
that you don't want to do. Sacrifice
你不想做的事。牺牲
more or want less. Those are your two
想要更多还是更少。那是你们俩
choices. And I think that's important in
选择。我认为这很重要
the passive income debate because I I I
被动收入之争，因为我我我
don't think there's but there by and
别以为有，但就在那里。
large is not a thing of passive income.
大额收入并非被动收入的来源。
Even if you're just like, you know, you
即使你只是，你知道，你
put your money in a in a savings account
把钱存入储蓄账户
that pays 3% interest. Well, you had to
年利率为3%。嗯，你不得不
sacrifice to earn that money
为了挣到这笔钱而做出牺牲
&gt;&gt; and to save that money and to delay the
为了节省这笔钱并推迟……
gratification of that money. I I I
对那笔钱的满足感。我 我 我
really think it's an ironclad formula.
我真的觉得这是一个万无一失的公式。
Sacrifice more or want less. Those are
要么牺牲更多，要么减少欲望。那些是
your two options.
你有两个选择。
&gt;&gt; It's not nice. That's true.
这不好。这是真的。
&gt;&gt; People want, you know, tell me which
人们想知道，你知道，告诉我哪个
crypto to [laughter]
加密货币[笑声]
&gt;&gt; right
正确的
&gt;&gt; to invest in to get that.
投资才能获得它。
&gt;&gt; Of course, everyone's always going to
当然，每个人总是会……
want the easy answer. Just like for
想要简单的答案。就像……
health,
健康，
&gt;&gt; the answer is eat a better diet and
答案是改善饮食习惯。
exercise. Nobody wants that. They just
锻炼。谁都不希望那样。他们只是
say get what's the what's the secret
说出秘密是什么。
potion? What's the secret formula? And
药水？秘诀是什么？和
maybe now we have OMI. So maybe now we
或许现在我们有了OMI。所以也许现在我们
have it's closer to a to a secret
它更接近于一个秘密
formula. But the truth is what's the
公式。但真相是什么？
secret to better health? Sacrifice more
保持健康的秘诀是什么？牺牲更多
because working out and lifting weights
因为锻炼和举重
and running is a sacrifice. It's not
跑步是一种牺牲。它不是
fun. It hurts. That's why it's good. Or
乐趣。好痛。这就是它好的地方。或者
want less. Be happier with your
想要的更少。对自己更满意
imperfect body. I mean, I think that's a
不完美的身体。我的意思是，我认为那是一个
great analogy between health and and
健康与……之间是一个很好的类比
wealth.
财富。
&gt;&gt; Often the difference between a company
通常，公司之间的区别就在于此。
succeeding or failing isn't down to its
成功或失败并非完全取决于它
product or strategy. It's down to the
产品或策略。这取决于……
people on the inside. After all, the
内部人员。毕竟，
definition of the word company is group
公司一词的定义是集团
of people. And some of the best
人。还有一些最好的
companies in the world have been largely
世界上的公司大多
built by a players. Because I'll let you
由玩家建造。因为我会让你这么做
in on a little secret. When you hire an
知道一个小秘密。当你雇佣一个
A player, they go on to hire more A
一名球员，他们继续雇佣更多球员。
players. and it perpetuates. The
玩家。而且这种情况还会持续下去。这
challenge is finding those first few A
挑战在于找到最初的几个A
players. I found the majority of mine on
玩家。我的大部分都是在……上找到的
LinkedIn who are a sponsor of this show.
LinkedIn是本次节目的赞助商之一。
LinkedIn provides talent I could not
LinkedIn 提供了我无法企及的人才。
find anywhere else. Talent with the
别的地方都找不到。天赋
necessary skills and culture fit that
必要的技能和文化契合度
I'm looking for. Whenever I've paid to
我在找。每当我付费
promote a role on LinkedIn, I've been
我一直在LinkedIn上推广一个职位。
able to hire faster and of course
能够更快地招聘到人才，当然
better. Their data supports this, too.
更好的。他们的数据也支持这一点。
You'll actually get three times more
实际上你会得到三倍的收益
qualified applicants than if you posted
比你发布的信息能吸引更多合格的申请人
the same role for free. So, if you're
免费担任同样的角色。所以，如果你是
trying to build something truly great,
努力打造真正伟大的事物，
you can get started by posting a job for
你可以通过发布职位来开始。
free by visiting linkedin.com/doac.
访问 linkedin.com/doac 即可免费获取。
That's linkedin.com/dac
那是 linkedin.com/dac
and you can post your role for free
您可以免费发布您的职位信息。
there. Terms and conditions of course
那里。当然，条款和条件也包含在内。
apply. How much do I need to understand
申请。我需要了解多少？
what's going on in the wider world and
世界范围内正在发生什么？
the economy in order to understand my
为了理解我的经济状况
own spending behaviors? What I should
自己的消费习惯？我应该
spend on, how to get wealthy, how to
花钱的方式、如何致富、如何
save? Is it important to have any
节省？拥有任何东西都重要吗？
understanding around the macro? Because
对宏观经济的理解？因为
most people that listen to this show
大多数收听这个节目的人
will probably hear these terms being
你可能会听到这些术语。
spouted out on by political commentators
政治评论员们大肆宣扬
like the Federal Reserve, interest
就像美联储一样，利率
rates,
利率
&gt;&gt; tariffs, etc. And
关税等等。
should I understand any of this? Should
我应该能理解这些吗？应该
does any of it really impact me in a way
这些事真的会对我产生什么影响吗？
that matters to me and my family?
这对我以及我的家人来说很重要吗？
&gt;&gt; I don't think it's necessary. And you
我觉得没必要。你呢
could point to people I've written about
可以指出我写过的人。
in my books who had no financial
在我看来，那些没有经济能力的人，在我看来都是如此。
education, no training, did not read the
教育程度不高，没有接受过培训，也没有阅读过相关书籍。
Wall Street Journal, could not tell you
《华尔街日报》无法告诉你
how the Federal Reserve works, but they
美联储的运作方式，但是他们
had control of their psychology, control
控制了他们的心理，控制
of their emotions, they they worked
他们表达了自己的情绪，他们努力工作
hard, they saved their money, they
他们很努力，省吃俭用，他们
invested it, and that that's all you
你投资了，仅此而已。
need. They you you you so the answer is
需要。他们你你你，所以答案是
you don't need to know how this works.
你不需要知道它是如何运作的。
Just in the same way that in order to be
就像为了成为……一样
healthy, you don't need a PhD in
健康并不需要博士学位
biology. You don't need to understand
生物学。你不需要理解
how cell division works in order to be
细胞分裂是如何进行的？
in good shape. And I think it's the same
状况良好。我觉得是一样的。
for the economy. And it can actually
对经济而言。而且它确实可以
backfire for a lot of people that once
对很多人来说，这曾经是适得其反的事情。
they start reading the Wall Street
他们开始阅读《华尔街日报》。
Journal and learning a bit about
写日记并了解一些相关知识
finance, it increases their confidence
金融领域，这能增强他们的信心。
more than their ability. So they're
超出了他们的能力范围。所以他们是
like, "Oh, like I read the Wall Street
比如，“哦，就像我读过华尔街日报一样”
Journal. I should go day trade crypto
杂志。我应该去做加密货币日内交易。
now
现在
&gt;&gt; because I read a thing that teaches me
因为我读了一篇文章，它教会了我很多东西。
how the Federal Reserve works. So now
美联储的运作方式。现在
like I'm going to It increases your
就像我要去的那样，它会增加你的
confidence more than your skill."
自信比技巧更重要。
&gt;&gt; That's so interesting. And so I I I
真有趣。所以，我我我
think it's important to be an informed
我认为了解情况很重要
citizen and the Federal Reserve impacts
公民和美联储的影响
your life and tariffs impact your life.
你的生活和关税都会影响你的生活。
So it's important to have some baseline
所以，设定一些基准线很重要。
understanding, but I think that's more
我能理解，但我认为这更……
about being an informed citizen and
关于做一个知情公民
informed voter than it is having
比现在更了解情况的选民
financial skill.
金融技能。
&gt;&gt; Of all of my best friends, there's like
在我所有最好的朋友中，有一位是……
five or six of them, the one that's most
其中五六个，最……
catch cash is the one that knows the
抓住现金的人知道
least about I think he's the most rich
至少我认为他是最富有的。
period to be honest. He's the one that
坦白地说，就此打住。他就是那个人
knows the least about finance and he
他对金融一窍不通，而且
knows the least about investing. He
他对投资一窍不通。他
knows the least about crypto.
他对加密货币了解最少。
&gt;&gt; Well, what's the meme of like the the
嗯，这个梗是什么？
the tail spectrum of like the poor
像穷人一样的尾部光谱
person drives a Toyota, the middle
这个人开的是丰田车，中间
person has a Porsche, a BMW, a Mercedes,
这个人拥有一辆保时捷、一辆宝马、一辆奔驰。
and the rich person goes back to Toyota
富人又回到了丰田
of like it's like whether you are very
就像你是否非常
uneducated or extremely wise, you tend
无论你受教育程度如何，或者你极其睿智，你往往
to end up,
最后，
&gt;&gt; oh, this one. Okay. And so I I think I
哦，就是这个。好的。所以我觉得我
think it it does tend to be the truth
我认为这往往是事实。
that the people who do the best
那些做得最好的人
financially either have like no
经济上要么一无所有，要么几乎没有
financial education or extreme financial
金融教育或极端金融
education. And it's a person in the
教育。而且他是其中的一个人
middle that has their confidence is
中间派拥有他们的信心
increased much faster than their
增长速度远超他们的
ability. And they're like, "Oh, no, no.
能力。他们会说：“哦，不，不。”
I I read this thing on Reddit that
我在Reddit上看到过这样一篇文章
taught me about day trading. So now I'm
教会了我如何进行日内交易。所以我现在是
going to go bet my entire net worth on
我要把我全部身家都押上去
this company I've never heard of."
这家公司我从未听说过。
&gt;&gt; So funny. But so what is it that the the
太搞笑了。那么，究竟是什么呢？
person on the left and right side of the
左右两侧的人
spectrum are both doing that is the same
频谱都在做同样的事情。
here? So for anyone that can't see, I'll
这里？所以，对于任何看不见的人，我将
put it up on the screen, but it just
把它放到屏幕上，但它只是
shows the bottom axis says net worth.
底部横轴显示的是净资产。
And it basically says that people with
它基本上是说，那些拥有
low net worth buy a Toyota, people with
低净值人士购买丰田汽车
like in the middle, that sort of middle
就像中间那种中间地带
percentage by Lamborghinis and Porsches
兰博基尼和保时捷所占比例
and Jaguars, and then people with
还有捷豹，以及那些人
extremely high net worths buy Toyotas.
极少数高净值人士会购买丰田汽车。
And obviously it's it's metaphor. It's
显然，这是一种比喻。它是
not it's not it's not exactly perfectly
不，它不是，它并不完全完美
true, but I think people like a lot of
没错，但我认为人们喜欢很多
comedy you see it like it's funny
喜剧，你看它就像觉得好笑一样。
because people are like, "Yes, that's
因为人们会说：“是的，就是这样。”
true. That's how it works." I think a
真的。事情就是这样运作的。”我认为
lot of it is like the richer you become,
很多时候，情况就像你越富有，
you realize that the big house and the
你意识到那座大房子和
fancy car didn't do anything for you. It
那辆豪车对你来说毫无意义。它
did. It didn't give you what you thought
做过。它并没有给你想要的结果。
it was going to give you. And then so
它本来会给你的。然后就是这样
you're like, "Look, I'm just going to go
你会想，“听着，我这就走。”
back to utility." Like status didn't do
回归实用性。”就像地位没有起到作用一样。
it for me, so I'm going to go back to
对我来说是这样，所以我打算回去。
utility. It can also be the case that if
公用事业。也可能出现这种情况：
you're successful and rich, you can gain
你成功又富有，你可以获得
your admiration and your attention
你的钦佩和你的关注
through what the business that you built
通过你所建立的业务
or the intelligence that you have or the
或者你拥有的智力，或者
the friendship that you can offer others
你能给予他人的友谊
and therefore your desire to be like
因此，你渴望成为那样的人。
look at my car look how cool my car is
看看我的车，看看我的车多酷！
just goes down from there.
从那以后就一路下滑了。
&gt;&gt; The way I also interpret it is that when
我的另一种理解是，当
you're when you don't have much money or
当你没多少钱的时候，或者
when you don't have a huge financial
当你没有雄厚的经济实力时
understanding like my friend, you end up
就像我的朋友一样，你最终会……
playing the really boring money games.
玩那些非常无聊的赌博游戏。
Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And when you have a huge financial
当你拥有巨额资金时
understanding, you probably also spend a
理解了这一点，你可能也花费了……
lot of time playing the boring money
花费大量时间玩无聊的钱
games. And by boring money games, I mean
游戏。我说的无聊的赌博游戏是指
index funds.
指数基金。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And the S&amp;P 500 versus like crypto.
以及标普500指数与加密货币的对比。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. I think you'll see that in
是的。我想你会在……中看到这一点。
investing that like the absolute lay
投资就像绝对的下注
person will invest in index funds. And
这个人会投资指数基金。和
the extremely experienced Wall Street
经验丰富的华尔街
veteran will invest in index funds as
这位老兵将投资指数基金。
well. And it's a person in the middle
出色地。中间这个人
that just has like a little bit of
那只是有一点点
intelligence, a little bit of
智力，一点点
experience, a little bit of information
经验，一点信息
that's trying as hard as they can to
他们正在尽最大努力
outperform the market.
跑赢市场。
&gt;&gt; I kind of learned that from reading your
我大概是从你的文章里学到这一点的。
your book, The Psychology of Money,
你的著作《金钱心理学》
because I I think like many people
因为我的想法和很多人一样
thought there was some trick or hack
我以为有什么技巧或窍门。
that this book was going to teach me to
这本书本该教会我……
figure out how to trade coins at the
弄清楚如何在……交易硬币
right time or to like do forex trading
合适的时机，或者像做外汇交易一样。
or whatever. But ultimately the book, if
或者其他什么。但归根结底，这本书，如果
there was one overarching lesson it
其中有一个贯穿始终的教训。
taught me was that like patience and uh
教会我的就是耐心之类的东西，呃……
more boring investing is is the way to
更枯燥的投资方式是……
get to build my wealth over the long
长期积累财富
term and that like all other strategies
期限，而且像所有其他策略一样。
have
有
hidden trade-offs which lead you to
隐藏的权衡取舍会引导你
being broke. Yeah, I think there's a
身无分文。是的，我认为有一个
truth too that like there's a there's an
事实也一样，就像有一个……
optimal level of intelligence that you
你的最佳智力水平
want for investing where you want to be
想在你想去的地方投资
smart enough to understand the basics
聪明到足以理解基本概念
but not so smart that the basics bore
但又不至于聪明到让基础知识都变得枯燥乏味。
you. And a lot of people get so smart
你。很多人都变得非常聪明
that they're like look index funds
它们就像指数基金一样。
compound interest like I'm putting like
就像我所说的复利一样
it's too boring. Like I I need something
太无聊了。就像我需要什么东西一样
really complex to satisfy the
要满足这个要求真的非常复杂
intelligence that I have. And I I think
我所拥有的智力。而且我认为
there's a sweet spot where like for me
对我来说，存在一个最佳平衡点。
I'm just like ah index funds and
我就喜欢指数基金之类的东西。
compound interest like that's that's
像这样的复利就是如此。
kind of as high as my intelligence goes
差不多就是我智力所能达到的最高水平了。
here.
这里。
&gt;&gt; But I [clears throat] think the truth is
但我认为（清了清嗓子）真相是
that that is the best position to be in.
这是最佳的处境。
Smart enough to understand the basics
聪明到足以理解基本概念
but not so smart that they become boring
但他们又不会聪明到让人觉得无聊。
to you because once they're boring to
对你来说，因为一旦他们变得无聊了
you, you're just like ah sweep those
你，你就像啊，扫荡那些
away. Let's try to pull some more levers
离开。我们再试试拉动一些控制杆。
here.
这里。
&gt;&gt; What is going on in the world at the
世界正在发生什么？
moment Morgan? There's um it feels like
摩根，你好吗？感觉好像……
people are more divided than ever before
人们比以往任何时候都更加分裂。
and I feel like a lot of these subjects
我觉得很多这类主题
we talk about are somewhat
我们谈论的在某种程度上
interconnected. It feels like there's a
互联。感觉好像有
rise in inequality. You probably know
不平等加剧。你可能知道
the numbers better than I do. Um I mean
他们比我更懂数字。嗯，我的意思是
there's a graph in front of you there
你面前有一张图表。
which shows I think it's is it wage
这表明我认为这是工资问题。
growth?
生长？
&gt;&gt; Yes, monthly wage growth.
是的，月工资增长。
&gt;&gt; Monthly wage from
月薪
&gt;&gt; about 25 years
大约25年
&gt;&gt; and it appears to be going down.
而且似乎还在下降。
&gt;&gt; Well, but this is growth. So in any
嗯，但这本身就是一种成长。所以在任何情况下
given year, even if the growth is 2%,
即使某一年增长率只有2%，
that's 2% higher than the previous year.
比上一年高出2%。
So this is not wages over time. Now, it
所以这不是工资随时间的变化。现在，它
is true that if you look over a 25-year
确实，如果你回顾过去25年的情况。
period and you took the average American
就这么简单，你选取了美国普通民众。
family, not everybody, but the median,
家人，不是所有人，而是大多数人。
&gt;&gt; that their wages adjusted for inflation
他们的工资已根据通货膨胀进行了调整。
have gone up. Not not up as much as
已经上涨了。没那么高
people would want over 25 years, but
人们希望超过25年，但是
that that they are better off than they
他们比以前过得更好了
were 25 years ago. What is also true is
那是25年前的事了。还有一点也是真的：
that the average median family would
平均而言，中位数家庭会
probably disagree with that statement
我可能不同意这种说法。
even if it is true statistically for
即使从统计学角度来看这是真的
several reasons. One of which is their
原因有很多。其中之一是他们的
expectations have gone up over the last
过去一段时间以来，人们的期望值不断提高。
25 years. The other is even if you're
25年。另一种情况是，即使你是
looking at average wages
从平均工资的角度来看
average and when we talk about these
平均而言，当我们谈论这些时
statistics does not refer to any
统计数据不涉及任何
specific family. This is just a
特定家族。这只是一个
statistical number. Everyone spends
统计数字。每个人都要花钱
their money differently. So, if I told
他们对金钱的态度不同。所以，如果我说
you, "Hey, average family, you're richer
你，“嘿，普通家庭，你们更富有。”
than you were in the year 2000." And
比你在2000年时要好得多。”
they're like, "Yeah, but I'm trying to
他们会说：“是啊，但我正在努力……”
put my kids through college, and have
我供孩子们上大学，而且
you seen the price of college?" And
你了解大学学费吗？
like, yeah, that might be true because
嗯，这或许是真的，因为
the price of TVs has gone down, but have
电视机的价格下降了，但是……
you seen the price of rent and housing?
你了解房租和房价吗？
Like, at the individual level, these
例如，就个人层面而言，这些
statistics don't really mean that much
统计数据其实意义不大。
and never have. I think a lot of
而且从来没有过。我认为很多
economists get into a problem with that
经济学家们在这方面遇到了问题。
when they're like, "Well, statistically,
当他们说：“嗯，从统计学角度来看，
X, Y, and Z has happened." But ignoring
X、Y 和 Z 都发生了。” 但忽略
the psychology and the individuality of
心理学和个性
like what's happening actually on the
比如，实际上正在发生的事情
ground in people's heads and how they
人们头脑中根深蒂固的想法以及他们如何看待这些想法
spend their money, there's a there's
花他们的钱，那里有
just endless amount of nuance in here.
这里面蕴含着无穷无尽的细微差别。
And so I think it's it's always been
所以我认为一直以来都是如此。
true that we live in a world where over
的确，我们生活在一个……的世界。
long periods of time there's good
长时间都有好处
economic growth. We become wealthier. We
经济增长。我们变得更富有了。我们
be we have bigger better things. We have
但我们还有更大更好的东西。我们有
more income. We have better medicine.
收入增加。我们有更好的药物。
It's equally true too that like there is
同样地，就像存在一样……
always something legitimate to complain
总有理由抱怨。
about and it's legitimate to complain
对此感到不满是合理的，而且抱怨也是无可厚非的。
about. It's not just like oh you should
关于。这不仅仅是“哦，你应该……”那么简单。
be more grateful. It's a real thing. And
要懂得感恩。这是真的。和
so when I look at a graph like this
所以当我看到这样的图表时
actually what like if I was thinking
实际上，如果我在想什么呢？
just like with my math head I'd be like
就像我那数学头脑一样，我会说：
oh there's been quite a bit of growth
哦，增长相当显著。
over the last 25 years. Like the growth
过去25年。就像生长一样
has been gone up and down but it's
价格有起有落，但总体来说
growth. You know never in this chart is
生长。你知道这张图表中永远不会出现
growth below zero. I guess the question
增长率低于零。我想这个问题
there is are rich people getting richer
有富人越来越富。
and are the poor getting poorer?
穷人是不是越来越穷了？
&gt;&gt; It depends. I mean it's at the indiv are
这取决于。我的意思是，这是在个人层面上。
rich are the rich getting richer? Yes.
富人越来越富了吗？是的。
Are the poor getting poorer?
穷人越来越穷了吗？
Statistically no.
统计上没有。
&gt;&gt; Even adjusted for inflation.
即使考虑通货膨胀因素后也是如此。
&gt;&gt; I mean it it depends what period we're
我的意思是，这取决于我们处于哪个时期。
talking about here. There was about a 20
就在这里说。大约有20
or 30 year period where the answer was
或者30年期间，答案是
unequivocally yes. There was an
毫无疑问，是的。曾有一个
interesting trend over the last 10 years
过去十年来的有趣趋势
where in percentage terms the the group
以百分比表示，该组
of of wage earners who had the highest
收入最高的工薪阶层
percentage growth were actually the low
实际增长率很低
wage. That was true for two or three
工资。这种情况持续了两到三个人。
years after COVID where if you were a
新冠疫情爆发数年后，如果你是……
low if you were a minimum wage worker
如果你是最低工资劳动者，那收入就很低了。
those were in percentage terms great
从百分比来看，这些都很棒。
years for you for getting wages. It's
你花了多年时间才拿到工资。它是
tapered off. So I the answer to your
逐渐减弱。所以，你的答案就是我。
question is the rich are getting richer.
问题是富人越来越富了。
The poor, I think, are treading water by
我认为，穷人只是在原地踏步。
and large. There's there's always people
而且很大。总会有人。
who are doing differently than that. But
他们的做法与此不同。但
when one group of society is getting
当社会中的一个群体获得
richer, treading water feels like you're
更富有，原地踏步的感觉就像你在……
falling. And the the specifics of how
坠落。以及具体操作方法
people spend their money, so even if on
人们花钱，所以即使在
average adjusted for inflation, their
经通胀调整后的平均值
wages are flat. But if your rent
工资水平停滞不前。但如果你租房
skyrocketed or you're trying to send
价格飙升，或者你正试图发送
your kids through college or you have a
你的孩子上大学或者你有……
long commute and you got to put gas in
通勤时间长，而且还得加油。
your tank, at the individual level,
你的油箱，就个人而言，
things can feel very very different from
事情的感觉可能与以往截然不同。
what the statistics show.
统计数据显示了什么。
&gt;&gt; And what role do you think this sort of
你认为这种类型扮演着什么角色？
wealth inequality that is widening
日益扩大的财富不平等
between the very very top and everybody
从最高层到所有人
else is playing in everything that we're
其他的一切都在我们的掌控之中
seeing play out at the moment? Because
目前的情况如何？因为
in the UK, it's almost like there's
在英国，几乎就像……
we're on like the verge of riots it
我们正处于暴乱的边缘。
seems. And I think last last month there
似乎如此。我觉得上个月那里
was millions of people in London
当时伦敦有数百万人。
protesting against immigrants coming
抗议移民涌入
over on boats and society becoming more
关于船只和社会变得越来越
multicultural. I'm so fascinated by this
多元文化。我对此非常着迷。
subject because you know earlier on we
主题是因为你知道，我们之前……
said that unless you have immigration in
他说，除非你有移民局。
the western world you have population
西方世界人口众多
decline and if you have
拒绝，如果你有
&gt;&gt; and population decline sucks
人口下降真糟糕。
&gt;&gt; because you have a hit on GDP
因为这会对GDP造成冲击。
&gt;&gt; the biggest problem right now throughout
目前最大的问题是……
a lot of the world at least one of the
世界上很多地方至少有一个
biggest perceived problems is
人们普遍认为最大的问题是
immigration
移民
&gt;&gt; and the same is playing out in the
同样的情况也正在发生
United States if I go on X although I
如果我去美国 X 虽然我
know I know what X is um it's people
我知道我知道X是什么，嗯，是人。
maybe it's just my algorithm but it's
也许只是我的算法问题，但确实如此。
people attacking immigrants and
攻击移民的人
immigration and people that are brown
移民和有色人种
and black and whatever else it might be
还有黑色，以及其他任何颜色。
I'm wondering how all of this is
我想知道这一切是怎么回事。
intertwined and and if it if it is
交织在一起，而且如果它是
connected at all in your view.
在你看来，它们完全连接在一起。
&gt;&gt; I think as a amateur student of history
我认为，作为一个业余历史爱好者，我应该这样想。
across cultures all over the place all
跨越所有文化
through history what you want to avoid
纵观历史，你想避免什么？
more than anything in society is when
社会中最重要的事情莫过于此。
probably a third of the population wakes
大约三分之一的人口醒来
up every morning and says this isn't
每天早上醒来都说这不是
working. That's the point at which it's
在职的。那就是关键点。
gonna collapse from there is when enough
到那时就会崩溃，直到足够的时候。
people wake up in the morning and just
人们早上醒来，然后就……
have this feeling of like whatever this
有一种感觉，就像这样
is, it's not working out for me. You
是的，这对我来说行不通。你
want to avoid that part. And so, like,
想避开那部分。所以，就像，
look, I'm a I tend to be a a free
你看，我倾向于自由自在。
markets guy. I'm a capitalist. I think
市场人。我是个资本家。我认为
people should be able to become very
人们应该能够变得非常
wealthy, etc., etc. You also don't want
富有等等等等。你也不想
to get to a point where people become so
达到这样一个地步：人们变得如此
wealthy that a big chunk of society just
富裕阶层占据了社会很大一部分人的份额
wakes up every morning and says, "Fuck
每天早上醒来都会说：“操”
this. This is not this is not going to
这。这不是，这不会是
work out for me." And I think we've got
对我来说很合适。”而且我认为我们已经做到了。
we've we're either there or precariously
我们要么已经到达目的地，要么处境岌岌可危。
close to there. In a lot of areas in the
就在附近。在许多地区
world, social media, that's always been
世界，社交媒体，一直都是如此。
the case. And social media makes it 100
案件。而社交媒体则使之达到100%。
times worse than it's ever been.
情况比以往任何时候都糟糕得多。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; For example, you and I are recording
例如，你我正在录音
this a day after Charlie Kirk was
这是查理·柯克去世后的第二天。
assassinated yesterday.
昨天遇刺身亡。
And there were who knows what number
还有谁知道有多少人
percentage it was, but I think it was
百分比是肯定的，但我认为……
not hard on social media to find people
在社交媒体上找到人并不难。
who were celebrating it yesterday. Now,
昨天庆祝的人。现在，
when Martin Luther King was
马丁·路德·金
assassinated, did those people exist too
被暗杀的人，他们也存在吗？
who celebrated assassination? Of course.
谁在庆祝刺杀事件？当然。
But because of social media, by and
但由于社交媒体，以及
large, you did not hear from them unless
规模很大，除非你收到他们的消息，否则你不会收到他们的任何消息。
you were part of that group. Whereas
你曾是那个团体的一员。然而
today, virtually everybody yesterday saw
今天，昨天几乎每个人都看到了
people celebrating Charlie Kirk's
人们庆祝查理·柯克
assassination. And so, even if those
暗杀。所以，即使那些
feelings existed in the past, they're
这些感情存在于过去，它们是
much more apparent today. You see them
如今这一点更加明显。你看到他们了
today in a way that that you did not
今天你以一种你没有的方式
before. So, because of that, it's easy
前。所以，正因如此，这很容易。
to say we're more divided today. We're
也就是说，我们今天的社会更加分裂了。是
more extreme today. were more
如今情况更加极端。更
pessimistic than they today. I think the
比他们今天更悲观。我认为
nuance is that's not actually true.
微妙之处在于，这实际上并非事实。
You're just more aware of it. That those
你只是对此更加敏感了。那些
feelings always existed. They existed in
情感一直都存在。它们存在于
the 1990s. They existed in the 1950s. It
20世纪90年代。它们存在于20世纪50年代。它
was just much easier to contain those.
控制那些东西要容易得多。
And for the average citizen who got
而对于普通公民来说，他们得到了
their information from one newspaper,
他们的信息来源是一份报纸。
one evening news program to feel like
看一集晚间新闻节目，感觉就像
things were much more stable and in
情况稳定得多，而且
control and that people were much more
控制，以及人们更加
uniform in their opinions than they
他们的观点比他们更一致
actually were. Before we start
确实如此。在我们开始之前
recording, we were talking about the
录音的时候，我们正在谈论……
Charlie Kirk shooting and how
查理·柯克枪击案及相关情况
social media's ability to dehumanize
社交媒体使人丧失人性的能力
other people at a probably a faster rate
其他人可能速度更快
than history would have done it is
比历史本应做的还要好。
pretty remarkable. And you see a lot of
非常了不起。你会看到很多
that. You see a lot of it taking place
那。你会看到很多这样的事情发生。
on both sides. I think both sides
双方都是如此。我认为双方都是如此
describe each other as being like
互相形容对方就像
animals and inhumane. and one side's
虐待动物，不人道。以及一方的
calling the other side Nazis and then
称对方为纳粹，然后
the other side is calling the other side
对方正在呼叫对方
referring to them in in animal terms
用动物的语言来指代它们
because of maybe the color of their skin
或许是因为他们的肤色
or their behavior. We saw a lot of that
或他们的行为。我们看到了很多这样的情况。
when the that heinous individual killed
当那个罪大恶极的人被杀害时
the young lady on the on the the train
火车上的那位年轻女士
in in America
在美国
&gt;&gt; and the way look this person is the
这个人看起来是
[__] this worst thing on planet
操他妈的这星球上最糟糕的东西
earth. Um but the language was very
地球。嗯，但是语言非常……
it was putting that person in a group of
就是把那个人放到一个群体中
other people.
别人。
&gt;&gt; Yes.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And then making the whole group a pack
然后将整个群体变成一个整体
of animals.
动物。
&gt;&gt; Right. Because in that situation too, we
正确的。因为在那种情况下，我们
talked about this earlier. I I don't
之前已经谈过这个问题了。我不
know that individual's name doesn't
知道那个人的名字并不重要
matter, but no one refers to him by his
这件事本身并没有什么特别之处，但没有人会这样称呼他。
name. It's them. It's they. And that
姓名。就是他们。就是他们。而那
once you dehumanize any group of people
一旦你将任何一群人非人化
like that, and this has been the case
就是这样，而且一直都是这样。
for all of human history, that 99.9% of
纵观人类历史，99.9%
people cannot kill another human, but
人不能杀害另一个人，但是
they're perfectly fine killing them.
他们杀了他们完全没问题。
They that group once you dehumanize, you
一旦你将他们非人化，你
can do anything. And at the at a much
可以做到任何事。而且在很多方面
lower level, everyone realizes this with
较低层次的人，每个人都意识到了这一点。
road rage. I've had road rage. The
路怒症。我曾有过路怒症。这
person cut me off. Son of a [__]
有人插队了我。王八蛋。
Honor, flip. I I I don't I don't get too
荣誉，翻转。我，我，我不，我不会太
extreme with it. But in things I would
非常极端。但在某些事情上，我会
never do eye to eye. But once I'm
永远不要和对方意见一致。但一旦我
looking at a car, then it's it's there's
看着一辆车，然后它就在那里
no human there. And my ability to have a
那里没有人。以及我拥有的能力
level of anger is so much higher than it
愤怒程度远高于此
would be if we were just looking eye to
如果我们只是眼神交流，那会怎样呢？
eye. I had this experience a couple
眼睛。我曾有过这样的经历。
years ago where I was pulling into a gas
几年前，我正要驶入一个加油站。
station and I inadvertently cut somebody
车站里，我不小心割伤了某人。
off. It was an accident, but I totally
离开。那是一场意外，但我完全
cut them off and he honked and threw up
他切断了他们的连接，然后按喇叭，接着呕吐了。
his middle finger at me. And um we since
他朝我竖起了中指。而且，嗯，自从
we pulled into the same gas station, we
我们把车开进了同一家加油站，我们
were now like eye to eye and I walked
我们现在就像四目相对，我走了过去。
over to him and I think he thought I was
我把注意力转向他，我想他以为我是
like coming to like confront him and I
就像要来和他对峙一样，而我
put up my hands. I said, "I just want to
举起双手。我说：“我只想……”
apologize. I didn't I didn't mean to cut
道歉。我不是故意要割伤的
you off. I'm so sorry. I did." It was
你走开。我很抱歉。我确实这么做了。
not on purpose. And he I think he was so
并非故意的。我觉得他就是这样的人。
surprised and he was like, "Wow, thank
他很惊讶，然后说：“哇，谢谢。”
you. Thanks for like and we had this
你。谢谢你的点赞，我们一起度过了美好的时光。
moment of like almost hugging of just
那一刻，仿佛近乎拥抱。
like a I'm so like I hope hope you have
就像我一样，我希望你也有
a great day." It was one of those of
真是美好的一天。” 那是其中之一。
like once in the moment when it was you
就像有一次，就在那一刻，是你
strip the humanity off it when it was
剥夺它的人性，当它……
two cars each other both of us were like
两辆车彼此相邻，我们俩就像
[__] you once we looked eye to eye it
去你的，我们目光交汇之后
was like oh brother like it's okay it's
当时的感觉就像是“哦，老兄，没关系，没事的”。
okay I think that was just like for me
好吧，我觉得那对我来说就是这样。
that was an individual example of what
那是一个具体的例子，说明了什么
happens at society when you strip the
当你剥夺社会……时，就会发生这种情况。
humanity off it we're capable of so much
人类摆脱了这种状态，我们拥有如此多的能力。
anger and hate eye to eye we're like oh
愤怒和仇恨面对面，我们就像……哦
that's all good and I think all of us
那都很好，我想我们所有人都会这么想。
know somebody who we disagree with
认识一个与我们意见相左的人
politically regardless of what it might
从政治角度来看，无论它可能是什么
be and it's easy to be like oh person's
成为，而且很容易像哦，某人那样。
an idiot. They're stupid. They're
一个白痴。他们很愚蠢。他们是
ill-informed. And actually, if you sit
消息不灵通。实际上，如果你坐着
down and talk to them, you're like, "Ah,
下来和他们谈谈，你会说：“啊，
look, we might have some disagreements
你看，我们之间可能存在一些分歧。
here, but it's all good. Cheers. Let's
这里，不过一切都很好。干杯。我们开始吧
have a good night." Like, eye to eye,
祝你晚安。”就像，眼神交流一样，
the vast majority of people get along
绝大多数人都能和睦相处。
and get together. But social media has
大家聚在一起。但社交媒体已经
turned all of life into road rage.
把生活中的一切都变成了路怒症。
&gt;&gt; Gosh. Yeah. I mean, you know that more
天哪。是的。我的意思是，你知道，更多的
starkly than anyone as a podcaster
比任何人都更像播客主播
because I sit here with everybody of all
因为我和所有人一起坐在这里
political opinions, extreme left, you
政治观点，极左，你
know, pretty extreme right. And at this
我知道，这相当极端。而此时
table, we get along,
餐桌旁，我们相处融洽，
&gt;&gt; right? We even off camera we get along.
正确的？即使在镜头之外，我们也相处得很好。
&gt;&gt; I [laughter] think so many people have
我（笑）觉得很多人都有
said this in the last 24 hours about
在过去24小时内说过这番话
Charlie Kirk.
查理·柯克。
&gt;&gt; One of the most common phrases I've
我最常听到的短语之一是
heard was I didn't agree with everything
据说我并非完全赞同所有观点。
he said, but at least he was brave
他说，但他至少很勇敢。
enough to have a conversation with
足以与人交谈
people who he disagreed with. That was
他意见不合的人。那是
what he did by and large was going into
他所做的基本上都是进入
schools and being like, I know you
学校，还有那种感觉，我知道你
disagree with me. Let's talk.
我不同意你的观点。我们来谈谈吧。
&gt;&gt; And and he turned it from road rage into
他把路怒症变成了
a conversation between people. And even
人与人之间的对话。甚至
if you disagreed with him,
如果你不同意他的观点，
&gt;&gt; I think he did it very right in that
我认为他在这方面做得非常好。
sense. And I think that's what's why
感觉。我想这就是原因所在。
people from all over the spectrum are
来自各行各业的人们
devastated in the last 24 hours. It was
过去24小时内遭受重创。那是
like he was one of the people who was
就好像他是那些人中的一员一样
doing it right. Even when you disagreed
做对了。即使你们意见不一致
with them, he was having a conversation
他当时正在和他们交谈。
face to face and bringing people
面对面地把人们聚集在一起
together.
一起。
&gt;&gt; I think that absolutely hits the nail on
我觉得这完全说中了要害。
the head which is I think, you know,
头部，我想，你知道，
there's things that I absolutely don't
有些事我绝对不会
agree with him on. But I actually think
同意他的观点。但我其实觉得
that's just completely beside the point
那完全是跑题了。
because I want to live in a world where
因为我想生活在一个这样的世界里：
there's people that I disagree with.
有些人我并不认同。
Like I actually wouldn't choose the
我真的不会选择
world where everyone I encountered
在这个世界里，我遇到的每个人都在经历着同样的事情。
agreed with my opinions. There would be
同意我的观点。将会有
no intellectual growth. There'd be no
没有智力发展。不会有
understanding. there been no real
理解。没有真正的
progress. Um, but also as you've
进步。嗯，但正如你所看到的
highlighted the way that Charlie Kirk
重点介绍了查理·柯克
went about it was he would went to
他采取的方式是他会去
Oxford University and went on the
牛津大学，并继续深造
formalized debate panel against
反对正式辩论小组
&gt;&gt; hi in an office and a pine on social
嗨，办公室里有人，社交媒体上有人在发帖
media. He went face to face and said I
媒体。他走上前去，面对面说道：
know you disagree with me.
我知道你不同意我的观点。
&gt;&gt; Let's have a Yeah. And I'll listen to
好啊。我会听的。
what you He wasn't interrupting people
你说什么？他没有打断别人。
all the time. He's hearing out their
一直如此。他正在听取他们的意见。
points and he was making
他正在得分，而且他正在证明自己。
&gt;&gt; respectful about it. And what is missing
对此表示尊重。还有什么缺失呢？
from all political discourse today, it's
从当今所有的政治论述来看，是
that. It's I know you disagree, but
那。我知道你不同意，但是……
let's talk and let's try to be
我们来谈谈，我们试着……
respectful about it.
对此表示尊重。
&gt;&gt; And I can't think of [clears throat]
我想不起来[清嗓子]
anyone
任何人
on either side who who did that as
双方谁做了这件事
consistently as he did,
就像他一直以来所做的那样，
&gt;&gt; even if I disagree with him.
即使我不同意他的观点。
The idea that we're only going to talk
我们只会谈论的想法
to people who we agree with is what
对我们意见一致的人来说，这才是最重要的。
causes all the problems.
造成所有问题的根源。
&gt;&gt; I don't understand these [__] people.
我真搞不懂这些人。
I don't understand. It's much more
我不明白。远不止如此
comfortable
舒服的
to surround yourself with people who
让自己身边围绕着这样的人
agree with you than to accept the nuance
与其说是接受你的意见，不如说是更愿意接受其中的细微差别。
of life. And this is the problem with a
生命。这就是问题所在
lot of political media is that it
很多政治媒体就是这样。
creates much better content when people
当人们……时，就能创造出更好的内容。
say this is right, this is wrong, he's
他说这是对的，这是错的，他是
right, he's wrong, to make it very
没错，他错了，这么说很……
explicit, binary, black and white, than
明确的、二元的、黑白的，而不是
it is to accept the truth, which is like
接受真相就像……
it's complicated.
情况很复杂。
&gt;&gt; I think I was like traumatized yesterday
我觉得我昨天受到了很大的精神创伤。
when I watched that when I saw the video
当我看到那段视频时
of him being shot. I think it was this
他被枪击了。我想应该是这样
weird like deep sense of like like uh
很奇怪，就像一种很深的、类似……的感觉
I've not been able to articulate what it
我一直无法清楚地表达它是什么。
is, but it was I don't know Charlie
是的，但我不知道查理是谁。
Kirk. I've never met him. There was a
柯克。我从未见过他。曾有一个
time when, you know, we were potentially
你知道，那段时间我们可能
going to have him on the show and we
我们会邀请他上节目，我们
were trying to figure out like, you
我们当时想弄清楚，比如，你
know, who to who to have here with him
知道，该让谁陪在他身边。
because he's such an unbelievable
因为他真是个不可思议的人
debater that he would run [__] rings
辩论者说他会赢得所有比赛
around me.
我周围。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; I was like, who can you put to
我当时就想，你能把谁放进去呢？
&gt;&gt; You'd be like you'd be like, fine, I'm
你会说，好吧，我
conservative. [laughter]
保守的。 [笑声]
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
But there was something really
但确实有些事……
surprising in how I felt when I when I
当我……的时候，我的感受让我感到惊讶。
both heard the news and saw um him being
他们俩都听到了消息，也看到了他。
shot. This young guy, family person who
射击。这个年轻人，顾家，
was out debating, who had ideas that
当时正在外面辩论，谁有想法……
many people disagreed with, but was in a
许多人不同意，但他却身处其中
forum where he was having them
他当时正在论坛上和他们交流。
challenged, could be executed in public
如果有人质疑，可能会被公开处决。
on live stream in a way that his
在直播中以一种他的方式
children are going to watch that video
孩子们会看那个视频
when they grow up, probably multiple
当他们长大后，可能会有多个
times. And I was like, "Oh god, what?"
次数。我当时就想，“我的天，怎么回事？”
Yeah. What does this say about the
是的。这说明了什么？
society we live in and where we're
我们所处的社会以及我们所在的地方
heading? You know, I know guns play a
标题？你知道，我知道枪支在……
huge role in this and we have to
这其中我们扮演着至关重要的角色，我们必须……
acknowledge that because it's very very
承认这一点，因为它非常非常
unlikely that could have happened in the
这种事不太可能发生。
UK because no, we don't have guns there.
英国，因为那里没有枪支。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; So, you could have thrown a rock or
所以，你本来可以扔一块石头，或者
something, but you couldn't have killed
某种东西，但你不可能杀死它
the guy.
那个人。
&gt;&gt; But it it's almost a it feels like a
但这几乎就像……感觉就像……
crescendo of the moment. Yeah.
此刻的高潮。是的。
&gt;&gt; Where division and algorithms and now
划分和算法以及现在
that, you know, X has gone a certain way
你知道，X已经走上了某条道路。
and other platforms are going certain
其他平台也正在朝着这个方向发展。
ways. And if you look at the stats,
方法。如果你看一下统计数据，
there's more social networks now that
现在有更多社交网络了。
have more than 20 million active users
拥有超过2000万活跃用户
than at any time in human history. It's
比人类历史上任何时期都更加如此。它是
gone up by 50% in recent times, which
近期上涨了50%，
means we're becoming more splintered.
这意味着我们变得越来越分裂。
And then if you if you understand the
如果你理解了
commercial models of these algorithms,
这些算法的商业模型
their commercial model is dependent on
他们的商业模式依赖于
you spending more time there. So, how do
你在那里待的时间更长。那么，该如何……
I get you to spend more time there?
我让你多花点时间在那里？
Well, I give you more of the things that
嗯，我再给你讲讲这些东西……
are going to trigger your amydala, which
这会刺激你的杏仁核，而
is, you know, your fear senses and and
你知道，就是你的恐惧感和……
uh the things that are going to drive,
呃，那些将要推动事情发展的事情，
you know, drive you into rage and debate
你知道，这会让你怒火中烧，引发争论。
and engagement and these and sharing
以及参与和这些分享
things. And so, I don't know. I I wonder
事物。所以，我不知道。我想知道
if there's a way back from here. I have
如果这里还有回头路的话。我有
a an optimistic view and this is not a
这是一种乐观的观点，但这并非……
forecast because I don't have 100% faith
因为我没有百分之百的把握，所以只能做出预测。
in this
在这方面
&gt;&gt; but there are so many endless examples
但这样的例子不胜枚举。
in history when people discount how
在历史上，当人们低估了这一点时
powerful cycle cycles can be and so my
强大的循环可以如此，所以我的
optimistic my hope it's not even a
乐观地认为这甚至都不是……
forecast it's a hope is that 15 or 20
预测希望是15或20
years from now we look back at this era
多年以后，当我们回首这个时代时，我们将会回顾这个时代。
as when things bottomed politically from
就像政治局势跌至谷底时一样
which we grew out of we improved and
我们逐渐摆脱了这种状况，我们改进了它，并且
we're going to look back and be like,
我们将来回首往事时会想：
man, the the 2020s were so bad and we
唉，2020年代真是太糟糕了，我们
are so divided, but that was also a
他们之间存在如此大的分歧，但这也是……
bottom that we came out of, like a
我们从谷底爬了出来，就像……
generational bottom. And that sounds
世代底线。听起来
crazy today, but that's always been the
今天真是疯狂，但一直以来都是这样。
case. If you and I were talking about
案件。如果你我谈论的是
the economy in the 1930s, it would have
如果放在20世纪30年代的经济形势下，它本应如此。
been preposterous, completely insane to
简直荒谬至极，完全是疯了
say the 1950s are going to be the
有人说1950年代将是
greatest, most unbound prosperity,
最大、最无限制的繁荣
middle class prosperity we're ever going
中产阶级的繁荣永无止境
to have. That would have seemed insane.
拥有。那在当时看来简直是疯了。
If this was the 1970s and we just had a
如果这是 20 世纪 70 年代，我们刚刚经历了一场
raft of political assassinations in the
一系列政治暗杀事件
60s, John F. Kennedy, Martin Luther
60年代，约翰·F·肯尼迪，马丁·路德
King, Robert F. Kennedy, and then
马丁·路德·金、罗伯特·F·肯尼迪，然后是……
Richard Nixon uh is impeached and
理查德·尼克松被弹劾了。
resigned for Watergate, it would have
因水门事件辞职，他本可以
been completely insane for you and I to
对你我来说，这简直太疯狂了
say, "Hey, do you know what? The 80s and
比如说，“嘿，你知道吗？80年代和
90s are going to be an era of political
90年代将是一个政治时代
stability and political faith and trust
稳定、政治信任和信心
in government." Would insane like it's
在政府部门。”这简直太疯狂了。
always when things are the lowest that
总是在事情最糟糕的时候
you feel like you're never going to
你感觉自己永远不会
recover. But if you understand how
恢复。但如果你理解了如何
cyclical things can be, it's usually the
事物往往呈循环往复的规律，通常是这样。
case that looking back, you're like,
回首往事，你可能会想：
man, it was bad. But looking back, that
天哪，情况糟透了。但回首往事，
was the bottom. And I have no idea if
是底部。我不知道是否
the bottom was yesterday or if it's
昨天触底了，或者如果是的话
going to come 10 years from now. But I
十年后即将到来。但我
would bet that the most likely scenario
我敢打赌，最有可能的情况是
whenever that bottom comes is that we
无论何时触底，那就是我们
will look 15 or 20 years back and be
回首15或20年前，你会发现
like, that was terrible. And at that
那真是太糟糕了。就这样
moment, everyone assumed it would go on
那一刻，所有人都以为它会继续下去。
forever, but looking back, that was
永远，但回首往事，那已是过去。
actually a bottom. When enough people
实际上是底部。当足够多的人
came together and said, stop, stop. This
他们聚在一起说，停，停。这
is this is too much. the forces that
这是否太过分了？这些力量
we've gone too far in the other
我们在另一个方面做得太过火了
direction. We need to we need to come
方向。我们需要，我们需要来
around from them. It is always
他们周围。总是
impossible in real time to wrap your
实时包裹你的
head around that and to forecast it.
绕道而行，并进行预测。
It's only looking back that you're like,
只有回首往事，你才会觉得：
"Yes, that was the that that there was
“是的，那就是那件事。”
the bottom." And you can see things
底部。” 你可以看到一些东西
getting so bad. Trust in government is
情况越来越糟了。对政府的信任
so low. Polarization is so high. That
太低了。极化程度非常高。那
would not surprise me in the slightest
这丝毫不会让我感到惊讶。
if we look 20 years from now and be
如果我们展望20年后，并且
like, "Oh, things things got better."
就像，“哦，情况好转了。”
&gt;&gt; I understand that from an economic
我从经济角度理解这一点。
standpoint. I I struggle with it because
立场。我为此感到困扰，因为
of the presence of how we like because
因为我们喜欢它的存在而感到高兴
of the the medium in which we
我们所使用的媒介
communicate now with social media. Yeah.
现在就通过社交媒体进行沟通。是的。
And I was looking at the some of the
我当时正在看一些……
stats here and it says in 1994 only 20%
这里有统计数据，显示1994年只有20%。
of Americans held a very unfavorable
美国人普遍持非常不利的态度
view of the other party. By 2022 that
对方的观点。到2022年，
number has jumped to 72%
数字已跃升至72%。
among Republicans and 63% among de
共和党人中63%的人支持，而民主党人中63%的人支持。
Democrats according to Pew Research. Uh
根据皮尤研究中心的数据，民主党人。呃
and this is particularly pronounced in
这一点在以下方面尤为明显：
the United States. um and and the UK and
美国。嗯，还有英国和
other parts of Europe. In this report,
欧洲其他地区。本报告中，
it says that social media um and also
它说社交媒体嗯，还有
cable news's role has only amplified
有线电视新闻的作用只会越来越大。
echo chambers, making the divide sharper
回音室效应，加剧了分歧
and more emotional.
而且更情绪化。
And I I can't especially with AI in the
尤其是在人工智能领域，我更不能……
way. I go, well, AI is going to make
方式。我说，嗯，人工智能将会……
those algorithms even smarter.
这些算法甚至更加智能。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; At understanding exactly what to show me
明白该向我展示什么
to increase my engagement, therefore
因此，为了提高我的参与度。
increase their advertising dollars. So,
增加广告投入。所以，
I'm like, what what would be the the
我当时就想，那会是什么呢？
mechanism in this context? I have no
在这种情况下，机制是什么？我没有
statistic or even strong thing to back
统计数据，甚至是强有力的证据来支持
this up with, but my gut tells me that
这件事已经过去了，但我的直觉告诉我……
the younger generation in particular is
尤其是年轻一代
going to be the one that looks at social
将会是那个关注社交的人
media and looks at AI and recognizes the
媒体关注人工智能并认识到
[__] that can come out of it. It's
由此可能产生的种种荒谬言论。它是
the older generation. It's the boomers
老一辈。是婴儿潮一代
today on social media who believe
今天在社交媒体上，那些相信的人
everything that they see. And I think
他们所看到的一切。我觉得
that tends to be where a lot of the
那往往是很多事情发生的地方
polarization comes from. not to blame
极化源于……不应责怪
everything on the older generation. But
一切都与老一代有关。但
I think if you were to look at
我认为如果你仔细观察一下……
statistically who is the most gullible
从统计学角度来看，谁最容易上当受骗？
on social media of believing every post
在社交媒体上，人们往往相信每一条帖子。
in their feed, it's the older
在他们的动态中，是较旧的那条。
generation. And it would not surprise me
一代。这不会让我感到惊讶。
if the younger generation is much more
如果年轻一代更加
attuned to how quickly you can be led
敏锐地察觉到你被引导的速度有多快
astray into some [__] rabbit hole
误入歧途，掉进了某个狗屁兔子洞
that is not reflective of how the
这并不能反映出……
broader world works. I don't know if
更广阔的世界运作。我不知道是否
that's true or not, but if you were to
不管这是真是假，但如果你……
ask me to articulate why we're going to
请你解释一下我们为什么要这样做
get around the social media bubbles, it
摆脱社交媒体的泡沫，它
would be that the generations who have
那就是那些拥有……的世代。
been doing this the longest are going to
从事这项工作时间最长的人将会
be the best at recognizing how dangerous
最擅长识别危险
it can be.
有可能。
&gt;&gt; You're a very smart guy and you're
你是个非常聪明的人，而且你
someone that studies has studied history
研究历史的人
and understands, you know, you wrote the
而且你也明白，你写了
book Same as Ever, which shows
《一如既往》这本书，展现了
a a guide to what doesn't change through
一份关于哪些东西不会改变的指南
history and how things can often stay
历史以及事物如何常常得以保留
the same. So, this is a bit bit of a
相同。所以，这有点像……
peculiar question for you, but in the
这个问题对你来说可能有点奇怪，但是……
wake of what happened to Charlie Kirk
查理·柯克事件之后
yesterday, his his public murder and all
昨天，他被公开谋杀，以及所有的一切
that's rising from that, what should
由此而来，应该是什么？
someone like me and you, who have public
像你我这样的人，拥有公共
platforms, who reach people on a daily
每天都能触达用户的平台
basis, do help?
基础，能帮上忙吗？
&gt;&gt; I think we have to remind ourselves two
我认为我们必须提醒自己两点。
things about social media. One is that
关于社交媒体的一些事情。一是
it's been designed by the smartest
它由最聪明的人设计。
people of our generation to deliver you
我们这一代人将为您服务
in your feed not the best information,
你的信息流里没有最好的信息。
not the right information. Basically,
信息有误。基本上，
what's going to give you the most FOMO,
什么会让你产生最大的错失恐惧感（FOMO）？
the most anxiety, what's going to like
最焦虑的是，接下来会发生什么？
pull out the starkkest reaction in you.
激发出你内心最强烈的反应。
[clears throat]
[清嗓子]
&gt;&gt; And the smartest people of our
而我们中最聪明的人
generation have gone to work at Facebook
一代人已经去Facebook工作了。
and Google and whatever and Tik Tok to
还有谷歌，还有TikTok等等
make an algorithm that's going to give
编写一个算法，该算法将给出
you that. That's going to give you the
你就是那个人。这将给你带来
the thing in your feed that's going to
你信息流里即将出现的内容
make you go, "Wow, what?" Like, that's
让你不禁惊呼：“哇，这是什么？”比如，那就是
so out. And two is that even when it's
所以出局了。第二点是，即使当它是
it's not that even when it is just
即使只是
people's thoughts
人们的想法
people go on social media to perform
人们在社交媒体上表演
&gt;&gt; they go on like they are trying to give
他们继续说下去，好像在试图给予什么。
you and I'm trying to do this on social
你和我正在尝试在社交媒体上做这件事
media as well. I don't want to give you
媒体也是如此。我不想给你
any random thought in my head. I'm going
脑海中任何随机的想法。我要去
to specifically give you what I think is
具体来说，我认为……
going to be interesting and what not.
将会很有趣等等。
So, if we view social media as a proxy
所以，如果我们把社交媒体视为一种代理
for the real world, and I think everyone
就现实世界而言，我认为每个人都是如此。
kind of intuitively does, even if they
即使他们
when you say it out loud, you're like,
当你大声说出来的时候，你会觉得：
"No, of course it's not the real world."
“不，这当然不是现实世界。”
But it's easy to assume that when I open
但很容易假设，当我打开时
up Twitter or Facebook or Instagram, I'm
我在Twitter、Facebook或Instagram上。
like, "I I'm just I'm just seeing a
比如，“我只是，我只是看到一个
window into the world." And you're like,
“通往世界的窗口。”然后你会想，
"No, these are people performing for you
不，这些人是在为你表演。
and the smartest minds in the world
以及世界上最聪明的头脑
ordering that performance for what's
订购那场演出是为了什么？
going to give you the most anxiety."
会让你最焦虑。
&gt;&gt; Are you optimistic about the the Western
你对西方持乐观态度吗？
economy, the US economy? I could be
经济，是指美国经济吗？我可能是
optimistic long term and realistic about
长期乐观，务实
what growth means. The reason we tend to
增长的意义。我们倾向于这样做的原因
have growth in the economy and in the
经济增长和
stock market is because it's
股市之所以存在，是因为……
specifically because there's short-term
正是因为存在短期
chaos. So, am I optimistic about the
混乱。那么，我对……持乐观态度吗？
next 30 years? AB: Absolutely. I know
接下来的30年？ AB：完全正确。我知道
that my kids will be living a better
希望我的孩子们能过上更好的生活。
material life than you and I are.
物质生活比你我都要丰富。
They'll have better medicine. They'll
他们会得到更好的医疗服务。他们会
have better technology. They'll have
拥有更先进的技术。他们将拥有
flying cars. whatever it is does that
飞行汽车。无论它是什么，它都会这样做。
but I'm equally confident if not more
但我同样充满信心，甚至更有信心。
confident that the path between now and
确信从现在到
then is going to be chaos and that's not
那样的话就会一片混乱，那可就糟了。
exclus mutually exclusive like the fact
互斥的，例如事实
that I know I'm extremely confident that
我知道我非常有信心
there's going to be a lot of growth and
将会有很大的增长，
that it's going to be a constant chain
这将是一个持续不断的连锁反应
of setback and suffering and misery
挫折、苦难和悲惨
between now and then.
从现在到那时之间。
&gt;&gt; Is there anything that you see it
你看到什么了吗？
creating a setback? I mean there's these
造成挫折？我的意思是，有这些
new protagonists in the story. There's
故事中的新主角。有
AI. There's um the declining birth rates
人工智能。还有出生率下降的问题。
which is going to have an impact on the
这将对……产生影响
population. Is there anything that you
人口。你有什么想说的吗？
think is your most focus? There's
你认为你最关注的是什么？有
tariffs as well. Um there's Trump
关税也包括在内。嗯，还有特朗普
economics which can cause some
经济因素可能会导致一些问题
instability.
不稳定。
&gt;&gt; Historically, the biggest risk by far
从历史上看，最大的风险莫过于此。
has always been the thing that nobody's
一直以来，这都是没人知道的事情。
talking about. So when we sur you and I
谈论。所以当我们确定你和我
survey the world today, we talk about
纵观当今世界，我们谈论的是
exactly what you just said, tariffs,
正如你刚才所说，关税。
birth rate. People know about those
出生率。人们都知道这些事。
things. There's never been a period when
事物。从来没有过这样一个时期：
the biggest risk was something that was
最大的风险是……
knowable. It's always something like
可知的。总是类似这样
COVID, which nobody saw coming,
新冠疫情，谁也没预料到。
September 11th, which nobody saw coming,
9月11日，谁也没有预料到会发生这样的事。
the Great Depression, like all these
大萧条，就像所有这些一样
things, Pearl Harbor, all these things
珍珠港事件，所有这些事
that were not on people's radar that did
那些不在人们关注范围内的事情
the most damage. And so, it's not that I
损失最大。所以，并不是我
don't worry about tariffs or that I
别担心关税或者我
don't worry about uh birth rates, I do,
别担心出生率，我倒是挺担心的。
but I would guarantee you that the the
但我可以向你保证，
worst economic story of the next 10
未来十年最糟糕的经济故事
years, the biggest risk is something
多年来，最大的风险在于……
that you and I are not talking about
你我之间并没有谈论的
whatsoever. It's a risk that's going to
任何。这是一个即将发生的风险
come completely out of the blue. That is
完全出乎意料。那是
not in any newspaper. It's not in any
报纸上没有刊登。它不在任何
podcast. That's going to be the biggest
播客。那将是最大的
risk.
风险。
&gt;&gt; Is there a particular chapter in the
是否有某个特定的章节？
psychology of money which was your the
金钱心理学，也就是你的
book that sold I hear almost 10 million
听说那本书卖了将近1000万本。
copies and had a profound impact on my
副本对我产生了深远的影响
life and and my family's life. Is there
我的生活以及我家人的生活。有没有
a particular story or chapter in this
这其中的某个特定故事或章节
book that is your favorite?
你最喜欢的书是什么？
I think the the chapter on reasonable
我认为关于合理性的章节很重要。
versus rational, which to very quickly
与理性相对，这很快就会发生
summarize it is don't pretend like you
总结起来就是别假装你
are purely rational and you're a
完全理性，而你就是
spreadsheet and your financial decisions
电子表格和你的财务决策
have to like make perfect sense.
必须完全合乎逻辑。
Everyone is a little bit flawed, a
每个人都有些缺点，
little bit emotional, different family
有点感伤，不同的家庭
situations, different goals. As long as
情况不同，目标也不同。只要
your financial decisions are merely
你的财务决策仅仅是
reasonable, that's good. And I think a
合理，那就好。而且我认为
lot of people, for me and for a lot of
很多人，对我来说，对很多人来说
people, they're like, "Oh, thank you for
人们会说：“哦，谢谢你。”
giving me permission because I have this
给我这个许可，因为我有这个
quirky thing that I do with my money and
我用钱做的一件古怪的事
it doesn't make any sense, but it's
这完全说不通，但事实就是如此。
reasonable and but it makes sense for my
合理，而且对我来说也说得通。
personality." And like, as long as it's
个性。”而且，只要它是
reasonable, like don't be unreasonable,
要讲道理，不要不讲道理。
but don't think that every one of your
但不要以为你的每一个人都是如此
financial decisions has to add up
财务决策必须合乎逻辑
perfectly in a spreadsheet. You want to
在电子表格中完美呈现。你想要
use money as a tool for a better life.
把金钱当作创造更美好生活的工具。
&gt;&gt; And there's many different ways to do
而且有很多不同的方法可以做到这一点。
that. A lot of which might make sense to
那。其中很多可能都很有道理
me, but not make sense to you or vice
对我来说，但这对你或反之亦然，就毫无意义了。
versa. And so that's fine. And so, uh, I
反之亦然。这样就没问题了。所以，呃，我
I think that to me of just like, hey,
我觉得对我来说，这就像是，嘿，
this is not an exercise in a spreadsheet
这不是电子表格练习。
where I'm just trying to make sure all
我只是想确保一切
the numbers add up. I'm just trying to
数字加起来没错。我只是想
use money to be a little bit happier and
用钱让自己更快乐一点，
to sleep better and to give myself, my
为了睡得更好，为了给自己，我的
family, a little bit of a better life.
家庭，以及更美好的生活。
Even if it doesn't always make sense, is
即使它并非总是合乎逻辑，也是
as a tool to give me a better life.
把它当作一种工具，让我过上更好的生活。
&gt;&gt; If money is a tool for happiness, I
如果金钱是获得幸福的工具，我
guess you have to get really clear,
看来你得把事情说清楚才行。
which you talk about in in your new
你在新书中谈到的
book, The Art of Spending Money. You
书籍：《花钱的艺术》。你
have to get really clear on what your
你必须非常清楚你的
goal is. And I think most of us have
目标是。而且我认为我们大多数人都有
never actually done an exercise to get
实际上从未做过任何练习来获得
clear on that.
这一点很清楚。
&gt;&gt; Yes.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Which is quite shocking.
这真是令人震惊。
&gt;&gt; Jeff Bezos talks about this in a way
杰夫·贝佐斯以某种方式谈到了这一点。
that I think was really profound where
我觉得那真的很有意义。
he's like he thought about building
他好像在考虑建造什么。
Amazon with what he called the regret
亚马逊带着他所谓的遗憾
minimization framework which was he
最小化框架，也就是他
envisioned himself being 90 years old or
他想象自己90岁的样子，或者
whatever on his deathbed and looking
无论如何，在他临终之际，他看起来
back. And he said the goal for life was
后退。他说，人生的目标是
to be on your deathbed and have as few
临终之际，尽可能少地……
regrets as possible. And he said if he
尽可能地感到遗憾。他说如果他
started Amazon and it failed, he would
他创办了亚马逊，但失败了。
not have regretted that. But if he never
我不后悔。但如果他从未
tried to start it, he would regret it.
如果他试图开始，他会后悔的。
And so it was an easy of of course he
所以，这当然很容易。
has to do it because he wants to have as
他必须这样做，因为他想拥有
few regrets as possible. But I just
尽量减少遗憾。但我只是
think that very simple framework of the
认为这个框架非常简单
overarching goal in life. If you have
人生中的总体目标。如果你有
like what is the base of the pyramid for
比如，金字塔的底部是什么？
how to live a good life, you want to
如何过上美好的生活，你想……
have as few regrets as possible. Not
尽量少留下遗憾。不是
take as few risks as you can, just have
尽量减少风险，只要有就行。
as few regrets as possible. I think
尽量减少遗憾。我认为
what's hard is that people by and large
难就难在，大多数人
don't have a good concept of what they
对他们自己没有很好的概念
will regret. It's it's easy to do
我会后悔的。这很容易做到
because a lot of things kind of compound
因为很多事情都会相互叠加。
slowly. So, uh if you eat a poor diet or
慢慢地。所以，呃，如果你饮食不健康或者
if you're like not treating your friends
如果你不喜欢你的朋友，那就太不像话了。
as well as you should, that's like a
你也应该这样做，这就像……
slow thing. You might regret it
慢吞吞的。你可能会后悔。
eventually, but you're going to look
最终，但你会看到的
back, but in real time, you don't really
回来，但实际上，你并不能真正做到。
understand what you're doing. So, to
明白你在做什么。所以，
have a good sense of what you're going
对你要去的地方要有个清晰的认识。
to regret is a difficult thing, but to
后悔是一件难事，但是……
me, that's the ultimate goal in life.
对我而言，那是人生的终极目标。
There is a a you know I I I heard the
你知道，我听到了
story one time of a uh of a guy who his
有一次，讲的是一个男人的故事，他
his his last words on his deathbed were
他临终前说的最后一句话是
so much wasted time. Those are his last
浪费了太多时间。那是他最后的遗物。
words. And I remember thinking like
字。我记得当时我想的是
that's that's that's as worse that's
那就更糟了
that's as bad as it comes to be on your
这已经是你所能遇到的最糟糕的情况了。
deathbed and look back and being like
临终之际，回首往事，感觉就像……
man what a what a regret just filled
天哪，真是后悔莫及。
with regrets of the things you didn't do
后悔那些你没做过的事
of the way that you treated people of
你对待他人的方式
the risks that you didn't take. And so I
你没有承担的风险。所以，我
think that if there's an overarching
想想如果存在一个总体的
philosophy, it's that. And I ask myself
就是哲学。我问自己
a lot like, do I have a good sense of
很像，我对……有很好的感觉吗？
what I'm going to regret? And for every
我会后悔什么？而且对于每一个
decision that I make, do I ask myself,
我做出的决定，我会问自己吗？
will I regret doing or not doing this
我会后悔做或不做这件事吗？
thing? Easier said than done, but it's
事物？说起来容易做起来难，但确实如此。
something I think about a lot.
这是我经常思考的问题。
I think it's generally just hard for us
我觉得这对我们来说通常都很困难。
to appreciate that there will be a
要明白，将来会有一个
future self. I I was reading a study
未来的自己。我当时正在阅读一项研究
where they put people in these MRI
他们把人放在这些核磁共振成像仪里。
scanners and then asked them to think
扫描器，然后让他们思考
about themsel and then a celebrity and
关于他们自己，然后是一位名人，
then themselves in 10 years time and the
然后是他们自己，10年后，以及
when they thought about themselves a
当他们想到自己时
certain part of the brain lit up when
当……时，大脑的某些部分会亮起来。
they thought about a celebrity or
他们想到了某个名人或
themselves in 10 years time a different
十年后，他们会变成另一个人。
part of the brain lit lit up which kind
大脑的哪一部分被点亮了？
of makes [clears throat] you think that
让你觉得[清嗓子]
we don't really our future self is a
我们并不真正了解未来的自己。
stranger.
陌生人。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And so we act and I think this
是的。所以我们采取了行动，我认为这
about the people that I sit here with I
关于和我一起坐在这里的这些人，
think probably most of the people that I
我想我认识的大多数人可能都是这样。
sit here with learning from. If you
坐在这里学习。如果你
could like distill it down to why
或许可以将其提炼为“为什么”。
they're here, it's because they were
他们在这里，是因为他们曾经在这里。
able to think about themselves in 10
能够以10分之一的思维方式思考自己
years time.
几年时间。
&gt;&gt; They were able so they became an athlete
他们有能力，所以就成为了运动员。
and trained or they became a CEO or they
并接受了培训，或者成为了首席执行官，或者他们
became an expert in something. They were
成为某个领域的专家。他们是
able to like think to and they got
他们能够像思考一样思考，并且他们得到了
through the PhD and all the I don't know
攻读博士学位期间以及所有我不知道的事情
just
只是
&gt;&gt; there's a great quote from Jerry
杰瑞有一句很棒的话
Seinfeld. He says self-control is
宋飞正传。他说，自制力是
empathy with your future self. M
对未来的自己抱有同理心。 M
&gt;&gt; it's you [clears throat] are making a
是你（清了清嗓子）在做
decision to either do or not do
决定做还是不做
something today because you have respect
今天发生的事，是因为你值得尊重。
for your future self and you care about
为了未来的自己，你很关心
your future self. You know there's going
未来的自己。你知道会有这么一天
to be a Steven 10 years from now and you
十年后成为史蒂文，而你
want to do something today with
今天想做点什么
compassion for that person 10 years from
十年后，我仍然对那个人抱有同情心。
now.
现在。
&gt;&gt; I'm guessing kids help in some regard
我猜孩子们在某些方面会有所帮助。
because they give you a future
因为它们能给你一个未来
&gt;&gt; to think about. Yeah. Right. something
值得思考。是的。正确的。某物
that's gonna outlive you and you want to
那东西会比你活得更久，而你却想……
teach them something and and you know
教他们一些东西，你知道
push them into becoming someone that's
促使他们成为那样的人
gonna outlive you. So you're you're
我会比你活得更久。所以你是你是
having like by default you're thinking
默认喜欢你正在思考
about something that's going to outlive
关于一些将会超越时间而存在的事物。
yourself. If you've ever worked in a
你自己。如果你曾经在……工作过
startup you already know it's chaos.
创业公司你肯定知道，那肯定一团糟。
It's speed and it is survival. And now
速度决定生存。现在
with AI accelerating everything that
人工智能正在加速一切。
speed has only increased. Startups are
速度只会更快。初创公司是
landing enterprise deals even earlier
更早达成企业交易
than before. But what comes with those
比以前更糟。但随之而来的又是什么呢？
deals is regulatory requirements.
交易符合监管要求。
Something a lot of earlystage businesses
很多早期企业都存在这个问题
aren't equipped to handle. And a sock
不具备处理能力。还有一只袜子
too, if you know what that means, isn't
如果你知道这意味着什么，那也没什么问题。
always enough. When having the right
永远足够。拥有正确的
kind of security is the difference
安全类型不同，这就是区别所在。
between making a deal or breaking a
在达成交易还是破坏交易之间
deal, you need to have a plan in place.
达成交易，你需​​要事先做好计划。
Vanta, who are a sponsor of this
Vanta是本次活动的赞助商之一。
podcast, have an AI and automation
播客，拥有人工智能和自动化
system that makes it easier to meet
使满足需求更容易的系统
buyer expectations in just days. and
买家的期望将在短短几天内实现。和
they continuously monitor your
他们会持续监控你
compliance so any future deals are never
合规性，因此任何未来的交易都不会受到影响。
blocked. With AI changing regulations,
已屏蔽。随着人工智能改变监管规定，
their team knows exactly what's needed
他们的团队非常清楚需要什么。
and when it's needed. And they've built
以及在需要的时候。他们已经建成了
the fastest and easiest path to get you
到达你的最快最简单的途径
there. If you're running a startup and
那里。如果你正在运营一家初创公司，
this appeals to you, you can visit
如果您对此感兴趣，您可以访问
vanta.com/ceo
vanta.com/ceo
and get $1,000 off. That's vanta.com/ceo
立减 1000 美元。那是 vanta.com/ceo
for $1,000 off. AI agents aren't coming.
立减 1000 美元。人工智能代理不会到来。
They are already here. And [snorts]
他们已经到了。然后[嗤之以鼻]
those of you who know how to leverage
你们这些懂得如何利用……的人
them will be the ones that change the
他们将会是改变世界的人。
world. I spent my whole career as an
世界。我整个职业生涯都从事……
entrepreneur regretting the fact that I
企业家后悔我
never learned to code. AI agents
从未学过编程。人工智能代理
completely change this. Now, if you have
彻底改变这一点。现在，如果你有
an idea and you have a tool like Replet,
有了想法，你就能使用像 Replet 这样的工具。
who are a sponsor of this podcast, there
他们是本播客的赞助商。
is nothing stopping you from turning
没有什么能阻止你转身
that idea into reality in a matter of
将这个想法变成现实只需……
minutes. With Replet, you just type in
分钟。使用 Replet，你只需输入
what you want to create and it uses AI
你想创造什么，它就运用了人工智能。
agents to create it for you. And now I'm
代理人为您创建。而现在我是
an investor in the company as well as
该公司的一位投资者，以及
them being a brand sponsor. You can
他们是品牌赞助商。你可以
integrate payment systems or databases
整合支付系统或数据库
or loginins, anything that you can type.
或者登录名，任何你能输入的内容。
Whenever I have an idea for a new
每当我有了新的想法
website or tool or technology or app, I
网站、工具、技术或应用程序，我
go on replicate.com and I type in what I
我访问 replicate.com 网站，然后输入我的内容
want. A new to-do list, a survey form, a
想。一份新的待办事项清单、一份调查表、一份
new personal website. Anything I type, I
新的个人网站。我输入的任何东西，我
can create. So, if you've never tried
可以创造。所以，如果你从未尝试过
this before, do it now. Go to replet.com
之前做过这件事，现在就做。访问 replet.com
and use my code steven for 50% off a
使用我的优惠码 steven 可享 50% 折扣
month of your replicate core plan. You
您的复制核心计划的月份。你
talk in the book about trying new things
书中谈到了尝试新事物
and and why that is. Uh there's a
以及原因。呃，这里有一个
chapter called try something new and I
本章名为“尝试新事物”，我
think a lot of us actually get stuck in
我认为我们很多人实际上都陷入了困境
ruts in life and that ends up we get
生活中的种种困境最终会导致我们陷入停滞不前。
stuck in routine. It's weird how as we
陷入一成不变的日常。很奇怪，当我们
age we like routine more but intuitively
随着年龄增长，我们更喜欢规律的生活，但这种感觉是直觉的。
everyone would say that routine makes
每个人都会说，规律性使人变得……
them
他们
&gt;&gt; boring
无聊的
&gt;&gt; boring less less life less spontaneous
无聊的，更少的生活，更少的自发性
less interesting less or less wonder
趣味性降低，惊奇感减少。
there's that thing people realize this
人们会意识到这一点
that summer vacation when you're 10
你十岁那年的那个暑假
years old seems like it lasts forever
感觉过了好几年，它就永远都不会变。
but when you're an adult summer goes by
但当你长大成人，夏天就过去了。
in 3 seconds and you're like what like
3秒钟之内，你就会想：这是什么？
why does why is time going faster at
为什么时间过得这么快？
least one of the theories for why it
至少有一种理论解释了为什么会这样
seems like time goes faster as you age
随着年龄增长，感觉时间过得更快了。
is because when you're a child every day
那是因为你小时候每天都……
is something new. You're experiencing
这是新事物。您正在经历
something for the first time. It's a
这是第一次。这是一个
constant chain of novelty. When you're
层出不穷的创新。当你
an adult, it's probably the same commute
对成年人来说，通勤时间可能也差不多。
going to the same job, living in the
去同一份工作，住在……
same house, and one day blends into the
同一栋房子，有一天却融入了……
next, and before you know it, 10 years
接下来，不知不觉中，十年就过去了。
has passed. And so, the idea of like
已经过去了。所以，就像……的想法
trying something new, I think, is is is
尝试一些新的东西，我想，就是这样。
important. The point I made in the book
重要的。我在书中提出的观点
about trying something new is you don't
关于尝试新事物，你并不……
know what your thing that you really are
要清楚你真正想要的是什么
going to enjoy in life is. It might not
享受生活就是。可能不会
be intuitive. Some people value travel
要凭直觉行事。有些人重视旅行
by and large. I don't. Some people enjoy
总的来说。我不。有些人喜欢
like spending a ton of money on wine. By
就像花很多钱买酒一样。经过
and large, I don't. But I do spend my
而且，大的我就不觉得大。但我确实花了我的
money on things that you might not
把钱花在你可能不想做的事情上
appreciate. Like everybody's different.
欣赏。每个人都不一样。
You can't. There's no formula for how to
你不能。没有固定的公式可以指导如何
do it. You have to try a million
去做。你得尝试一百万次。
different kinds of spending before
不同类型的支出
you're like, "Oh, I like this. I don't
你会想，“哦，我喜欢这个。我不喜欢。”
like that. I want to focus more on
就是这样。我想更专注于
this." And it's not intuitive what that
这一点。”而且这并不直观。
thing is going to be. My wife and I also
事情将会如何发展。我和我妻子也
had this realization in the last month.
上个月我才意识到这一点。
So many people when they talk and think
很多人在谈话和思考时都会这样。
about money and spending, they're like,
谈到金钱和消费，他们的态度是这样的：
"I want to travel. I want to I want to
我想旅行。我想，我想……
have more money so I can travel." And I
有了更多钱，我就可以去旅行了。”而我
think by and large that's great. Travel
总的来说，我认为这很棒。旅行
is an amazing thing. My wife and I
真是太神奇了。我和我妻子
realized that like I think we've done so
意识到这一点，就像我认为我们已经做到的那样
much of it and because we have kids
很多都是因为我们有孩子。
right now that we're like I don't think
现在我们就像……我觉得……
we enjoy it that much. And it wasn't
我们非常喜欢它。但事实并非如此。
until we were looking at our summer
直到我们开始回顾我们的夏天
schedule that we're like okay we got two
我们安排好日程后，就说“好的，我们有两个”。
more trips coming up that we were like
接下来还有更多旅行，我们就像……
really and we realized the best part of
真的，我们意识到了最棒的部分
the last several trips that we've taken
最近几次旅行我们都去了
is coming home. [laughter] The most
即将回家。 [笑声] 最
enjoyable part of the trip was coming
旅途中最令人愉快的部分即将到来
home. And we were like, can we just
家。我们当时就想，我们能不能就这么
admit that maybe we shouldn't be doing
承认或许我们不应该这样做
this as much as we do.
我们在这方面做得和他们一样多。
&gt;&gt; That's so fun.
真有趣。
&gt;&gt; Even if society tells us that we should
即使社会告诉我们应该
do it and everyone else I travel a lot
去做吧，其他人也一样，我经常旅行。
for work. So like my idea of a vacation
为了工作。所以，这就像我理想中的假期一样。
is not not going on an airplane. And but
不是不坐飞机。但是
you have to realize like everyone's
你必须意识到，就像每个人一样
unique and different. Like if travel is
独特而与众不同。比如，如果旅行是
your thing or someone listening to this,
你的东西，或者正在听这段话的人，
awesome. Please go do it. We had to just
惊人的。请去做吧。我们不得不这样做
admit to ourselves that at least at this
承认这一点，至少在这一点上
phase of our life, we want to do a
在我们人生的这个阶段，我们想做一件事
little bit less of it. The idea that
少一点。这种想法
everyone's different is important.
每个人的独特性都很重要。
&gt;&gt; I think I mean I think exactly that. I
我想，我的意思是，我就是这么想的。我
think what underp underpins much of your
想想你的大部分行为背后的根本原因是什么
message here is this ability to
这里的信息是这种能力
cultivate self-awareness.
培养自我意识。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And I think a lot of what throws
是的。我认为很多因素都会导致这种情况
people off with money is chasing a
带着钱逃跑的人正在追逐
lifestyle that is right for somebody
适合某人的生活方式
else but not right for them. And that it
除此之外，其他方面都不适合他们。就是这样
can be very a hard thing to do because
这可能是一件非常困难的事情，因为
you're like, man, this person over here,
你会想，天哪，这个人……
he's working this hard and and she has
他如此努力工作，而她也……
this house and they're living this
他们就住在这栋房子里。
lifestyle and it looks like they're
生活方式，而且看起来他们
pretty happy. And then you try to do it
挺高兴的。然后你尝试去做。
and you're like, but I'm not happy. And
你会想，但我并不开心。和
the truth may have been that working
真相或许是，工作
that hard and spending money on that was
那很困难，而且把钱花在那上面是
right for that person, but it's not
对那个人来说是合适的，但对其他人来说却不是。
right for you.
适合你。
&gt;&gt; That's what we understand.
我们就是这样理解的。
&gt;&gt; You and I had Jeff Bezos's
你和我都拥有杰夫·贝佐斯的
ambition, Elon Mus's ambition, I think
我认为，埃隆·马斯克的野心，他的野心。
we I I' I'd draw we drive ourselves
我们 我 我 我会画 我们开车我们自己
absolutely crazy. It's right for them,
简直疯了。这对他们来说是正确的。
it might not be right for us.
这或许不适合我们。
&gt;&gt; And so when we view it as it worked for
所以，当我们从这个角度来看待它时，它就奏效了。
them, so I should do it, too. No, no,
他们都这么做了，所以我也应该这么做。不，不
no. It doesn't work like that. You have
不。事情并非如此。你有
to figure it out for yourself.
自己想办法解决。
&gt;&gt; But also the inverse, right? It didn't
但反过来也一样，对吧？没有
work for them, so it won't work for me.
对他们有效，所以对我无效。
is also incorrect,
也是不正确的。
&gt;&gt; right? I think it's immature for people
正确的？我认为这对人们来说是不成熟的。
to say, I like this thing and therefore
也就是说，我喜欢这个东西，因此
you should too.
你也应该这样做。
&gt;&gt; Or the reverse, this didn't work for me
反过来说，这种方法对我不起作用。
and therefore nobody should do it.
因此，任何人都不应该这样做。
&gt;&gt; This is the whole work life balance.
这就是工作与生活平衡的全部意义。
&gt;&gt; That's not how life works. Right. Right.
生活并非如此。正确的。正确的。
&gt;&gt; And this is what you see raging on
这就是你现在看到的肆虐景象。
LinkedIn is one group of people saying
LinkedIn 上的一群人表示
that amount of work and sacrifice is
那样的工作量和牺牲是
toxic.
有毒的。
&gt;&gt; You should do it or or which is you're
你应该这样做，或者说，这就是你的……
lazy.
懒惰的。
&gt;&gt; You have you have to hustle. You're lazy
你必须努力拼搏。你很懒
if you don't live the life that I do.
如果你没有过上和我一样的生活。
&gt;&gt; And both sides are wrong.
双方都错了。
&gt;&gt; Yes. It comes from a sense of immaturity
是的。这源于一种不成熟感。
that everyone else should enjoy life in
让其他人都能享受生活
the exact same way that I do.
跟我做的一模一样。
&gt;&gt; I think there's a few psych
我觉得有一些心理学方面的问题。
psychological forces at play here. One
这里存在心理因素在起作用。一
is
是
if you're looking at a bunch of people
如果你正在观察一群人
working really hard and you're not, it's
你明明很努力，却没做到，这是……
in a weird way holding a mirror up to
以一种奇怪的方式举起镜子
you and implicitly sort of like
你，还有那种隐含的、类似的感觉
indirectly saying that you're not
间接表明你不是
enough.
足够的。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And then maybe on the other side there's
然后，也许在另一边还有……
some other force going the other way.
还有其他力量在朝相反的方向作用。
But I think both sides are kind of like
但我认为双方都有点像……
misunderstanding
误解
that everybody is not them.
不是每个人都和他们一样。
&gt;&gt; Yes. And I can pick apart elements of
是的。我可以仔细分析以下各个方面：
your life and say, "Wow, Stephen, his
你的生活，然后说，“哇，斯蒂芬，他的
podcast is is this and he's got homes
播客就是这样，他有房子
here and he's doing this." But there's a
他就在这里，正在做这件事。”但是还有
million different components of your
你的数百万个不同组成部分
life and my life and everybody's life
生命，我的生命，以及每个人的生命
that are invisible. And most people
那些看不见的东西。而且大多数人
because of self-preservation or because
因为出于自保，或者因为
they're trying to get ahead in life will
他们试图在生活中取得成功
not disclose what the bad parts of their
没有透露他们不好的方面。
life are. [laughter]
生活就是这样。 [笑声]
Of course, everybody does this. I I do
当然，每个人都会这样做。我愿意
this, you probably do it. Everyone does
这件事，你大概也会做。大家都这么做
that because either they don't want to
那是因为要么他们不想……
admit them to themselves or they don't
他们要么承认自己有这些想法，要么就不承认。
want to talk about it because they think
他们想谈论这件事，因为他们认为
other people are going to judge them for
其他人会因此评判他们。
the bad parts of their life. So, it's
他们生活中糟糕的部分。所以，就是这样。
very easy to look at other people's
查看别人的非常容易
lives and have a sense of like, oh,
生活，并有一种感觉，哦，
well, theirs is better than mine because
嗯，他们的比我的好，因为
all you can see is what they are
你只能看到它们是什么。
advertising.
广告。
And uh and and and because of that, it's
正因如此，所以……
very easy to be jealous or envious of
很容易产生嫉妒或羡慕之情。
people and say, "If only I had their
人们会说：“如果我能拥有他们的……”
life, things would be better." And part
生活会变得更好。”以及一部分
of it is good. It's part of is good for
这是好事。这是其中的一部分，对……有好处
me to look at be like, man, Stephen's
我看着他，心想，天哪，斯蒂芬的
[clears throat] been so successful doing
[清嗓子] 一直以来都非常成功
this kind of content. Maybe I should do
这类内容。或许我应该这样做
that's motivation. But once I say
这就是动力。但一旦我说
their life looks better than mine, and
他们的生活看起来比我的好，而且
if only I had what they had, I would be
如果我拥有他们所拥有的，我就会……
happier is is a very treacherous path,
追求快乐是一条充满荆棘的道路。
treacherous path to go down.
这是一条充满危险的道路。
&gt;&gt; Jack is the producer on the show. He's
杰克是该节目的制片人。他是
he's done the show with me since the the
从那时起，他就一直和我一起主持这个节目。
very beginning of us launching on
我们启动之初就……
YouTube. And so he understands the
YouTube。所以他明白了
intricacies of my life very well. He
我对自己生活中的种种复杂情况都非常了解。他
understands my business. He understands,
了解我的业务。他明白了。
you know, the this what it takes and the
你知道，这就是成功所需的条件。
trade-offs. So, Jack,
权衡取舍。杰克，
would you want my life?
你想要过我这样的生活吗？
&gt;&gt; Absolutely not. [laughter]
绝对不是。 [笑声]
&gt;&gt; No hesitation there.
毫不犹豫。
&gt;&gt; There's there's no world where like I
没有哪个世界像我一样
could even imagine being in your world.
甚至可以想象自己置身于你的世界。
The amount of people that are bidding
参与竞标的人数
for your attention on a daily basis is
每天需要您关注的是
mind-blowing to me. the podcast is like
这让我感到难以置信。这个播客就像
such a huge part of your life, but the
这是你生命中非常重要的一部分，但是
fact that I barely hear from you on like
事实上，我几乎没收到你的任何消息。
a weekly basis can probably put into a
每周可能可以投入到
little bit of perspective how much you
稍微换个角度想想，你有多……
have on your plate. I just like couldn't
你盘子里有什么？我就是做不到
imagine having the magnifying glass on
想象一下把放大镜对准……
me that much
对我来说就是这样
&gt;&gt; that the whole world is kind of looking
全世界似乎都在关注着
at me and thinking like has an opinion
看着我，好像在想什么似的。
on you.
在你身上。
&gt;&gt; Mhm. [clears throat]
嗯。 [清嗓子]
&gt;&gt; And you run lots of businesses, so you
而且你经营着很多企业，所以你
almost have to perform a little bit. And
几乎都要表演一下。和
I think I see the worst of you and I
我觉得我看到了你最糟糕的一面，而我
actually take that a huge compliment
实际上，这算是莫大的赞美。
because you can be yourself around me. I
因为在我面前你可以做真实的自己。我
remember the time when you had to
还记得你不得不……的时候吗？
schedule your lunch.
安排好你的午餐时间。
&gt;&gt; Oh, I still schedule my lunch. It
哦，我还是会安排午餐时间。它
doesn't happen but I schedule it.
虽然没发生，但我还是安排了。
&gt;&gt; You schedule it cuz you like don't get
你安排它是因为你不喜欢
time for your lunch.
该吃午饭了。
&gt;&gt; Like you went out of here, you went to
就像你离开了这里，你去了
the toilet and people are asking you
厕所里有人问你
questions in between going from here to
从这里到那里的中间问题
the toilet. It's stuff that needs to be
厕所。这是需要做的事情
asked, but it's that is your life.
你问了，但这就是你的人生。
That's the kind of thing that you've um
这就是你……
gone into.
进入。
&gt;&gt; And I don't know if that kind of answers
我不知道这种答案是否可行。
your question. I could probably go on
你的问题。我大概还能继续说下去。
for a long long time, but
很长很长一段时间，但是
&gt;&gt; you should do a whole episode [laughter]
你应该做一整集节目[笑声]
to do
要做
&gt;&gt; I've got last question then. So I have
那我最后一个问题了。所以我有
two more questions. The next question is
还有两个问题。下一个问题是：
do you think that I do you think I'm
你觉得我……你觉得我是……
happy in my life?
我的生活幸福吗？
&gt;&gt; Uh yes. I don't think you're content.
嗯，是的。我觉得你并不满足。
&gt;&gt; I think you're happy, but I don't think
我觉得你很开心，但我并不这么认为
you're content.
你很满足。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And what do you mean by content? Like
你说的“内容”指的是什么？喜欢
what do you mean by content? you're
你说的“内容”指的是什么？你是
always trying to chase the next thing
总是试图追逐下一个目标
and I'm not sure why. Like you could so
我也不确定原因。就像你可以这样
easily just do this podcast and it would
做这个播客就很容易了，而且
do so well for you. Like it does do so
对你来说真是太好了。就像它确实会这样做一样
well for you. Uh you could spend all
那对你来说真是太好了。呃，你可以花光所有
your time doing this and I think you're
你花时间做这件事，我认为你是
super happy when you do do this. But
你这样做我真的非常开心。但
then there's also other stuff that
此外还有其他一些东西……
clearly makes you happy that you want to
显然，你想要的东西会让你感到快乐
do, but then you'll come to me and
去做吧，但之后你会来找我，
you're like, "We should start this new
你会想，“我们应该开始这项新的工作。”
YouTube channel."
YouTube频道。
And I'm kind of like, yeah, great idea,
我当时就想，嗯，好主意。
but I don't know why you want that extra
但我不知道你为什么想要那额外的费用。
effort. To your core, you're a
努力。从本质上讲，你是一个
businessman, so you're constantly trying
你是商人，所以你一直在尝试
to build and scale, but on like a
为了建设和扩展，但就像……
personal reflection of how much extra
个人反思额外投入了多少
toll that takes on you. And also for
这会给你带来怎样的代价。而且也为了
Mel, I know your relationship with Mel,
梅尔，我知道你和梅尔的关系。
you don't see her that much.
你不太常见到她。
So, I think that's quite an interesting
所以，我觉得这很有意思。
one. But yes, I do think you're happy,
一。是的，我觉得你很幸福。
but I don't think you're content.
但我认为你并不满足。
&gt;&gt; And last question, what would you like
最后一个问题，你想要什么？
from my life?
从我的生活中？
&gt;&gt; What would I like from your life?
我希望你的生活是什么样的？
&gt;&gt; Yeah. So you said you wouldn't want my
是的。所以你说你不会想要我的
you wouldn't want my life because and
你不会想要我这样的生活，因为……
you talked about the downsides.
你谈到了缺点。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. What elements of Yeah. of my life
是的。 “是的”有哪些要素？我的生活
would you like?
你想要吗？
&gt;&gt; That's actually quite interesting cuz I
这其实挺有意思的，因为我
was I think I was talking to Jem and
我想我当时是在和杰姆说话。
Cozy about this last night. Your life is
昨晚感觉很温馨。你的生命是
so engineered to be super efficient.
经过精心设计，效率极高。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; So you have someone books your cars for
所以你会找人帮你预订车辆。
you, someone books your flights for you.
你，或者有人帮你预订机票。
You you basically, as far as I'm aware,
基本上，据我所知，你就是……
I don't think you do much kind of normal
我觉得你做的并不怎么正常。
admin that I would do.
我会做的管理员工作。
&gt;&gt; No. [laughter] I don't even pick what I
不。[笑声] 我甚至都不挑选我
eat.
吃。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. Exactly.
是的。确切地。
&gt;&gt; I like I get the surprise. I walk out
我喜欢惊喜。我走出去
here and it's there and I go, "Okay,
这里，那里，然后我就说：“好吧，
well, I'm having broccoli today."
嗯，我今天吃西兰花。
[laughter]
[笑声]
&gt;&gt; And I think so much of like the joys of
我觉得这其中有很多乐趣……
what comes from life is the little
生活中的一切都源于小事
messiness of life.
生活的混乱。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And I actually think Morgan kind of
而且我觉得摩根其实挺……
touched on this at the start, that
开头就提到过这一点，
simple kind of family that just they're
一个简单的家庭，他们就是这样。
not like super ambitious, but they're
虽然他们并非雄心勃勃，但他们……
super happy. Like that messiness of life
超级开心。就像生活的那种混乱。
is kind of there's so much like beauty
感觉就像有很多东西都像美一样。
in that. I know you asked me what you
在这方面。我知道你问过我你
would want from your life, but I think
你会希望你的生活是怎样的，但我认为
on the surface I probably would like
表面上我可能喜欢
that stuff, but I understand and
那些事，但我理解。
appreciate the beauty of doing those. I
欣赏做这些事情的美好之处。我
ask the question around um
问问关于嗯的问题
[clears throat] um do you think I'm
[清嗓子] 嗯，你觉得我是
happy? Because
快乐的？因为
even though you heard all of that stuff
即使你听到了所有这些话
and you go, "Fuck me, this guy like he
然后你会想，“操，这家伙就像……”
he doesn't have much time and he's he's
他时间不多，而且他……
always working and like we took a toilet
一直都在工作，就像我们上厕所一样。
break, which the audience probably won't
打破常规，观众可能不会这么做。
know, but yeah, as I walked out of
我知道，但是，是的，当我走出去的时候
there, two different team members came
那里，来了两名不同的团队成员。
up to two different issues. They said
最多两个不同的问题。他们说
someone wants to come on the podcast
有人想来参加播客节目。
tonight. I've got this huge meeting in
今晚。我有个很重要的会议要开。
New York City tonight with this major
今晚纽约市将迎来这场重大事件。
investor for 4 hours. That then they
投资者投入了4个小时。然后他们
asked me in the hallway. They said, "Do
他在走廊里问我。他们说：“做
you want this major guest to come on the
你想邀请这位重量级嘉宾来参加
show tonight or to cancel this huge
今晚的演出还是取消这场盛大的演出？
meeting with this investor? You
与这位投资人会面？你
&gt;&gt; need to make the decision in 4 seconds."
需要在4秒钟内做出决定。
&gt;&gt; 4 seconds. So you saw me sit down and go
4秒。所以你看到我坐下来走了
tell the team yes.
告诉团队“好的”。
&gt;&gt; I did.
我做了。
&gt;&gt; Which was me making that executive
那就是我担任那个高管的职位。
decision. I was on my phone for two and
决定。我玩手机玩了两个小时，
a half seconds trying to make the
半秒钟试图……
decision. But it also means that date
决定。但这也意味着日期
night is if impacted with my girlfriend
如果晚上受到我女朋友的影响，那就是夜晚了。
who's so like that that was a little
谁会那样啊，这有点……
representation of my life. And I I um I
我人生的写照。我，嗯，我
asked Jack if he thinks I'm happy
我问杰克他是否觉得我快乐。
because my opinion
因为我的观点
and I could be living in a delusion is
我可能一直生活在幻想中。
that I am happy and I the way that I
我很快乐，我喜欢我的方式
would hazard a guess that I'm happy is I
我猜想，如果我……，我会很开心。
am not unhappy and I don't have
我并不感到不快乐，我也没有
unhappiness.
不快乐。
My guess too is that you if you said I'm
我的猜测也是，如果你说我是……
going to quit the podcast, quit all
我要退出播客，退出一切。
this, close the business down, you would
这样的话，关门大吉，你就会……
be beside yourself with anxiety and
焦虑得几乎无法自拔
depression.
沮丧。
&gt;&gt; And so it's less about like is doing
所以，关键不在于它是否在做某事。
this, does doing this make you happy? I
这样做会让你快乐吗？我
think the better answer is not doing
我认为更好的办法是不做。
this would make you miserable.
这会让你很痛苦。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; But that's who you are and that's how
但这就是你，这就是你
and I again I'm so grateful that people
我再次由衷地感谢大家。
like you exist because I get to benefit
你的存在就像是因为我受益而来的。
from the sacrifices that you made.
源于你们所作出的牺牲。
&gt;&gt; It's not a sacrifice to me.
对我来说，这不是牺牲。
Yes, I I I I get that. But what from my
是的，我明白了。但是，我的呢？
perspective would be a sacrifice I get
换个角度看问题，我明白这是一种牺牲。
to benefit from because you make great
从中受益，因为你做得非常棒
content that I listen to and whatnot.
我听的内容等等。
&gt;&gt; And so I like living in a world where
所以我喜欢生活在这样一个世界里
most people wake up in the morning and
大多数人早上醒来，
say this isn't enough.
说这还不够。
&gt;&gt; And I I I think I do that too. I want to
而且我觉得我也会这样做。我想要
write more books, better books, and but
多写书，写更好的书，但是
if you don't have some capacity to say,
如果你没有能力表达自己的想法，
look, I have ambitions. I have goals
你看，我也有抱负。我有目标
that I want to achieve. I want to work
我想要达成的目标。我想工作
hard to achieve those. I want to
这些目标很难实现。我想要
sacrifice to achieve those, but I'm
为了实现这些目标需要做出牺牲，但我
never going to have a good life unless I
除非我
can take a step back and be like, man,
可以退后一步，然后想，唉，
like look what I have right now, even if
看看我现在拥有什么，即使
it's not that much. There's a very good
没那么多。有一个非常好的
book written by a gerontologist named
一本由一位名叫……的老年学家撰写的书
Carl Pillmer. He wrote a book called 30
卡尔·皮尔默。他写了一本书，名为《30》。
lessons for living where he interviewed
他接受采访时分享的生活经验。
a bunch of elderly Americans who were
一群年长的美国人，他们
like 90 to 100 years old. And he just
大概有90到100岁了。他只是
said, "Tell me the secret to a good
他说：“告诉我好成绩的秘诀。”
life. You've experienced a lot of life.
生活。你经历了很多人生百态。
Tell me what you know."
告诉我你知道些什么。
And he has a section where he says, "Of
他在其中一个章节中写道：“关于
the thousand people who we interviewed,
我们采访了一千多人，
not a single person looking back at
没有一个人回头看。
their life said,"I wish I made more
他们的生活仿佛在说：“我希望我能做得更多。”
money."
钱。”
&gt;&gt; Not a single person said, "I wish I
没有一个人说：“我希望我
would picked a career that paid more
会选择一份收入更高的职业
money." Not one, but almost every single
钱。”不是一个，而是几乎每一个
one of them looking back at their life
其中一人回顾了自己的人生
said, "I wish I was nicer to people. I
他说：“我希望我能对别人更友善一些。”
wish I was more helpful to my friends. I
我希望我能对朋友们更有帮助。我
wish I spent more time with my family."
我真希望我能多花些时间陪伴家人。
That was universal. So, if you want to
这是普遍现象。所以，如果你想
talk about like regrets, what are we
谈论后悔之类的事情，我们到底是什么？
most likely what are you and I most
你和我最有可能是什么
likely to regret when we're 90? It's not
到了90岁可能会后悔吗？它不是
making more money. It's spending time
赚更多钱。这是在花时间
with the people around us that we love
和我们身边我们所爱的人在一起
and appreciate.
并心存感激。
&gt;&gt; I find myself switching between states
我发现自己会在各种状态之间切换。
and sometimes it's because of a thought,
有时，这只是因为一个念头。
but I find myself switching between
但我发现自己会在两者之间切换
these states of being like in a moment
这些状态就像瞬间一样
and a in in a mode of gratitude. So last
并怀着感恩之心。所以最后
night I did the Jimmy Fallon show here
昨晚我在这里参加了吉米·法伦秀。
in New York. My team were there. It was
在纽约。我的团队当时都在现场。那是
this really wonderful moment. My, you
这是一个多么美好的时刻。我的天哪，你
know, I woke up this morning feeling
我知道，我今天早上醒来的时候感觉
incredibly grateful. Last night I was
无比感激。昨晚我
like listening to some of my favorite
就像听我最喜欢的一些歌一样
music. I felt incredibly grateful and
音乐。我感到无比感激，
really happy. And then I know that I'm
非常开心。然后我知道我是
gonna switch into the lack of
即将转向缺乏
contentment that Jack's referring to.
杰克所指的那种满足感。
&gt;&gt; Happiness is always a five minute
幸福总是短短五分钟。
emotion.
情感。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And and like today I'm I'm back to
是的。就像今天一样，我又回来了。
business and it's like build build bill
商业，就像建设法案一样。
build. And then I have this moment last
建造。然后，我还有最后这一刻。
night where I was I was making the
那天晚上，我所在的地方，我正在制作
Instagram post to announce that I've
在 Instagram 上发帖宣布我已经
been on Jimmy Fallon and I noticed my
我上过吉米·法伦的节目，我注意到我的
girlfriend next to me in bed had fallen
睡在我旁边的女朋友摔倒了
asleep. And this thought comes through
睡着了。这个想法由此而来。
my head all the time now, probably from
我现在一直都在想这件事，可能是因为
doing this podcast, which is exactly
做这个播客，正是如此。
what you said, which is
你刚才说的，就是
&gt;&gt; I am going to regret not spooning her
我会后悔没和她依偎在一起的。
and cuddling her while I have the
我抱着她，同时……
chance, especially I think cuz Charlie
机会，尤其是我认为是因为查理
Kirk had just been shot and I'd seen her
柯克刚刚中枪，我亲眼看到了她。
his family. Yeah. Maybe that's why it
他的家人。是的。也许这就是原因吧
was front of mind for me. And I remember
这件事一直萦绕在我心头。我还记得
putting the phone down and thinking
放下手机，开始思考
&gt;&gt; the thing I'm going to regret is not
我最后悔的不是
cuddling her.
拥抱她。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And so I put the phone down and cuddled
于是我放下手机，依偎在一起。
cuddled her. And so, yeah, I I I'm I'm
拥抱了她。所以，是的，我，我，我，我
strange, I think, because I I I flock
我觉得很奇怪，因为我成群结队
between these states and sometimes on an
在这些州之间，有时在
hourly basis, sometimes on a daily
按小时计算，有时按天计算
basis, sometimes on like a
以……为基础，有时就像……
minute-by-minute basis.
逐分钟进行。
&gt;&gt; The fact that you're just merely aware
你仅仅是意识到这一点而已。
of those states
这些州
&gt;&gt; and the the false story that those
以及那些虚假的故事
states can tell you puts you way ahead
各州可以告诉你，这会让你遥遥领先。
of most people. I think that I think to
对大多数人来说。我认为我认为
a some extent that there there's a
在某种程度上，确实存在
there's an interesting book called 10%
有一本很有意思的书，叫做《10%》。
Happier and it's about meditation and
更快乐，这与冥想有关。
[clears throat] the point the title came
[清嗓子] 标题的出现
from everyone's like oh can meditation
大家都在说，哦，冥想可以吗？
change your life and his point was like
改变你的人生，他的观点是这样的
it can make you 10% happier but like
它可以让你快乐10%，但是……
that's pretty cool and I think that's
那太酷了，我觉得那
true for money as well of like can it
对于金钱来说也是如此，就像它可以一样。
completely change your life and turn you
彻底改变你的生活，让你
into a much better person and way
成为一个更好的人，并以更好的方式
happier like I kind of feel like no but
感觉更快乐了，就像我感觉的那样，不，但是
like it can make you 10 maybe 20%
比如它可以让你增加10%到20%的收益。
happier in life I think that's that's
我觉得这样生活更幸福。
probably right but just Being aware of
可能没错，但只是需要注意这一点。
its limitations like is a huge relief. I
它的局限性反而让人松了一口气。我
think I think be like no, if you want a
我觉得应该说不，如果你想要一个
happier life, you're going to have to
想要更幸福的生活，你必须……
find it through your purpose and your
通过你的目标和你的
friends and your family and your health
朋友、家人和你的健康
and your other philosophies of life that
以及你其他的人生哲学
have nothing to do with money. It can
与金钱无关。它可以
help. It can make you 10, 20, maybe 30%
帮助。它可以让你获得 10%、20% 甚至 30% 的收益。
happier, but understanding its
更快乐，但理解它的
limitations and what it's not going to
局限性以及它不会做什么
do for you is pretty important.
对你来说很重要。
That lack of contentment I think I
我认为，这种不满足感……
sometimes feel guilty about because I
有时我会因为这件事感到内疚，因为我
sit with so many people especially like
和很多人坐在一起，尤其喜欢
people that are monks and such and they
那些当僧侣之类的人，他们
tell you that wanting will make you
告诉你，渴望会让你……
despair and make you unsatisfied but I
绝望和不满，但我
find myself as being one of those people
我发现自己也是这些人中的一员。
that you describe that constantly wants
你描述的那种不断想要
to chase and pursue and pursue
追逐、追击、追逐
&gt;&gt; and I think that I do have like am I
我觉得我确实有这种感觉，我是吗？
supposed to feel guilty about that? Is
我应该为此感到内疚吗？是
that something like wrong with me? No, I
是不是我有什么问题？不，我
mean I think that's how humans have
我的意思是，我认为人类就是这样拥有的。
evolved is to because at the core of it
进化是因为其核心在于
is competition. Like where you have that
这是竞争。就像你那里有那样
I think drive everyone has that drive is
我认为每个人都有那种驱动力。
not necessarily because you want to
不一定是因为你想这么做
build another business or build a grow
建立另一项业务或发展壮大
your podcast. It's competition with
你的播客。这是与……的竞争
others who might be doing that better
其他人可能做得更好
than you or who might take your place if
比你或可能取代你位置的人更甚
you were to step back that gives you the
你应该后退一步，这样你就能……
anxiety. I think that's what everything
焦虑。我觉得这就是一切的意义所在。
has as its core. And that's why I like
以……为核心。这就是我喜欢它的原因
asking the question, if nobody was
问这个问题，如果没有人……
watching, what would you want to do? If
看着这些，你会想做什么？如果
nobody was watching your podcast,
没人听你的播客。
would you still want to do these
你还想做这些吗？
interviews?
面试？
If nobody could see your house, would
如果没人能看到你的房子，会怎么样？
you still would you buy a house that was
你还会买那栋房子吗？
as big as the one you did? Sometimes the
跟你做的那个一样大吗？有时
answer is yes. The answer might be yes
答案是肯定的。答案可能是肯定的。
to both of those questions. But it's an
这两个问题的答案。但这却是
important question to ask of are you
需要问的重要问题是：你是否……
doing this because it actually fulfills
这样做是因为它确实能达到目的。
you or because you are competing with
你或者因为你正在与……竞争
other people and you think you're
其他人，你认为你是
gaining their attention by doing these
通过这些方式吸引他们的注意力
things.
事物。
&gt;&gt; I think everyone who is answering
我认为所有回答这个问题的人
honestly would say for most of the
说实话，对于大多数……
decisions in their life especially the
他们人生中的决定，尤其是
big ones the answer is both.
对于大的问题，答案是两者都是。
&gt;&gt; Yes. So like choosing Harvard versus the
是的。就像在哈佛和……之间做选择一样。
other university which might have been
其他大学也可能是
better but it's Harvard or buying the
更好，但要么是哈佛，要么是买房。
house where you bought it or that watch
你买那块手表的地方，或者你买那块手表的地方
that you bought or the Apple watch
你买的苹果手表
instead of the whatever.
而不是其他什么东西。
&gt;&gt; And signaling is important. You can't
信号传递非常重要。你不能
just discount it because if you want,
就别管它了，因为如果你愿意的话，
you know, to attract the right the right
你知道，为了吸引合适的人
friends, the right spouse, the right
朋友、合适的伴侣、合适的
employers, there's a signaling aspect. A
对雇主而言，这其中存在信号传递的意味。一个
college degree is signaling. It's not
大学学位是一种标志。它不是
the education you obtained. It's you're
你所接受的教育。是你
showing employee you're giving a signal
向员工发出信号
to an employer that for four years I
对于我工作了四年的雇主，我
showed up and did the material and got
他到场后完成了作业，并且拿到了证书。
the right answers. It's a it's signal
正确答案。这是它的信号
like signaling can be very very
信号传递可以非常非常
important. It's not to discount it, but
重要的。并非要否定它，而是……
there's a right and a wrong kind of
有正确和错误之分。
signaling. There's a right kind of like
信号传导。有一种合适的喜欢
I'm I'm doing this. I'm dressing in a
我正在做这件事。我正在穿……
way and displaying myself and cutting my
方式和展示自己以及剪掉我的
hair in a way that's going to attract
头发以一种会吸引人的方式
the right friends and the right mates,
合适的朋友和合适的伙伴，
the right boyfriend, girlfriend,
合适的男朋友、女朋友
whatever it might be. There's also
不管是什么。还有
signaling of like, I'm going to aspire
发出类似“我要追求”的信号
to buy this car that's a huge pain in
买这辆车真是太麻烦了。
the ass and I actually hate driving, but
我其实很讨厌开车，但是……
I think strangers are going to look at
我认为陌生人会看
me and pay more attention to me. That's
请多关注我。那是
the wrong kind of signaling.
错误的信号传递方式。
&gt;&gt; I think this is the thing that both
我认为这是两者都……
sides misunderstand in the debate is
辩论双方的误解在于
that someone who is a workaholic,
那个人是个工作狂，
believe it or not, can be happy. And
信不信由你，幸福是存在的。和
someone who does no work or works one
不工作的人或只工作一天的人
day a week can be happy.
一周中总有一天会很快乐。
&gt;&gt; And this is like a really difficult
这真的很难
concept for either side to understand
双方都能理解的概念
about the other side. And that's why as
关于另一边。这就是为什么……
well I asked the question about Jack
我问了关于杰克的问题。
like do you think I'm happy? Because
你觉得我快乐吗？因为
Jack would know that if I'm like if I
杰克会知道，如果我像我一样
walk out of here and he sees me as this
我走出这里，他看到的我就是这样。
depressed person who never smiles, never
抑郁的人从不微笑，从不
laughs and has no joy in my life,
笑声，却给我的生活带来了毫无快乐。
doesn't have mo, you know, then I would
如果没有更多，你知道，那我就会
very much fit the stereotype of like the
非常符合人们对这类人的刻板印象
tortured work or whatever. But it's uh
痛苦的工作或其他什么。但是呃
yeah, it's surprising. It's surprising.
是啊，真令人惊讶。这很令人惊讶。
&gt;&gt; I think we all just want contentment. So
我认为我们都只是想要满足。所以
like we I think we get into a lot of
就像我们一样，我认为我们陷入了很多……
trouble when we chase happiness when
当我们追求幸福时，麻烦就来了
what we're actually going for is
我们真正想要的是
contentment. We actually just want to
满意。我们其实只是想
get to an area where we're like, I'm
到了某种程度，我们就像，我是
good. I'm all set.
好的。我准备好了。
&gt;&gt; What's the most important thing or the
最重要的是什么？
most interesting thing in your book that
你书中最为有趣的部分是
you can remember that we didn't talk
你应该记得我们当时没说话。
about that maybe we should have talked
或许我们应该谈谈这件事。
about?
关于？
&gt;&gt; I think the relationship between money
我认为金钱之间的关系
and kids is is a is an interesting one
孩子们是一个有趣的人
where every parent wants to use their
每个家长都想使用他们的
hard work. What money they might have.
努力工作。他们可能有多少钱。
It doesn't have to be a ton. You don't
不必很多。你没有
have to be rich, but they want to use
他们必须富有，但他们想使用
their hard work in order to give their
他们辛勤工作，为了奉献他们的
kids a better life. When a lot of times
让孩子们过上更好的生活。很多时候
what the kid needs to do is learn on
孩子需要做的就是学习……
their own. and they're going to learn
他们自己的。他们会学到
vicariously the values that you have
间接地，你所拥有的价值观
about money. They're going to learn just
关于金钱。他们会学到……
by watching. You don't need to sit your
通过观看。你不需要坐着
kids down and say, "Let me teach you how
孩子们下来，说：“让我教你如何……”
to budget. Let me teach you how to save.
纳入预算。让我来教你如何存钱。
Let me teach you how to invest." They're
让我来教你如何投资。
going to figure they're going to watch
我猜他们会看的。
you and figure it out. And so, you have
你自己想办法解决。所以，你拥有
to just lead by example with those kids.
以身作则，给孩子们树立榜样。
You cannot lecture values into them.
你不能对他们进行价值观说教。
They're just going to watch how you
他们只会观察你如何行动。
spend, what you value, how you save, how
消费习惯、价值观、储蓄方式
you judge other people and talk about
你评判他人并谈论
other people, and they're going to form
其他人，他们将会形成
a philosophy of money based off of that.
基于此而形成的金钱哲学。
I often think about money in terms of
我经常从以下角度思考金钱问题：
like attachment styles. You know, in
例如附件样式。你知道，在
like dating psychology and romance, they
就像约会心理学和浪漫爱情一样，他们
talk about anxious, avoidant, um, and
谈谈焦虑型、回避型、嗯，还有
then [clears throat] the what's the
然后[清嗓子]什么？
middle person called? They're like a
中间人打过电话吗？它们就像……
basically neutral. But I think I had an
基本中立。但我认为我曾经有过
avoidant money attachment style. I think
回避型金钱依恋模式。我认为
money was the like the third parent in
金钱就像是第三个父母。
my household. And I learned that money
我家。我了解到金钱
causes problems. That it doesn't come
会造成问题。它不会来
around as much as we would like. That
想待多久就待多久。那
it's really why we argue in the
这就是我们争论的真正原因。
household. That it's the reason why I am
家庭。这就是我存在的原因
embarrassed when we pull up in that
当我们开着那辆车停下来时，感觉很尴尬。
terrible car. And I try and get my I
糟糕的车。我努力得到我的
hope the traffic lights change in a
希望交通信号灯在某个时候会改变。
certain way so that I can be dropped off
以某种方式下车，这样我就可以下车了。
further away from the school so no one
离学校更远，所以没有人
sees me. Like my relationship with money
看见我了。就像我和金钱的关系一样。
was established at such a young age. And
成立时间如此之早。和
it was it's almost like a I had like a
感觉就像我曾经有过……
unhealthy like they say relationship.
就像他们说的那样，一段不健康的关系。
Yeah. like an attachment style to it.
是的。就像一种依恋方式。
Um, and I just wonder like is that a
嗯，我只是想知道那是不是……
useful frame to think through that you
一个有用的思考框架，可以帮助你理清思路。
have this Yeah. like this romanticesque
有这个。就像这种浪漫主义风格
relationship with this thing and in
与此事物的关系以及在
order to change that you need to
要更改您需要做的。
unlearn the lessons.
忘记那些教训。
I think a lot of like the lessons that
我认为很多人都喜欢这些课程。
we learn about money when we're younger
我们很小的时候就开始学习理财。
are because like I said earlier, it's
因为就像我之前说的，就是这样。
because you when you're young,
因为你年轻的时候，
particularly you're a teenager, you're
尤其是你还是个青少年，你是
in your early 20s, most people in that
二十出头的时候，大多数人都是这样。
situation have very little other skills
这种情况导致我几乎没有其他技能。
to offer the world. Yeah.
为世界奉献。是的。
&gt;&gt; Humor, intelligence. Some some people
幽默，智慧。有些人
more than others, but in that situation,
比其他人更多，但在那种情况下，
you're always going to gravitate towards
你总是会倾向于
if only I had a nicer car when I was
如果我当时有辆更好的车就好了
being dropped off at school, then they
被送到学校后，他们
would pay attention to me. But the truth
会注意到我。但事实
is, if you are the funniest kid in
如果你是家里最有趣的孩子……
class, it doesn't matter if you're
阶级，这并不重要，无论你是
dropped off in a junky car. People still
被塞进一辆破车里。人们仍然
respect you because they're like, "Man,
尊重你，因为他们会说：“伙计，
he's a star of the football team." Like,
他是这支足球队的明星球员。
it's hilarious. Doesn't matter what kind
太搞笑了。什么类型的都无所谓。
of car he's driving. You gain your
他正在驾驶的汽车。你获得了你的
attention and your respect from
您的关注和尊重
something else. But if you're not the
别的什么。但如果你不是
star football player, if you're not
如果你不是明星足球运动员，那你就不是
funny, if you have nothing else to
有趣的是，如果你没有其他事可做的话
offer, then you seek your admiration
然后，你寻求你的赞赏。
through, oh, he's dropped off in an
哦，他已经下车了。
escalade. He's cool. That's where you
凯雷德。他很酷。那就是你的地方
want your attention to come from.
希望你的注意力来自哪里。
&gt;&gt; Is there anything else we should have
还有其他需要补充的吗？
talked about that we haven't talked
我们谈过这件事，但我们还没谈过。
about, Morgan?
关于摩根的事？
For people that are trying to get a grip
对于那些试图掌控局面的人来说
of their life, be happy, make better
在他们的生活中，快乐，变得更好
money choices. To me, like the common
金钱选择。对我来说，就像普通人一样
denominator between all three of those
这三者之间的分母
books that you're holding is the idea
你手里拿着的书就是这种想法。
that we talked about quite a bit on all
我们在所有方面都谈了很多。
the shows we've done together, which is
我们一起做过的节目，就是
that there is no formula for it. And
没有公式可以解决这个问题。和
that's very disheartening for a lot of
这对很多人来说都非常令人沮丧。
people to hear. There's no formula for
人们会听到。没有公式可循
here's what I want you to go out and do,
我希望你出去后做这件事：
which is a lot of what people want out
这正是很多人想要摆脱的。
of content, whether it's a book or
内容，无论是书籍还是
podcast, like just tell me what to do.
播客，就像直接告诉我该怎么做一样。
And the answer is like I I can't because
答案是，我不能，因为
I don't know you and you don't know me.
我不认识你，你也不认识我。
We're all different. But I think that's
我们每个人都不一样。但我认为那是
actually the biggest like relief. That's
实际上，最大的感受就像是如释重负。那是
actually the best news that you don't
实际上，最好的消息就是你不需要
have to follow somebody else's playbook.
必须按照别人的剧本行事。
You can do it your own way. And it's
你可以按照自己的方式去做。而且是
easier to do it your own way when you
当你按照自己的方式去做时，更容易做到
come to terms with the fact that nobody
接受没有人的事实
is paying as much attention to you as
对你给予的关注程度与……
they think they are. You can do it your
他们自认为如此。你可以自己做
own way free of judgment and other
以不受评判和其他方式行事
people, you know, making fun of you or
你知道，人们会取笑你，或者
judging how you're living life because
评判你的生活方式，因为
they're too busy worrying about
他们忙着担心……
themselves. You have to figure out what
他们自己。你必须弄清楚什么
works for you and do it. And that's as
对你有效就去做。就是这样
close as we can get as a formula for
我们能得到的最接近公式的
living a better life. It's funny because
过上更好的生活。这很有趣，因为
the book is called The Art of Spending
这本书名为《消费的艺术》。
Money, but much of the throughine
金钱，但大部分贯穿
throughout the book is really about
整本书其实都在讲……
happiness. And I guess that's really
幸福。我想那真是
what money is for many people
对许多人来说，金钱意味着什么
&gt;&gt; a tool tool. A tool to become happy.
工具工具。获得幸福的工具。
&gt;&gt; I remember when I interviewed Mo Gorda,
我记得我采访莫·戈尔达的时候，
he wrote a book um about happiness. He
他写了一本关于幸福的书。他
said to me a line that's always stayed
他对我说了一句我一直铭记于心的话。
with me. He said, "Happiness is when
与我一起。他说：“幸福就是当……”
your expectations of how your life is
你对生活的期望
supposed to be going are met."
应该去的地方都到了。
&gt;&gt; Yes.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And so with through that lens, I look at
因此，透过这个视角，我审视……
everything. I look at like the food that
一切。我看起来像那种食物
you're given in a restaurant. And if you
你在餐厅里得到的。如果你
expected it to be this and it doesn't
原本以为是这样，结果却不是。
come like that, there's unhappiness.
那样下去，就会有不快乐。
Even if it's like a fivestar a A5 Wagu
即使是像五星级的A5和牛那样的。
steak or whatever.
牛排之类的。
&gt;&gt; Um, and then your relationships, all of
嗯，还有你的人际关系，所有的……
my arguments I've ever had with my
我和我之间发生过的所有争论
girlfriend, all stem back to unmet
女朋友，一切都源于未满足的愿望
expectations.
期望。
&gt;&gt; Expectations. I was saying if if you
期望。我是说，如果你
ride the Amtrak train from like New York
从纽约乘坐美铁列车
to Washington DC, on every train they
前往华盛顿特区，每列火车上都有他们
have what's called the quiet car. And in
拥有一辆所谓的静音车。并且
the quiet car, you're not supposed to
安静的车厢，你不应该
talk at anything above a whisper. No
说话声音不要超过耳语音量。不
phone calls, no talking with your
电话，不跟你说话
friends. It's the quiet car. And people
朋友们。这是一辆安静的车。还有人
go there for peace and quiet and
去那里享受宁静吧
serenity. And the irony is that people
宁静。讽刺的是，人们
are so uptight in there because if if
他们在里面那么紧张，是因为如果如果
they hear one peep out of everyone,
他们听到每个人发出了一声微弱的声音。
they're like, "Would you shut up? WE'RE
他们会说：“你们能不能闭嘴？我们……”
IN THE QUIET CAR." They're so frustrated
在安静的车厢里。”他们感到非常沮丧。
about it because your expectation is,
关于这一点，是因为你的期望是，
"I'm going to get quiet." And if it's
“我要安静下来。”如果是这样的话
[clears throat] anything other than
[清嗓子] 除了……以外的任何事
quiet, you lose your mind. And it's like
安静下来，你会失去理智。就像
at that point, that's when your high
那时，你就处于兴奋状态了。
expectations are actually working
预期确实有效
against you.
反对你。
&gt;&gt; Interesting.
有趣的。
&gt;&gt; And people are actually calmer in the
人们实际上在……中更平静
normal car where there's chaos all
普通的车，到处都是混乱
around them because that's what they
他们围在他们身边，因为那就是他们
expect.
预计。
&gt;&gt; So that's the unhappiness car,
这就是那辆“不快乐之车”。
&gt;&gt; right? You're like your expectations are
正确的？你就像你的期望一样
a debt that has to be repaid.
必须偿还的债务。
&gt;&gt; [snorts]
[嗤笑]
&gt;&gt; That gives us a controllable element to
这给我们提供了一个可控因素
our happiness, doesn't it?
我们的幸福，不是吗？
&gt;&gt; Expectations because your expectations
期望，因为你的期望
are more in your control than things
比起其他事情，你更能掌控它们。
like what the economy or the stock
比如经济形势或股票市场。
market's going to do next. Like I have
接下来市场会如何发展。就像我一样
no nobody has any control of what the
没有人能控制什么。
stock market's going to do next. But you
接下来股市将会如何走势。但是你
have you do have more control over your
你是否对自己的某些方面拥有更多控制权？
expectations of how much money do you
你期望获得多少钱
expect to make next week? What do you
预计下周能到吗？你是什​​么
expect out of the stock market? What do
退出股市？什么
you expect out of your career? What do
你对自己的职业生涯有何期望？什么
you expect out of your spouse? like that
你对配偶有什么期望？就像那样
is more in your control than influencing
比起施加影响，你更能控制它。
other people's behavior.
他人的行为。
&gt;&gt; And this is probably why all these
这大概就是所有这些的原因吧
Eastern traditions talk about gratitude
东方传统谈及感恩
because gratitude is the very
因为感恩就是
realization that expectations I once had
意识到我曾经的期望
are currently being met.
目前已满足这些要求。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And it just even when you start to think
即使当你开始思考的时候，它也会如此。
about dreams you once had that you are
关于你曾经做过的梦，你是
now living out for me it makes me feel
现在，这种生活让我感觉
Yeah. that feeling of contentment. It
是的。那种满足感。它
makes me feel really really good inside.
这让我内心感觉非常好。
So like even yesterday where I took a
就像昨天我去的时候……
moment and I was on the Jimmy Fallon
那一刻，我上了吉米·法伦的节目。
show and it's like this crazy thing to
节目播出后，感觉就像发生了一件疯狂的事
me that I could never have imagined
我从未想象过的自己
someone like me doing and I took a
像我这样的人做了这件事，我接受了
minute to just like think about how far
哪怕只是一分钟，想想有多远
beyond my expectations
超出我的预期
this stuff was.
这东西就是这样。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; It if you feel overwhelmingly good about
如果你感觉非常好
it. You
它。你
&gt;&gt; But the truth was relative if you just
但如果你只是……，那么真相就是相对的。
thought about yesterday
想起昨天的事
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; you expected to go on the Jimmy Fallon
你原本打算上吉米·法伦秀
show. You that that that met your
展示。你满足了你的
expectations for the day. If you looked
对今天的期待。如果你仔细看
at your calendar for the day it was I
查看你的日历，那天是我
need to go to Jimmy Fallon. I need to
需要去吉米·法伦秀。我需要
perform. I need to say the right things.
履行。我需要说些正确的话。
But over the longer scope that's off the
但从长远来看，这就不重要了。
charts of your expectations
你的期望图表
&gt;&gt; and that's the zooming out where we see
这就是我们看到的画面，镜头拉远后可以看到
&gt;&gt; the gratitude you know fills us up
你知道，这份感激之情让我们充满力量。
&gt;&gt; and it's very difficult to say this
这很难说出口。
without sounding ridiculous but you can
虽然听起来有点荒谬，但你可以
even zoom out and be like god I'm so
甚至把镜头拉远，然后心想：天哪，我真是太……
grateful to live in a world with
感恩生活在一个充满爱的世界
antibiotics
抗生素
[laughter] like it sounds crazy because
[笑声]听起来很疯狂，因为
we expect them whenever we take
我们每次都期待它们出现。
penicellin we're like yeah like it's
青霉素，我们就像，是啊，就像是
just a thing that exists but can you
它只是存在的东西，但你能做到吗？
imagine living in a world without that
想象一下生活在一个没有这一切的世界里。
as 99% of humanity did before us like
就像我们之前99%的人类所做的那样
it's it's impossible to think of like
简直无法想象。
the most basic things that we take
我们所采取的最基本的东西
advantage of. But that's where gratitude
优势。但正是在这一点上，感恩之心油然而生。
like you have to zoom out to become more
就像你必须缩小视角才能看得更清楚一样
grateful to these things. And you're not
对此心存感激。而你并非如此。
going to be content until you can
你会一直满足直到你能
exercise that level of gratitude.
培养这种感恩之心。
&gt;&gt; You said something earlier which
你之前说过一些话，
doveetails into this where you said that
这与你刚才说的正好吻合。
um at different levels people will
嗯，不同层次的人会
aspire you know the billionaire wants
你知道亿万富翁想要什么
two billion. And I was reading a study
二十亿。我当时正在阅读一项研究
many years ago that said roughly all the
多年前，这大致说明了一切。
way up the income wealth spectrum people
收入财富等级很高的人
want like three times more than they
他们想要的大概是现在的三倍
have now is what seems like the amount
现在拥有的似乎是这个数额
that's going to keep you happy. So if
那会让你开心的。所以如果
you have $10,000 people are like once I
你有1万美元，人们会说，一旦我
have 20 then I'll be good. If you have
给我20个我就满足了。如果你有
$20 million, people are like, "Ah, 40
2000万美元，人们会说：“啊，40
seems like the right amount." It's
看起来数额合适。
always two or three times what you have.
总是拥有你所拥有的两到三倍。
&gt;&gt; And that's just the intentional creation
而这仅仅是刻意创造而已。
of an expectation gap. It's like
期望差距。就像
creating misery for yourself.
给自己制造痛苦。
&gt;&gt; Yes. It's this idea that like if only I
是的。正是这种想法，就好像如果我……
had a little bit more money, then these
手头稍微宽裕一些的时候，这些
problems that I have, this anxiety, this
我的问题，这种焦虑，这种
unfilled hole that I have will finally
我心中那个未被填补的空洞最终将会被填满。
be filled. And it's a it's a lie we tell
填满。而这是我们编造的谎言。
ourselves, of course.
当然，也包括我们自己。
&gt;&gt; And everyone listening right now has
现在正在收听的每个人都有
that. Everyone has a number in your head
那。每个人脑子里都有一个数字
where you think if I got there,
你觉得如果我到了那里会怎么样？
&gt;&gt; then it'd be I I have that. You have
那么，我就会说，我有那个。你有
that. We all do. And if you and I have
那。我们都一样。如果你和我
met that number, previous versions of
达到该数字，之前的版本
that number, it's the same thing. We're
那个数字，意思是一样的。是
like, okay, but double would be great.
好吧，不过要是能翻倍就更好了。
Double double would be awesome. I met
双份双份就太棒了。我遇到了
someone the other day whose income,
前几天有人提到他的收入，
annual income is almost exactly 2x mine.
他的年收入几乎是我的两倍。
We were being very open with each. He's
我们彼此之间非常坦诚。他是
a good friend of mine. And the instant
我的一位好朋友。瞬间
feeling I had, I didn't say this, but
虽然我没有说出口，但我有这种感觉。
the instant feeling I had was like,
我当时的第一感觉就像是：
okay, if I had that, everything would be
好吧，如果我拥有了那个，一切都会好起来的。
great. And it's it's absurd. We do that
伟大的。这太荒谬了。我们这样做。
all day. And I'm sure if my friend met
一整天。而且我确信，如果我的朋友遇到
someone whose income was 2x of his,
收入是他两倍的人
&gt;&gt; he would be like, "Oh,
他会说：“哦，
&gt;&gt; that's the level. That's the one."
这就是水平。就是它。
&gt;&gt; Because your your overheads go up, but
因为你的运营成本增加了，但是
then your competition comparison group
然后是您的竞争对手比较组
also increases. So you're now poorer in
也随之增加。所以你现在更穷了
a different class of comparison. Like
另一种比较方式。喜欢
Yeah. Your like when you bought that new
是的。就像你买了那件新衣服一样。
house you just bought.
你刚买的房子。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; That must have moved you to a new
那一定让你进入了一个新的阶段。
neighborhood.
邻里。
&gt;&gt; And there's houses in the neighborhood
附近还有一些房子。
nicer than ours.
比我们的好多了。
&gt;&gt; My wife and I talk about that.
我和妻子会谈论这件事。
[laughter] It's absurd. It's absurd.
[笑声] 这太荒谬了。太荒谬了。
Now, I I think I'm I think because I
现在，我觉得我之所以这么想是因为我
write about this stuff, I think I'm a
写写这些东西吧，我觉得我
little bit better at catching myself in
稍微擅长发现自己陷入困境了。
those moments, but I won't pretend that
那些时刻，但我不会假装
I don't have those moments. They're
我没有那种时刻。他们是
almost unavoidable.
几乎无法避免。
&gt;&gt; What has worked for you? Is there
哪些方法对你有效？有没有
anything that has actually worked for
任何真正有效的方法
you in terms of
你在这方面
detaching you from comparison and what
让你摆脱比较和什么
people think? Is there anything at all
人们怎么想？到底还有什么吗？
that's worked?
这样奏效了吗？
&gt;&gt; I like this term humble bubble. I want
我喜欢“谦逊泡沫”这个词。我想
to live in a humble bubble. It has to be
生活在一个简朴的小世界里。必须是
humble because I don't want to live in a
谦逊是因为我不想生活在……
bubble where I don't have empathy for
我无法感同身受的泡沫
other people. I want to take in the
别人。我想吸收
experience of others so I can try to
借鉴他人的经验，以便我能尝试
understand the world that I live in. But
理解我所生活的世界。
I want to live in a bubble in the sense
我想生活在某种意义上的泡沫里。
of like I want my expectations not to
就像我希望我的期望不要……
leave my own house. Easier said than
离开自己的家。说起来容易做起来难
done. But when my expectations don't
完毕。但当我的期望落空时
leave my own house, I'm like I want good
离开自己的家，我就想，我想要好
health for myself. I want happy kids. I
为了我自己的健康。我希望孩子们快乐。我
want a good marriage. And those things
想要一段美满的婚姻。还有那些事
don't leave my roof. Once my
别离开我的屋顶。曾经我的
expectations leave my bubble, my once
期望离开了我的泡泡，我曾经的
once they expand outside of my house,
一旦它们扩散到我家以外的地方，
I'm like, "Oh, look at his house. What?
我当时就想，“哦，看看他的房子。什么？”
It's like I just wanted I always think
就好像我一直都想的那样
about that humble bubble of like the
关于那个不起眼的泡沫，就像
only thing that's going to make me happy
唯一能让我快乐的事情
exists underneath my roof and I know
就在我的屋檐下，我知道
that and as soon as my aspirations are
而且，一旦我的愿望实现
for or leave that I know it's just going
不管怎样，我知道它只是在进行中。
to spin out of control. I I I try to
失控旋转。我 我 我 尝试
think about that a lot. And as I
好好想想这件事。而当我
mentioned before the idea of if nobody
之前提到过，如果没有人
was watching what would I care about?
我当时在看什么？我又会在乎什么呢？
That's that's the most powerful exercise
这就是最有效的锻炼方法。
to me. If nobody could see anything that
大部头书。如果没人能看到任何东西的话
I was doing, what how would I choose to
我当时在想，我该如何选择呢？
live?
居住？
&gt;&gt; I've always wanted to counter um this
我一直想反驳……
point with some thinking, which is but
提出一些思考的观点，但这
if I put myself in a higher status
如果我把自己置于更高的地位
position, I'm going to get more
职位，我将获得更多
opportunities, which means more money,
机会，意味着更多的收入，
which is then going to better allow me
这样就能更好地让我
to focus on utility. Not that that's how
注重实用性。并非就是这样
it ever plays out for anybody.
这种情况对任何人来说都可能发生。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; But the thinking is well actually status
但这种想法实际上很有地位
does equal revenue.
等于收入。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; In a lot of the world
在世界很多地方
&gt;&gt; and revenue can give you independence.
收入可以让你获得独立。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. the the I think that's right. I
是的。我觉得是对的。我
think to many extents that's been my
我觉得在很多方面，那都是我的
goal. How can I be successful in my
目标。我怎样才能在工作中取得成功？
career so that I can make enough money
一份能让我赚到足够钱的职业
to not have to work in the career
不必从事该职业
anymore? Like it's not that stark, but
还有吗？虽然情况并没有那么糟糕，但是
it's kind of like that. The flaw in it
差不多就是这样。它存在的缺陷
&gt;&gt; is that I like writing. You like
我喜欢写作。你喜欢
podcasting
播客
&gt;&gt; and so if we get more successful like I
所以如果我们像我一样取得更大的成功
I'm not I'm not chasing success so that
我不是在追求成功，所以
I can stop doing what I'm doing. I just
我可以停止做我正在做的事情。我只是
want to do things that I enjoy.
我想做自己喜欢的事情。
&gt;&gt; We have a closing tradition where
我们有一个结束仪式的传统，
they'll ask us leaves a question for the
他们会问我们，这会给我们留下一个问题。
next as you know. Um, do you have major
接下来，正如你所知道的。嗯，你有专业吗？
regrets in life? Then it says they prove
人生中有什么遗憾吗？然后它说他们证明了
no real purpose. Do you still have
没有实际目的。你还有吗？
regrets?
后悔吗？
&gt;&gt; Nothing huge.
没什么大事。
There are some regrets. I was thinking
有些遗憾。我在想
about this the other day. My wife and I,
前几天也提到过这件事。我和我的妻子，
we have two kids and we're done having
我们已经有两个孩子了，我们不想再要孩子了。
kids.
孩子们。
&gt;&gt; And there's part of me that's like, what
我内心深处有个声音在想，这到底是怎么回事？
would have life been like if I had four
如果我生了四个孩子，生活会是什么样子？
kids, three kids? we if we done that
三个孩子？如果我们那样做的话
like each both my kids have given me so
我的孩子们都给了我很多。
much meaning and purpose and I wonder
意义和目的很多，我很好奇
what a life would have been like if I
如果我当初选择这条路，我的生活会是什么样子呢？
just had if I had more and I I can't
我刚才想，如果我还有更多的话，但我不能。
imagine having just one kid I can't
想象一下只有一个孩子，我简直无法想象。
imagine just having zero kids but
想象一下，如果一个孩子都没有会怎样。
there's an alternative life in which I
还有另一种生活，在那种生活中，我
had four or five kids and you know life
生了四五个孩子，你知道，生活就是这样。
gets crazy at that point and that's not
那时就变得疯狂了，那不是……
a regret but you realize like once
后悔，但你意识到就像一次
you've kind of closed that door on your
你已经算是把那扇门关上了。
life you're like man what would have
生活就像，伙计，本来会怎样？
life been if I had done it if I had done
如果我做了，人生会怎样？如果我做了
it differently because it's given me
它不一样，因为它给了我
more purpose than anything that I ever
比我以往任何事都更有意义
could have imagined and I could have had
我本可以想象，我也本可以拥有
more and maybe it would have been worse.
如果数量更多，情况或许会更糟。
But I I I wonder what that would have
但我很好奇那会是什么样子。
been. I think it's not until you've
到过。我认为只有当你……
we've chosen to close that door that
我们选择关闭那扇门。
chapter of our life that we're like,
我们人生中的某个阶段，就像这样：
man, what if we had what if I had done
唉，如果我们当初……如果我当初那样做……
it a little bit differently.
略有不同。
&gt;&gt; Do you wish you had frozen embryos?
你是否希望自己拥有冷冻胚胎？
&gt;&gt; No.
不。
&gt;&gt; Because that would have kept the door
因为那样就能保住这扇门了。
open theoretically.
理论上开放。
&gt;&gt; Not really. Because I think there is a
并不真地。因为我认为存在
point of like you want you need youthful
就像你想要的那种感觉，你需要青春活力
energy to be a parent. I I I couldn't
为人父母的精力。我我我做不到
imagine having a newborn at 50 or 60. I
想象一下在50岁或60岁的时候生个新生儿。
just [clears throat] I think you need
清了清嗓子，我觉得你需要
the energy of a 30-year-old or 25 or a
30岁、25岁或更年轻人的精力
30-year-old to do that. And it's not a
30岁就能做到。而且它不是
regret because I'm very satisfied with
后悔是因为我非常满意
the the family that I have now. But it's
我现在拥有的家庭。但它是
one of those things of like you realize
其中一件就是你意识到的事情。
you're there's an infinite number of
你在那里有无穷无尽的
paths your life can go down. And we
你的人生可能会走上哪些道路。我们
could have had no kids. We could have
本来可以没有孩子。我们本可以
had four kids. We chose this path, but
生了四个孩子。我们选择了这条路，但是
it's one of just one. It's one of
它是独一无二的。这是其中之一
multiple paths that it could have gone
它本可以走多条路。
down.
向下。
Morgan, thank you. Thank you for doing
摩根，谢谢你。谢谢你这样做
what you do. You're my favorite author
你做什么。你是我最喜欢的作家
of all time, and I think I've told you
一直以来都是如此，我想我已经跟你说过。
this before, but it's the way that you
以前也这样，但这是你的方式。
write. I find it so unbelievably
写。我觉得这简直难以置信
engaging. You the message within your
引人入胜。你的信息就在你的……之中
book is a profound one. All of your
这是一本意义深远的书。你所有的
books are profound ones, but it's
书籍固然意义深远，但它却是……
actually the way that you tell the
实际上，你讲述的方式
stories. And if anybody's listened to
故事。如果有人听过……
you speak today, they'll understand
你今天说的话，他们会听懂的。
exactly what I mean. Your books are a an
正是我要表达的意思。你的书是……
a mirror of that. Um, the psychology of
那是它的镜像。嗯，心理学
money, as I told you before, is the book
正如我之前告诉你的，金钱就是这本书
that changed my financial life. the one
那改变了我的财务状况。那个
book my brother who's a very smart
给我哥哥写本书，他非常聪明
person told me to re to read and there's
有人让我重新阅读，然后就有了。
no wonder that it's one of the
难怪它是其中之一
bestselling books of all time. I think
史上最畅销的书籍。我认为
it might be the bestselling book of all
它可能是史上最畅销的书。
time in its category. Um and your new
在其类别中的时间。嗯，还有你的新
[clears throat] book The Art of Spending
[清嗓子] 书《消费的艺术》
continues on the same trend. Incredibly
延续了之前的趋势。难以置信
accessible, incredibly engaging,
平易近人，极具吸引力，
incredibly human, but within there
极其人性化，但内心深处
there's a profound lesson that stands
这其中蕴含着一个深刻的教训。
the chance of changing our lives for the
改变我们生活的机会
better. So I highly recommend everybody
更好的。所以我强烈推荐大家
goes and gets this book, The Art of
然后他去买了这本书，《艺术》
Spending Money, which comes out
花钱，就是花钱。
tomorrow,
明天，
&gt;&gt; October 7th.
10月7日。
&gt;&gt; October 7th. So, I'm going to link it
10月7日。所以，我要把它链接起来。
below for anybody that wants to grab a
下面供任何想要获取的人使用
copy of this book. And if you're someone
本书副本。如果你是某人
that does want a happier life, it is a
想要过上更幸福生活的人，这是一个
book about spending, but it's also more
这本书是关于消费的，但它也更……
broadly a book about happiness and
总体而言，这是一本关于幸福的书。
regret. And it tells stories that allow
后悔。它讲述的故事允许
you to make better decisions in your
让你在生活中做出更好的决定
life. And it's through stories, not
生活。而且是通过故事，而不是
through frameworks alone or data that I
仅通过框架或数据
think we're most influenced. And you can
我们认为我们受影响最大。而且你可以
probably relate to this if you're
如果你是……的话，你可能感同身受。
listening to this. You probably have
正在听。你可能已经有了
heard stats before. You probably know
以前听说过这些统计数据。你可能知道
you should save. But it's sometimes
你应该存钱。但有时
hearing real stories from real people
聆听真实人物的真实故事
that stick into your amydala and create
它们会粘附在你的杏仁核上并产生
that behavioral change. And that's
这种行为改变。就是这样。
exactly how Morgan writes. He writes
完全就是摩根的写法。他写道
through the context of great stories
通过精彩的故事来展现
that stand a chance of changing your
有可能改变你的
life. So it's a wonderful, wonderful
生活。所以，这真是太棒了！
book to read and I highly recommend you
这本书值得一读，我强烈推荐。
do.
做。
&gt;&gt; Thanks so much for having me.
非常感谢你们的邀请。
&gt;&gt; Thank you so much, Morgan. Hope to see
非常感谢你，摩根。希望能看到
you again sometime soon.
期待不久后再次见到你。
&gt;&gt; Likewise. [music]
同样地。 [音乐]
[music]
[音乐]